<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>TTIP Q&amp;A – unpacking EU-US trade talks</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/TTIP-Q-and-A-unpacking-EU-US-trade-talks/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Find the answers to all these questions at the link below.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box big-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/201507%20TTIP%20crushes%20democracy.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/201507%20TTIP%20crushes%20democracy.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does TTIP stand for and what is it about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the focus of negotiations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When will a deal be reached?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the environmental risks associated with TTIP?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is ISDS and what is wrong with it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the Commission’s new Investment Court System better than ISDS?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we trust that the European Commission will not weaken EU standards on the environment?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would be the economic advantages of a comprehensive EU-US trade agreement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the Commission as transparent as can be expected during complex and sensitive negotiations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Greenpeace’s alternative to TTIP?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is public resistance to TTIP confined to a radical European minority?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opposition to TTIP might slow its completion, but is a deal inevitable?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would happen if the EU and US failed to agree a deal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is bad news for the EU, is TTIP good news for the US?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is regulatory cooperation and why is it a threat?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is CETA and why do you also oppose it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is Greenpeace anti-trade?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US enforcement of air pollution standards led to the discovery of emissions cheating by Volkswagen. Is this not a perfect example of why Europeans should not be scared of TTIP?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A car that is sold in the EU cannot be sold in the US without being significantly re-engineered to fit different specifications. Why should Americans and Europeans not drive the same cars?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s wrong with rinsing chickens in a water and chlorine bath?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Americans have been growing and eating GM crops for years. Why do you not want GMOs in Europe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the implications of a TTIP agreement on EU energy imports and exports and for renewables?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can individual sectors be excluded from a future TTIP deal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;201602 comprehensive QandA TTIP FINAL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-02-17 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/201507%20TTIP%20crushes%20democracy.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>CETA: MEPs put European Parliament on the wrong side of history</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/CETA-MEPs-put-European-Parliament-on-the-wrong-side-of-history/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Strasbourg/Brussels – Support for the controversial EU-Canada trade and investment protection deal – known as CETA – puts the European Parliament on the wrong side of history, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJJ1SUF2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photos and video&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; of this morning’s protest.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIT7_Web_size.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIT7_Web_size.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Despite today’s vote, the ratification of CETA by all of Europe’s parliaments is still the most unlikely outcome. But the disconnect between MEPs and public concerns over living standards, public health and the environment is another blow to the EU, just when its principles of solidarity and cooperation are most needed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Millions are taking to the streets on both sides of the Atlantic against a rollback of social and environmental rights. Instead of standing up for justice and democracy, too many politicians continue to hand privileges to multinational corporations. Politicians in Europe and elsewhere – especially those who call themselves progressive – should put the public interest before corporate profits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt;                                                                                                                    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament’s support for CETA is likely to clash with the opinions of national and regional parliaments in Europe, when they vote on the trade deal, said Greenpeace. And questions remain over whether CETA can survive the scrutiny of the European Court of Justice. Belgium will seek a ruling on the legality of a controversial system – known as the Investment Court System (ICS) – which allows multinational corporations to sue states under CETA, but not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, protestors in Strasbourg warned that CETA would hand corporations the power to sue governments and threaten laws that protect nature, public health and social rights. Greenpeace activists kept a sinking statue of Lady Justice afloat in the river surrounding the European Parliament and displayed banners reading: &lt;em&gt;“Sink CETA, not justice”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser: +32 (0)477 790 415, &lt;a href="mailto:shira.stanton@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;shira.stanton@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIT7_Web_size.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Activists keep justice afloat as CETA threatens to sink democracy</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Activists-keep-justice-afloat-as-CETA-threatens-to-sink-democracy/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Campaigners warn EU-Canada trade deal is surrender to corporate takeover&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Strasbourg/Brussels – Eleven activists kept a sinking statue of lady justice afloat in the icy waters surrounding the European Parliament in Strasbourg, ahead of a crucial vote on a controversial EU-Canada trade and investment protection deal.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJJ1SUF2"&gt;Photos and video&lt;/a&gt; available for download soon.&lt;br&gt;Activists will stay in the water until the vote.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIRL_Web_size.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIRL_Web_size.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environment, health and labour rights campaigners warn that the deal – known as CETA – would hand corporations the power to sue governments and threatens laws that protect nature, public health and social rights. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The swimmers (from France and Germany), wearing survival suits and supported by activists in three inflatable boats, urged members of the European Parliament (MEPs) to reject the deal and displayed banners in English, French, German and Dutch. The English banner read: &lt;em&gt;“Sink CETA, not justice”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Endorsing CETA plays into the hands of populists and extremists from Europe to North America. And just as the world feels the impact of a corporate takeover in Washington, CETA threatens to undermine democracy and the rule of law in Europe, for the benefit of a handful of multinationals. Elected representatives from each EU country still have a chance to stop this toxic trade deal and take a stand for people and nature.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if a majority of MEPs approves CETA, questions remain over whether the deal will survive further votes in national and regional parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belgium is expected to ask the European Court of Justice to rule on the legality of a controversial system – known as the Investment Court System (ICS) – which allows multinational corporations to sue states under CETA, but not the other way around. Failure to stand up to the ECJ’s legal scrutiny would block CETA’s application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CETA’s aim is not only to eliminate trade tariff barriers, but mainly to remove any obstacles to trade and investment due to differences in laws and regulations between the EU and Canada. Campaigners warn that this could result in an &lt;a href="http://energydesk.greenpeace.org/2016/10/28/ceta-canada-challenged-eu-chemical-regulations-reach/"&gt;assault on public protection measures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href="http://www.ase.tufts.edu/gdae/policy_research/ceta_simulations.html"&gt;independent study&lt;/a&gt; found that CETA could cause the loss of 200,000 jobs across the EU, while the &lt;a href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/september/tradoc_148201.pdf"&gt;European Commission&lt;/a&gt;’s own assessment predicted only a tiny impact of 0.02 to 0.03 per cent long-term GDP increase for the EU, and a 0.18 to 0.36 per cent increase for Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="%20http:/bit.ly/CETAunspun"&gt;CETA spin unspun&lt;/a&gt; - a myth busting Q&amp;amp;A on the EU-Canada trade deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser: +32 (0)477 790 415, &lt;a href="mailto:shira.stanton@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;shira.stanton@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2011/september/tradoc_148201.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQIRL_Web_size.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU to renew glyphosate licence, ignoring concerns</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-to-renew-glyphosate-licence-ignoring-concerns/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – A qualified majority of European governments voted to approve the European Commission’s plan to grant a five-year unrestricted licence to glyphosate, a widely used weedkiller that has been linked to cancer and environmental harm. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Flower_GP0STR986_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Flower_GP0STR986_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission will now issue a formal renewal of the licence for glyphosate in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Reacting to the news, Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg said: “The people who are supposed to protect us from dangerous pesticides have failed to do their jobs and betrayed the trust Europeans place in them. The European Commission and most governments have chosen to ignore the warnings of independent scientists, the demands of the European Parliament and the petition signed by more than one million people calling for a glyphosate ban. The threats of corporate lawsuits are of obviously of much greater concern to them than people’s health and the environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Nine countries voted against the five-year licence (Austria, Belgium, Croatia, Cyprus, France, Greece, Italy, Luxembourg and Malta), while one country abstained (Portugal) and the other eighteen countries voted in favour (Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Germany, Hungary, Ireland, Latvia, Lithuania, the Netherlands, Poland, Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia, Sweden, Spain and the UK).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The Commission plan is based on a flawed health risk assessment of glyphosate, which states there is insufficient evidence of a cancer link, despite the WHO’s classification of the weedkiller as a probable cause of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The EU’s food (EFSA) and chemicals (ECHA) agencies relied on the pesticide industry’s own interpretation of unpublished cancer data when assessing glyphosate. In addition, crucial sections of the EFSA assessment were &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU/status/924948328953020422"&gt;copy-pasted&lt;/a&gt; from the application for a new licence submitted by glyphosate producers. Important findings linking glyphosate to health concerns were thus dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;In October, the European Parliament called for a full glyphosate ban within five years, starting with an immediate ban of use in public spaces, private gardens and unnecessary farming uses, such as pre-harvest spraying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Over one million Europeans have signed a &lt;a href="https://stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;European Citizens’ Initiative&lt;/a&gt; calling for a glyphosate ban, while &lt;a href="https://www.sumofus.org/media/new-glyphosate-polls-2017-en"&gt;polling&lt;/a&gt; in Germany, France, Italy, Portugal and Greece shows growing concern and overwhelming support for a ban.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Franziska Achterberg: Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-27 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Flower_GP0STR986_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Farming</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Neonicotinoids bigger threat to wild bees and other animals than previously thought</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/neonicotinoids-threat-wild-bees-other-animals/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Limits of partial EU ban exposed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 12 January 2017 – Neonicotinoid pesticides pose serious risks not only to honeybees, but also to many other species, according to a scientific review published today by Greenpeace. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/Global/international/publications/agriculture/2017/neonicotinoid-pesticides.pdf"&gt;The analysis, conducted by scientists at the University of Sussex&lt;/a&gt;, reviewed new data from hundreds of studies published since the &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2013:139:0012:0026:en:PDF"&gt;2013 adoption of a partial EU ban&lt;/a&gt; on the pesticides clothianidin, imidacloprid and thiamethoxam. Scientists found risks for honeybees, bumblebees, butterflies and water insects, with possible ripple effects through the food chain. Based on the new findings, Greenpeace is urging the European Commission to fully ban neonicotinoids and promote ecological alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave Goulson&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;professor of biology and leading European expert on the ecology of bumblebees&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The case that neonicotinoids are contributing to wild bee declines and exacerbating honeybee health issues is stronger than it was when the partial EU ban was adopted. In addition to bees, neonicotinoids can plausibly be linked to declines of butterflies, birds and aquatic insects. Given evidence for such widespread environmental harm it would seem prudent to extend the scope of the current European restriction.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, policy director on agriculture at Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“How much more damage has to be done before the EU bans these pesticides? Science clearly shows that neonicotinoids are omnipresent and persistent in the wider environment, not just in agricultural fields. These substances are routinely found in soils, waterways and wildflowers. We must get rid of potent neurotoxins like neonicotinoids from our fields and environment. ”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report confirms that neonicotinoids pose significant risks to many species, such as farmland butterflies, beetles, water insects and even birds such as house sparrows and partridges. Water insects get exposed as a result of neonicotinoids leaching from agricultural soils, drifting from sowing and  spraying machines, and from water systems in greenhouses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union restricted certain uses of clothianidin, imidacloprid and thiamethoxam in May 2013, based on assessments by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), which found that these pesticides are harmful to bees. As part of the decision to introduce a partial ban, the EU required that the producers of the substances submit further information on aspects for which EFSA could not conclude its assessment. On the basis of industry studies, &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4607"&gt;EFSA confirmed in November 2016&lt;/a&gt; that all authorised uses of imidacloprid and clothianidin pose a high risk to bees, or that a high risk cannot be excluded. In the case of thiamethoxam, &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/supporting/pub/1020e"&gt;Syngenta has already failed to produce the additional studies needed to back up an EU approval&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero - agriculture policy director at Greenpeace EU Unit&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 477 777 034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christine Gebeneter - EU communications coordinator, Ecological Farming Project at Greenpeace Netherlands:&lt;/strong&gt; +31 6 39 01 09 82, &lt;a href="mailto:christine.gebeneter@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;christine.gebeneter@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/Global/international/publications/agriculture/2017/neonicotinoid-pesticides.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-01-12 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Activists urge EU to go for 100% renewable energy</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Activists-EU-go-for-100-renewable-energy/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	** High-res photo and video available at bit.ly/GP_9Oct17** &lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20171009%20Go%20Solar%20Schuman.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20171009%20Go%20Solar%20Schuman.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Sixty-five activists, from five countries, [1] also painted surrounding roads with biodegradable yellow paint to turn the roundabout into a giant sun, but this was removed by the fire brigade at the request of the police. This is the latest in a series of seven eye-catching actions across European cities, [2] as the EU and national governments decide the future of the EU’s energy system and Europe's contribution in the global fight against climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Ansgar Kiene&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“Europe has an abundance of renewable energy waiting to be harnessed. Ordinary people, cooperatives and small businesses are all ready to take part in the energy revolution, making electricity from wind, water and sunlight. It’s time for the EU to wrest the energy system away from a few large corporate players invested in dirty fuels like coal, and give control to the people.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The EU is currently deciding the future of its energy system through the review of wide-ranging legislation covering renewable energy policy, fossil fuel subsidies and the design of the electricity market. The European Commission’s proposals were published late last year, branded as the ‘clean energy for all Europeans’ package.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament’s energy committee will vote on the policy plans for renewable energy on 28 November and on the reform of the electricity market rules on 11 December. The full Parliament will vote in early 2018. Energy ministers from all EU countries will also meet on 18 December to come to a preliminary agreement on the planned reforms, in preparation for negotiations with the Parliament and Commission.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;** High-res photo and video available at &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/a2umdxbvicjzfif/AACQmhicewserfb5W-r-TJYMa?dl=0"&gt;bit.ly/GP_9Oct17&lt;/a&gt;**&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt; Barcelona, Spain; Zadar, Croatia; Budapest, Hungary; Ljubljana, Slovenia; Pernik, Bulgaria; Sibiu, Romania; Brussels, Belgium&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2]&lt;/strong&gt; Belgium, the UK, Germany, the Netherlands and Switzerland&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene&lt;/strong&gt;, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (English, German): &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, +32 476 96 13 75 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Juliette Boulet&lt;/strong&gt;, Greenpeace Belgium spokesperson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (French): &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:juliette.boulet@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:juliette.boulet@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;juliette.boulet@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, +32 474 76 34 97&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joeri Thijs&lt;/strong&gt;, Greenpeace Belgium spokesperson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (Dutch): &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:joeri.thijs@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:joeri.thijs@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;joeri.thijs@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, +32 496 26 31 92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press release is also available online at &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ENDS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-10-09 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20171009%20Go%20Solar%20Schuman.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission rejects demands of #StopGlyphosate citizens’ initiative</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/commission-rejects-StopGlyphosate-ECI/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – The European Commission has issued its formal response to the #StopGlyphosate European Citizens Initiative (ECI).
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20on%20steps_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20on%20steps_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; It &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/citizens-initiative/public/initiatives/successful/details/2017/000002"&gt;officially recognised&lt;/a&gt; the submission of more than one million signatures on 6 October. Today’s response is an answer to the ECI’s three demands for a ban of glyphosate, a reform of the EU pesticide approval process and mandatory EU targets to reduce pesticide use. The Commission proposed action that could fulfil one aspect of one of the three demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reacting to the news, &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The Commission is trying to dress up its rejection of the #StopGlyphosate initiative with vague transparency proposals. Providing access to the data on toxic pesticides won’t make them any less dangerous. As long as the Commission leaves the testing of chemicals in the hands of the manufacturers, it will continue to lose the trust of citizens. We will continue to fight for meaningful measures to reduce pesticide use across the EU and for truly independent pesticide assessments.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Commission responded to the ECI by saying it had no scientific or legal grounds for a ban of glyphosate and that national European governments had voted in favour of a five-year licence. This ignores the fact that the Commission proposal is supposed to take into account the scientific evaluation by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), scientific uncertainties that persist (applying the precautionary principle) and “other factors legitimate to the matter”. In addition to investigating the evident flaws in the EFSA health risk assessment, the Commission should have taken into account the classification of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;UN cancer research agency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, the existing scientific evidence on the unacceptable environmental risks posed by glyphosate and significant public concern.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Commission’s proposal to increase data transparency is a partial and misleading response to the ECI’s demand that EU pesticide approvals be based only on fully published studies. Existing EU law already provides for the release of the studies, as confirmed by the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2016-11/cp160128en.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;European Court of Justice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. EFSA has withheld data contrary to this ruling. A number of members of the European Parliament have therefore brought a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=193437&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=en&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=1332248"&gt;&lt;span&gt;case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; against it. Monsanto and Cheminova are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://extranet.greens-efa-service.eu/public/media/file/1/5420"&gt;&lt;span&gt;supporting&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; EFSA in this case. The Commission rejected the ECI demand for studies to be funded by industry but commissioned by regulators instead of industry. Its proposal for EFSA to exceptionally commission ad-hoc studies does not remedy the conflict of interest inherent in the current system.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;While the Commission &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-17-3750_en.htm"&gt;&lt;span&gt;previously&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; acknowledged that the EU is doing too little to reduce pesticide use, it simply deflected responsibility to national governments. This is despite the fact that the Commission must take action against governments that fail to implement the sustainable use directive. The Commission also rejected the ECI demand to set EU-wide targets for pesticide reduction.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;On 27 November, a qualified majority of governments voted to approve the Commission’s plan to grant a five-year unrestricted licence to glyphosate. France is leading a group of governments that want to end the use of glyphosate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/press-room/20171020IPR86572/meps-demand-glyphosate-phase-out-with-full-ban-by-end-2022"&gt;&lt;span&gt;European Parliament&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; has called for a full glyphosate ban within five years, starting with a partial ban from 16 December 2017.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Note:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The #StopGlyphosate ECI fulfilled the requirements set by the EU in less than five months, making it the fastest-growing ECI since the EU introduced this tool in 2012. It was backed by a broad, pan-European coalition of 38 organisations from 15 countries, including Corporate Europe Observatory (CEO), Greenpeace, the Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL), Pesticide Action Network Europe (PAN-E), and WeMove.EU.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;: Greenpeace EU food policy director&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2016-11/cp160128en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-12 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20on%20steps_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>TTIP leaks update: Greenpeace response to Commission statements</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/TTIP-leaks-update-Greenpeace-response-to-Commission-statements/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 2 May 2016 – In response to the European Commission’s statements on the TTIP leaks and a blog post by EU trade commissioner Cecilia Malmström, Greenpeace EU director Jorgo Riss said: 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TTIP%20reading%20room%20with%20credits.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TTIP%20reading%20room%20with%20credits.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Greenpeace sets up a transparent reading room where members of the public can consult copies of the TTIP leaks
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commissioner Malmström is being disingenuous. The leaked consolidated documents make no mention of the EU’s precautionary principle, which provides a higher level of environmental and consumer protection. The mention of the precautionary principle that Malmström refers to is contained in an EU position paper that is not part of the leaked consolidated chapters.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The leaked documents also show the influence of industry lobbies on trade negotiators. The leak mentions several times that negotiators regularly consult with industry and are prepared to represent their positions.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Malmström may well promise not to undermine environmental and consumer protection, but the evidence tells a different story. In several areas the US proposes to lower EU standards, but there are no EU proposals in the leaked consolidated documents to counter this.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If Europeans are to believe Malmström’s promises, the best thing would be for the EU to publish the latest consolidated chapters with clear proof that the Commission is proposing higher environmental and consumer protection in TTIP.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classified documents cover 13 chapters addressing issues ranging from telecommunications to regulatory cooperation, from pesticides, food and agriculture to trade barriers. The leaked documents are available &lt;a href="http://www.ttip-leaks.org/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Q&amp;amp;A document explaining the release of the documents, including a full list of the documents and what they contain, is available &lt;a href="http://www.ttip-leaks.org/#faq"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concise analysis of the content of the chapters of the negotiating texts relating to environment and public health is available &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt; - +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-02 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TTIP%20reading%20room%20with%20credits.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>In just five weeks almost 500,000 people ask EU to ban glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/500000-people-EU-ban-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – In just five weeks, almost half a million Europeans have signed a petition calling on the European Commission to ban the controversial weedkiller glyphosate. On Wednesday, the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) may dismiss a warning by the World Health Organisation linking glyphosate to cancer.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20commission%20web%20credit.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20commission%20web%20credit.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A broad, pan-European coalition of 38 organisations from 15 countries launched the &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;European Citizens’ Initiative&lt;/a&gt; on 8 February. The signatories call on the European Commission to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process and set mandatory EU targets to reduce pesticide use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission must consider the petition if at least one million EU citizens have signed it within one year, reaching minimum thresholds in at least seven countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate is the world’s most heavily used weedkiller and has been &lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;linked to cancer&lt;/a&gt; by the World Health Organisation’s top cancer agency, IARC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health and environmental organisations have &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-on-the-independence-and-transparency-of-ECHAs-Risk-Assessment-Committee/"&gt;raised concerns&lt;/a&gt; about conflicts of interest in the ECHA committee responsible for assessing glyphosate, and criticised ECHA’s reliance on unpublished industry studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32009R1107"&gt;EU regulations&lt;/a&gt; prohibit the use of pesticides when there is sufficient evidence in laboratory animals that these substances can cause cancer, based on IARC’s scientific criteria. According to IARC, glyphosate fulfils these criteria. Nevertheless, the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/151112"&gt;dismissed IARC’s cancer findings&lt;/a&gt;, pointing to &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/4302_glyphosate_complementary.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;unpublished studies&lt;/a&gt; unavailable to the IARC experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, the European Commission proposed to re-approve glyphosate for 15 years, based on the EFSA assessment. However, a public outcry and insufficient backing from national governments forced the Commission to issue only an 18-month extension until the end of 2017, pending a safety assessment by ECHA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please find further background on the glyphosate decision-making process &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170303%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more information on the #StopGlyphosate petition, please visit &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;www.stopglyphosate.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diana G. Smith – &lt;/strong&gt;Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL) communications and media advisor: +33 (0)6 33 04 29 43&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/4302_glyphosate_complementary.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170303%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-14 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/glyphosate%20commission%20web%20credit.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission should stimulate public debate about trade after damning ECJ ruling, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-public-debate-trade-damning-ECJ-ruling/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – The European Commission should foster public debate about alternatives to uncontrolled trade, following a damning ruling by the General Court of the EU on Wednesday, said Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/TTIP%20CETA%20ECI%20stop%20ttip.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/TTIP%20CETA%20ECI%20stop%20ttip.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Photo: stop-ttip.org
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling on 10 May annulled a decision by the Commission in 2014 to block the registration of a European citizens’ initiative (ECI) petition that was critical of prospective EU trade agreements with the US, known as TTIP, and Canada, known as CETA. The registration of the ECI and the collection of at least a million signatures from across the EU would have forced the Commission to issue an official response and prompted a debate in the European Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade policy campaigner Kees Kodde&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The Commission needs to show it’s open to a public conversation about the future direction of trade policy. Silencing critical voices because they challenge a dogma of uncontrolled trade that tramples on people and nature doesn’t only go down badly in the courts, it also fosters bitterness and resentment among people. To become a force for good, trade must no longer be an end in itself, but a means to strengthen our social rights and keep us within planetary boundaries.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the Commission’s refusal to register it as an ECI, the petition collected close to 3.3 million signatures in under a year. The petition raises concerns about the effects of TTIP and CETA on democracy, the rule of law, the environment, health, public services, and consumer and labour rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TTIP negotiations were abandoned following the election of US president Donald Trump, who has been critical of trade agreements. On the other hand, CETA is expected to provisionally enter into force over the summer, even though it still requires ratification by national and regional parliaments in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is also available on:&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt; www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-11 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/TTIP%20CETA%20ECI%20stop%20ttip.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Farming</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Bee-killing pesticides dangerous even when used in greenhouses, new research</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Bee-killing-pesticides-dangerous-greenhouses/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Proposed EU restrictions on neonicotinoids would allow use in greenhouses&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels/Exeter – Bees and other wildlife are exposed to neonicotinoid pesticides even if they are used only inside greenhouses, a new study published today by Greenpeace Science Unit reveals.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/study-neonicotinoids-bees-greenhouses/"&gt;The new research from Greenpeace Science Unit is available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Representatives of European governments will meet on Tuesday and Wednesday to discuss and possibly vote on a European Commission plan to tighten restrictions on three neonicotinoids. Crucially, the plan would allow the continued use of these pesticides in greenhouses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Greenpeace study found that neonicotinoids are frequently present in waterways close to greenhouses where they have been used. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-017-0341-3"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Reviews of previous research&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; have shown that neonicotinoids not only kill bees outright, but also have sublethal effects like impairing the bees’ ability to navigate and reproduce, which contribute to the decline in bee populations. They also pose also a threat to many other species, such as water insects. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/neonicotinoids-threat-wild-bees-other-animals/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is calling for a full ban&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of all neonicotinoids.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Kirsten Thompson, scientist at Greenpeace Science Unit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; at Exeter University&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Even if neonicotinoids are used exclusively inside greenhouses, they contaminate the surrounding environment. Their use may be restricted in principle, but the danger they pose to bees and other wildlife is not. Only a full ban would protect bees, other pollinators and wildlife from neonicotinoids.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;In 2013, the European Commission introduced restrictions on three neonicotinoids – Bayer’s  imidacloprid and clothianidin, and Syngenta’s thiamethoxam – banning some uses on crops attractive to bees, such as sunflowers, oilseed rape, apples, almonds and cucumbers. Many other uses of these pesticides are still allowed, including spraying crops after flowering and use on crops considered less attractive to bees, for example cereals sown in winter or sugar beet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EU vote on new restrictions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;In March 2017, the Commission &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-takes-major-step-to-ban-three-neonics"&gt;drew up a plan&lt;/a&gt; to ban imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam, but still allow their use in greenhouses. This plan is based on an assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) that warns &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4607"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4606"&gt;chemicals&lt;/a&gt; can harm bees not only through dust drift from coated seeds and crop spraying, but also via residues in the wider environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/eli/loi/2016/8/8/2016-1087/jo/texte"&gt;&lt;span&gt;France will ban neonicotinoids&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; from 1 September 2018, with certain uses allowed until 1 July 2020.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; Apart from imidacloprid, clothianidin, and thiamethoxam, four other neonicotinoids are approved for unrestricted use in the EU – acetamiprid, thiacloprid, sulfoxaflor and flupyradifurone – and are increasingly used as substitutes for the three restricted pesticides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU food policy directo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-11 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Farming</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission takes major step to ban three bee-harming pesticides</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-takes-major-step-to-ban-three-neonics/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Governments must close remaining loopholes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Commission has proposed a ban of three neonicotinoid pesticides known to harm bees and other species, except for use in permanent greenhouses, according to a leaked document seen by the Guardian [1]. If such a plan becomes law, the use of Bayer’s imidacloprid and clothianidin, as well as Syngenta’s thiamethoxam will only be allowed in permanent greenhouses “where the crop stays its entire life cycle within the greenhouse and is thus not replanted outside”.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/beekeeper.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/beekeeper.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National representatives will vote on the proposal in Brussels at an upcoming meeting scheduled for 17-18 May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;This is great news for bees and the environment. For years, evidence that these chemicals harm bees has been mounting. Now governments must close the remaining greenhouse loophole and eliminate these chemicals once and for all. Healthy pollinator populations are crucial for healthy ecosystems and food production."&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Unfortunately, even if these dangerous pesticides are banned, similar chemicals will still be permitted. The EU must apply the same strict standards to all pesticides and support the transition to ecological methods of pest control,&lt;/em&gt;” continued Achterberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest proposal is based on opinions of the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) published in 2016 [2]. These opinions concur with independent scientific assessments of the dangers associated with neonicotinoid pesticides, such as a &lt;a href="http://www.tfsp.info/worldwide-integrated-assessment/"&gt;2014 global assessment&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="http://www.easac.eu/fileadmin/Reports/Easac_15_ES_web_complete_01.pdf"&gt;2015 assessment for Europe&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/Global/international/publications/agriculture/2017/neonicotinoid-pesticides.pdf"&gt;2017 review of the most recent scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt;, commissioned by Greenpeace. However, EFSA still has not evaluated the safety of spraying these pesticides and using coated seeds in greenhouses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its latest opinions, EFSA applied a more comprehensive method of assessing the risks pesticides pose to bees [3]. The European Commission has proposed using this method for all pesticide risk assessments, but national governments still have to agree to this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current proposal significantly extends a &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2013/485/oj"&gt;partial ban&lt;/a&gt; of these neonicotinoids instated in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/mar/23/europe-poised-for-total-ban-on-bee-harming-pesticides"&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/mar/23/europe-poised-for-total-ban-on-bee-harming-pesticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] EFSA, 2016, &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4607" target="_blank"&gt;Peer review of the pesticide risk assessment for the active substance imidacloprid in light of confirmatory data submitted&lt;/a&gt;, and EFSA, 2016, &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4606" target="_blank"&gt;Peer reviews of the pesticide risk assessment for the active substance clothianidin in light of confirmatory data submitted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] EFSA, 2013, &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/3295"&gt;Guidance on the risk assessment of plant protection products on bees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.easac.eu/fileadmin/Reports/Easac_15_ES_web_complete_01.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/Global/international/publications/agriculture/2017/neonicotinoid-pesticides.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-23 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/beekeeper.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>MEPs unable to adjust CETA course as global trade doctrine crumbles, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/MEPs-unable-to-adjust-CETA-course-TPP-trade/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Trump deserves no praise on TPP withdrawal, Greenpeace&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - Members of the European Parliament’s trade committee have endorsed a controversial EU-Canada trade and investment protection agreement (known as CETA), despite warnings that the deal could lead to a bonfire of environmental, health and social protection standards.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20170121%20Women's%20march%202.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20170121%20Women's%20march%202.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU committee vote took place a day after US president Donald Trump’s withdrawal from the Trans Pacific Partnership trade agreement (TPP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The trade committee’s recommendation is disappointing but not surprising. After years of indoctrination on this new breed of investment protection deal, many politicians are reluctant to stick their necks out. They label any criticism as a capitulation to populism, but an honest look at the evidence would force them to recognise that multinationals are gearing up for an assault on nature, on our health and on social rights. MEPs have one last chance in February to reject this corporate power grab. They should take it to protect the planet and the people who elected them.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Empowered by trade and investment protection deals similar to CETA, companies are already suing states in special private tribunals over health and environmental safeguards that they see as barriers to trade. The government and companies of Canada are among the most &lt;a href="http://investmentpolicyhub.unctad.org/ISDS/FilterByCountry"&gt;litigious&lt;/a&gt;. They have a record of challenging European standards on &lt;a href="http://www.ciel.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/CIEL-letter-to-Mr.-Magnette.pdf"&gt;dangerous chemicals&lt;/a&gt;, clean energy and food safety. Critics say that CETA is only expected to make this easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.euractiv.com/section/health-consumers/news/new-endocrine-disruptor-rules-address-your-trade-concerns-eu-tells-us-canada/"&gt;Leaked documents&lt;/a&gt; have shown that the EU is prepared to sacrifice safety standards to satisfy the trade demands of Canada and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The European Parliament’s plenary vote is expected in mid-February. If MEPs support CETA, national parliaments would still be required to ratify the deal before its full and final entry into force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;As European politicians struggle to ratify CETA, President Trump delivered on his election promise to withdraw the US from the TPP. Greenpeace warned he deserves no praise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace USA executive director Annie Leonard&lt;/strong&gt; said &lt;em&gt;“The TPP was a bad idea and already dead in the water thanks to a massive movement of resistance from unions to environmentalists. Trump deserves no praise for bumbling onto the right side of this issue. While the TPP would have had devastating results for labour rights and the environment, Trump’s cabinet picks and policy proposals threaten to be equally detrimental for the wellbeing of the people and the planet.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace calls for a trade policy that puts the protection of people’s rights, good jobs and a healthy environment at its heart. New trade policies should work to benefit of everyone, not just a few privileged corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser: +32 (0)477 790 415, &lt;a href="mailto:shira.stanton@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;shira.stanton@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.ciel.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/CIEL-letter-to-Mr.-Magnette.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-01-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20170121%20Women's%20march%202.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commissioner Andriukaitis confronted with demands of over one million Europeans to ban glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/andriukaitis-confronted-ban-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Two days before EU members states are expected to vote on whether to renew the licence for the controversial weedkiller glyphosate, representatives of the Stop Glyphosate European Citizens’ Initiative have met the European commissioner for health and food safety Vytenis Andriukaitis. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/DSC03367.JPG" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Small/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/DSC03367.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over one million people across Europe have demanded a ban on glyphosate, an overall reduction in pesticide use, and more transparency and independence in assessments of the risks posed by pesticides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jorgo Riss, Greenpeace EU director&lt;/strong&gt;, said:&lt;em&gt; “The glyphosate debacle has shown that the Commission continues to put the short-term interests of chemical companies before people’s health and the environment. Its failure to act on the concerns voiced by independent scientists, parliamentarians and over a million Europeans is a disgrace. Scientific research and the experience of thousands of organic farmers show that pesticides and glyphosate are not necessary. To help restore faith in the EU, the Commission must set a path to phase out dangerous pesticides and ensure healthy food and environmentally friendly farming.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;stopglyphosate.org&lt;/a&gt; petition is the fastest-ever ECI to succeed, with over one million signatures collected across Europe in five months, between February and July 2017. Under EU treaty rules, the Commission is required to meet the organisers of the pan-European initiative, while the European Parliament must hold a formal hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU licence for glyphosate runs out on 15 December 2017. The European Commission has proposed renewing EU approval for another ten years, based on European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) and European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) evaluations. The World Health Organisation’s cancer experts have said glyphosate causes cancer in animals and is a probable cause of cancer in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious concerns have been raised about the influence glyphosate manufacturers may have had on the EU’s evaluation of the risks linked to glyphosate. EFSA has come under fire after it was revealed that large sections of its glyphosate assessment rejecting independent scientific evidence were&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Monsantos-view-of-independent-science-copied-into-EU-evaluations-/"&gt;copied&lt;/a&gt; from an application submitted by Monsanto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four countries (France, Italy, Austria and Luxembourg) have said they will vote against the Commission’s proposal, and others such as Germany are expected to abstain. The European Parliament is expected to pass a&lt;a href="http://www.emeeting.europarl.europa.eu/committees/agenda/201710/ENVI/ENVI(2017)1019_1P/sitt-6837072"&gt;resolution&lt;/a&gt; demanding a phase out of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eight countries (France, Italy and Luxembourg, supported by Germany, Netherlands, Sweden, Denmark and Slovakia) have also called on the Commission to initiate a debate on a “&lt;a href="http://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-12893-2017-INIT/en/pdf"&gt;more transparent, more effective and safer assessment of chemical substances&lt;/a&gt;”. France also has a national plan to reduce pesticide use over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;For more information on the glyphosate decision-making process, please refer to this &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171020_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;timeline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Schwartz – &lt;/strong&gt;ECI Coordinator, WeMove.EU: +32 (0)486 078342, &lt;a href="mailto:david@wemove.eu" target="_blank"&gt;david@wemove.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Breddy&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;– &lt;/strong&gt;Head of communications, Greenpeace EU: +32 (0)496 156229, &lt;a href="mailto:mark.breddy@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;mark.breddy@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/DSC03367.JPG</value></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171020_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-10-23 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Small/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/DSC03367.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Renewables</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU-China statement must lead shift to renewables, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-China-must-lead-shift-to-renewables/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 1 June – The EU and China’s renewed commitment to fighting climate change must be backed up by a decisive shift to renewable energy, said Greenpeace. The EU-China joint statement comes amid reports of an imminent US withdrawal from the Paris Agreement on climate change.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQR6T_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQR6T_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/press/releases/2017/Climate-outcast-Trump-surrenders-US-global-leadership---Greenpeace/"&gt;**For the Greenpeace reaction to the announcement of the US withdrawal from the Paris Agreement, click here**&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene, climate and energy campaigner at Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: “There is a real opportunity for the technical prowess of both EU and China to shine as they switch from dirty power stations to wind and solar. With more than 1.1 million people employed in the renewables sector in the EU and more than 3.5 million in China, both are leagues ahead of the US. But the real game-changer is in unlocking the potential of citizens producing, investing in and consuming renewable energy smartly.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Li Shuo, climate policy advisor at Greenpeace East Asia&lt;/strong&gt;, said: “We are seeing much needed leadership emerge from the EU and China today; the will to take responsibility for climate action irrespective of Trump’s fickle stance. But both Beijing and Brussels now have to follow words with action to reap tangible benefits, as well as bragging rights, from a speedy transition to renewable energy.”&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;The statement is expected to highlight the social and economic benefits of climate action and gives details on how the EU and China will move ahead under the UN climate convention (UNFCCC) process. This includes a call on all countries to “strengthen efforts over time”. For the EU this should mean setting more ambitious emissions, renewables and efficiency targets and prioritising access and support for renewables. The European Parliament &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/parliament-fires-up-energy-transition/"&gt;recently called&lt;/a&gt; for an increase in the EU’s 2030 renewable target to between 35 and 45 per cent, compared to the current 27 per cent target. With the right support, &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Media-briefing-Potential-for-citizen-produced-electricity-in-the-EU/"&gt;half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity by 2050,&lt;/a&gt; meeting 45 per cent of the EU’s electricity demand.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;For recent employment figures in the renewables sector see the annual review of the &lt;a href="http://www.irena.org/menu/index.aspx?mnu=Subcat&amp;amp;PriMenuID=36&amp;amp;CatID=141&amp;amp;SubcatID=2729"&gt;International Renewable Energy Agency&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene, Greenpeace EU climate and energy campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1919, &lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Li Shuo, senior global policy advisor (climate &amp;amp; ocean) Greenpeace East Asia&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;br&gt;(86) 152-0168-1548, &lt;a href="mailto:li.shuo@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;li.shuo@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-01 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STQR6T_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU-Japan trade deal smacks of corporate protectionism</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-Japan-trade-deal-corporate-protectionism/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - According to media reports, the European Commission and Japan have reached an agreement which closes negotiations on most parts of the EU’s biggest bilateral trade deal to date. The deal is the latest example of an EU trade policy that only pays lip service to transparency, and social and environmental protection, warned Greenpeace. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP1STOVK_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP1STOVK_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade campaigner Kees Kodde said:&lt;/strong&gt; "&lt;em&gt;This trade deal, and others like it, smack of corporate protectionism at the expense of democracy and the environment. But uncontrolled trade and isolationism are not the only alternatives - both put the economic interests of the few over social and environmental protection for the many.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; Only enhanced international&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; cooperation that centres on people and the planet can help solve the pressing problems of our time, like climate change, inequality and conflict.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace Netherlands &lt;a href="http://trade-leaks.org/jefta-leaks/" target="_blank"&gt;leaked&lt;/a&gt; over 200 pages of the EU-Japan trade deal in June, highlighting several concerns on transparency and environmental protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace has laid out &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;ten principles&lt;/a&gt; for a fair trade policy that upholds social and environmental standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;– Greenpeace trade policy campaigner:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;+31 (0)6 53623818, &lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milo Laureij &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;– Greenpeace communications:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;+31 (0)6 29001159, &lt;a href="mailto:milo.laureij@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;milo.laureij@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-07-05 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP1STOVK_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Shorter EU licence would leave people and nature exposed to dangers of glyphosate, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Shorter-EU-licence-would-leave-people-nature-exposed-to-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	At a meeting on 18 and 19 May, EU government representatives are expected to decide whether or not to renew the EU licence of a controversial herbicide known as glyphosate, which scientists have linked to cancer.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="http://www.dw.com/en/eu-defers-vote-on-glyphosate-weedkiller-over-cancer-concerns/a-19102662"&gt;failing to garner enough support&lt;/a&gt; from EU governments for a 15-year renewal, the European Commission is now backing continued unrestricted use of glyphosate for at least 9 years [Commission &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/a/greenpeace.org/file/d/0Bzj_0to-Zg2LTmduMkpuazYwdlE/view"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/a/greenpeace.org/file/d/0Bzj_0to-Zg2LVlBqTXdreFc4eUk/view"&gt;annexes&lt;/a&gt;], after the licence runs out on 30 June this year. This would ignore a &lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;cancer warning&lt;/a&gt; by the WHO’s cancer agency, the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), as well as concerns raised by ministers in several EU countries [including &lt;a href="http://www.lefigaro.fr/flash-actu/2016/05/02/97001-20160502FILWWW00338-pesticides-royal-reaffirme-l-opposition-de-la-france-au-glyphosate.php"&gt;France&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-eu-glyphosate-idUSKCN0Y31MG"&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt;], the &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/news-room/20160407IPR21781/Glyphosate-authorise-for-just-seven-years-and-professional-uses-only-urge-MEPs"&gt;European Parliament&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2016/apr/11/two-thirds-of-europeans-support-ban-on-glyphosate-says-yougov-poll"&gt;public opposition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;Shortening the glyphosate licence does not protect people and the environment, only significant restrictions or a full ban will do that. What’s more, the Commission can stretch the licence by several years, as it has done with the current glyphosate licence. Greenpeace calls for immediate glyphosate restrictions to limit human exposure.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April 2016, the European Parliament called for a &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//NONSGML+TA+P8-TA-2016-0119+0+DOC+PDF+V0//EN"&gt;ban on glyphosate-based herbicides in private and public green areas&lt;/a&gt;, including public parks, playgrounds and gardens. MEPs also called for a prohibition of its use in agricultural fields shortly before harvesting, and where weeds can be controlled with other methods. The Parliament said any new glyphosate licence should be limited to seven years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2015, the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) contradicted the IARC glyphosate assessment, concluding that there was no cancer link. The EFSA assessment has come under fire from 96 independent scientists, including several of those involved in the IARC cancer review, as “&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;not supported by the evidence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EFSA was also criticised for &lt;a href="http://corporateeurope.org/efsa/2016/02/key-evidence-withheld-trade-secret-eus-controversial-risk-assessment-glyphosate"&gt;basing its conclusion on several unpublished industry-funded studies&lt;/a&gt;. The Commission has since requested that Monsanto and other glyphosate producers &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/2014-2019/andriukaitis/announcements/my-letter-dr-richard-p-garnett-chair-board-gl"&gt;publish the studies&lt;/a&gt;. The companies have proposed &lt;a href="http://www.glyphosate.eu/system/files/sidebox-files/letter_to_commissioner_andriukaitis.pdf"&gt;restricted access in guarded reading rooms&lt;/a&gt;, arguing that publication of the studies would violate their commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only restriction set out in the Commission’s proposal for this week’s meeting is on the use of glyphosate in pesticides that also contain a chemical called polyethoxylated (POE)-tallowamine. These products are no longer sold in Germany, one of Europe’s largest pesticides markets, while Monsanto says that it is &lt;a href="http://monsantoblog.eu/monsanto-transitions-away-from-tallowamine-in-products-enfr/#.VxZCRP4UWUk"&gt;preparing to phase them out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body responsible for cancer classification in Europe, the &lt;a href="http://echa.europa.eu/registry-of-submitted-harmonised-classification-and-labelling-intentions/-/substance-rev/13201/term"&gt;European Chemicals Agency&lt;/a&gt;, is also expected to complete an assessment of health hazards arising from the use of glyphosate, but not before the end of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32009R1107"&gt;EU regulations&lt;/a&gt; prohibit the use of herbicides when there is sufficient evidence from animal tests that these substances are linked to cancer. The EU rules are based on IARC criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 16 May 2016, the FAO /WHO Joint Meeting on Pesticide Residues (JMPR) released an assessment stating that glyphosate is &lt;em&gt;“unlikely to pose a carcinogenic risk to humans from exposure through the diet”&lt;/em&gt;. However, Greenpeace warned that at least two experts involved in the JMPR’s evaluation – &lt;a href="http://abonnes.lemonde.fr/planete/article/2016/05/17/une-expertise-favorable-au-roundup-suscite-la-colere-des-ong_4920523_3244.html"&gt;reportedly the chair and co-chair of the JMPR panel&lt;/a&gt; – had links to glyphosate producers, calling into question whether the organisation has ensured the independence of its advice [&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Industry-ties-JMPR-glyphosate/"&gt;Greenpeace press release&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For more information&lt;/strong&gt;, see our &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/BR%20glyphosate%20approval%20-%20FINAL%20%2003032016.pdf"&gt;March 2016 briefing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 19 11, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf</value><value>http://www.glyphosate.eu/system/files/sidebox-files/letter_to_commissioner_andriukaitis.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/BR%20glyphosate%20approval%20-%20FINAL%20%2003032016.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-18 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Pesticide%20spraying.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EUaffairs</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU at 60: Rome activists demand greener Europe</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-at-60-Rome-activists-demand-greener-Europe/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Rome/Brussels – As European leaders prepare to celebrate the foundation of the European Union in Rome 60 years ago, Greenpeace activists kicked off three days of public demonstrations and events by displaying a giant 100m2 banner from a piazza overlooking the centre of the ancient city.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photos &amp;amp; video&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://media.greenpeace.org/shoot/27MZIFJJ79I_X"&gt;http://media.greenpeace.org/shoot/27MZIFJJ79I_X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EuropeWeWant.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EuropeWeWant.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner was placed on the Pincio terrace, close to where European leaders signed the Treaty of Rome on 25 March 1957. It depicts a fluttering EU flag revealing a solar panel, and reads: “After 60 years: a better Europe to save the climate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU deputy director Saskia Richartz &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“A better Europe is possible and necessary. By putting people and the planet ahead of narrow corporate interests, our governments can restore trust in democracy. By enabling people to produce their own renewable energy, the EU can break free from fossil fuels. By reaching out to those in need, we can build bridges and tear down the walls that divide us. Only then can we breathe new life into Europe.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Richartz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; added: “For all its achievements since 1957, the EU’s current response to many global challenges is woefully inadequate. The future of Europe and our planet is at stake and the Rome celebrations can’t just be a photo op. They must signal a change of direction. It is all to play for, and every one of us can make a difference.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next three days, Rome will host dozens of citizen-led debates, protests and exhibitions charting a different course for the European Union. Greenpeace will join people from all over Europe and hundreds of civil society organisations for a &lt;a href="http://www.lanostraeuropa.org/"&gt;march&lt;/a&gt; on Saturday in Rome, in support of a &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170227%20joint%20CSO%20statement%20The%20Europe%20We%20Want%20-%20final.pdf"&gt;united, sustainable and democratic Europe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt; - +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170227%20joint%20CSO%20statement%20The%20Europe%20We%20Want%20-%20final.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-23 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Democracy</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EuropeWeWant.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>TTIP talks press ahead with new privileges for big business</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/TTIP-talks-press-ahead-with-new-privileges-for-big-business/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The 12th round of EU-US trade talks ends in Brussels today with negotiators pressing ahead to deliver new privileges for big business, said Greenpeace. The start of the talks was delayed on Monday after a blockade by Greenpeace activists, who warned against a “dead end trade deal” and called for an end to the negotiations.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p id="docs-internal-guid-51f4b3ed-1d15-c798-9e5e-5093f87b4654" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 5px; float: left;" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TTIP%20action%201.jpg" alt="Greenpeace action againt TTIP negotiations in Brussels. Activists block the entrances to the negotiations take take place in conference centre in Ixelles, Brussels, Belgium.   / © Eric de Mildt - Greenpeace / Mention of name obligatory / All rights reserved. " width="240" height="160"&gt;Negotiators discussed plans to establish a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/From-ISDS-to-ICS-A-leopard-cant-change-its-spots/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;quasi-court&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; under a future Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP) agreement. The court would allow corporations to sue governments over any environmental, health or labour safeguards that stand in the way of their investments, warned Greenpeace. Under a similar system, a Canadian energy company recently demanded $15 billion in compensation after US President Barack Obama rejected the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.euractiv.com/section/trade-society/opinion/keystone-isds-lawsuit-highlights-legal-risks-of-eu-trade-deals/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Keystone oil pipeline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Commenting on the conclusion of this week’s talks, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace TTIP campaigner Susan Cohen Jehoram&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Once again negotiators worked hard to deliver new privileges for big business, at the expense of people and the environment. They say they want to protect environmental, health and labour standards, but instead they are giving foreign corporations exclusive rights to challenge these same standards in a special court. This is a blatant disregard for democracy and the public interest. Opposition to this trade agreement is growing. The more people hear about it, the more concerned they are. And the harder it will be to ignore them.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; For more information on EU-US trade talks, read our&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;23 burning questions on TTIP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; Photos and video of the Greenpeace blockade are available &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://photo.greenpeace.org/C.aspx?VP3=SearchResult&amp;amp;ALID=27MZIFJ6IWA_2"&gt;&lt;span&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts: Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; – +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-02-26 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TTIP%20action%201.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Food</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU farming reform plan overlooks impact of meat sector, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-farming-reform-plan-overlooks-impact-of-meat-sector/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – On the eve of a major reform of European Union farming rules, the European Commission has glossed over the growing environmental and health impact of the industrial meat and dairy sectors, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Industrial pig farming in Germany
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;In a paper released today, the Commission recognised public concern over the impact of farming, but failed to provide a concrete plan to transition away from destructive farming practices. It reiterated its support for the current subsidy system under the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP), which has favoured large-scale industrial farming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The industrial production and overconsumption of meat, milk and eggs in Europe is having a devastating impact on our health, nature and the climate. The Commission’s failure to even mention the problem shows the EU is asleep at the wheel while our food and farming system heads straight for disaster. The new EU farming policy should reward farmers who provide healthy food while protecting nature, water and soil, and the climate.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The EU animal farming sector accounts for between &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2012.02786.x/abstract"&gt;&lt;span&gt;12 and 17 per cent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of the EU’s total greenhouse gas emissions and is a major cause of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/environmental-indicator-report-2014"&gt;&lt;span&gt;environmental destruction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, from water pollution to soil degradation and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fao.org/ag/againfo/themes/en/Environment.html"&gt;&lt;span&gt;habitat loss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. Over 80 per cent of EU agricultural &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pbl.nl/sites/default/files/cms/publicaties/Nitrogen_on_the_Table_Report_WEB.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ammonia emissions into the air and nitrogen emissions into water&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; are caused by livestock farming. Research published in the journal &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Nature &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;estimates that nitrogen pollution costs the EU up to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/51037822_Too_much_of_a_good_thing"&gt;&lt;span&gt;€320 billion per year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Average European meat and dairy consumption is about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pbl.nl/sites/default/files/cms/publicaties/Protein_Puzzle_web_1.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;70 per cent higher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; than the World Health Organisation’s recommendation. Meat consumption is double the global average, while dairy consumption is three times higher. The WHO warns that excessive animal protein consumption is a major cause of cancer, type 2 diabetes, heart disease and obesity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subsidising industrial farming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Commission also supported the continuation of the decried practice of subsidising farmers based on the area of land they own or lease, and irrespective of farming practices. These so-called ‘direct payments’ have been criticised for penalising small-scale farmers and encouraging unsustainable production, waste and environmental destruction.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Direct payments represent almost 80 per cent of the EU’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) budget. According to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/agriculture/sites/agriculture/files/statistics/factsheets/pdf/eu_en.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Commission data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 80 per cent of farmers received just 20 per cent of direct payments. Just over &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://capreform.eu/does-capping-direct-payments-make-sense/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;one per cent &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;of EU farms received one third of all CAP payments. Between 2007 and 2013, the EU lost 3 million farms, but the average size of farms increased.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Overall, the CAP accounts for almost 40 per cent of the EU budget, or the equivalent of €58 billion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero - Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0)477 777034, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press comment is also available on: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.pbl.nl/sites/default/files/cms/publicaties/Nitrogen_on_the_Table_Report_WEB.pdf</value><value>http://www.pbl.nl/sites/default/files/cms/publicaties/Protein_Puzzle_web_1.pdf</value><value>https://ec.europa.eu/agriculture/sites/agriculture/files/statistics/factsheets/pdf/eu_en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-29 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Conflict of interest concerns blight new glyphosate safety assessment</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Conflict-of-interest-concerns-blight-glyphosate-new-safety-assessment/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Potential conflicts of interest and transparency concerns hang over the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA), as it prepares a crucial assessment of glyphosate, a controversial weedkiller which has been linked to cancer, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateHazmatCOM.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateHazmatCOM.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee is &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/documents/10162/22932537/rac_40_agenda_en.pdf/81de9087-84fd-aca7-9662-bebef1da1d29"&gt;meeting on 8 and 15 March&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the health and environmental impacts caused by the use of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf"&gt;In a letter&lt;/a&gt; to the agency on behalf of 20 health and environmental organisations, Greenpeace said that the chairman of ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee and two other members appear to breach the agency’s own conflict of interest rules. The organisations also criticised ECHA’s practice of basing assessments on unpublished industry studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chair of the ECHA committee, Tim Bowmer, worked for &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/documents/10162/13576/bowmer_tim_doi_en.pdf/9c49e281-7f6a-4ede-821b-f9f0e453d269"&gt;two consultancies&lt;/a&gt; in the chemical sector for 20 years, including as business development manager and senior account manager. His contract with the organisations ended the day before he started his employment as chair of ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said:&lt;em&gt; “The question of whether glyphosate can cause cancer affects millions of people in Europe. This is why the scientists who review the evidence on behalf of the European Chemicals Agency must be entirely independent, especially from corporate interests. The practice of using unpublished industry studies must end so that all scientific assessments by EU regulatory agencies can be independently verified.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the WHO’s cancer research agency, IARC, classified glyphosate as “&lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;probably carcinogenic to humans&lt;/a&gt;”. However, the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) said there was&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/151112"&gt;insufficient scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; of a cancer link. EFSA also relied on “&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/4302_glyphosate_complementary.pdf"&gt;unpublished studies&lt;/a&gt;” unavailable to the IARC experts, stating that they formed the “core basis” of its evaluation. After significant controversy on the safety of glyphosate, the European Union postponed its decision on a new EU licence until ECHA finalised its assessment, due by November 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, a coalition of civil society organisations launched a &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;European Citizens’ Initiative&lt;/a&gt; calling on the European Commission to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU. Almost 430,000 people have already signed the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf</value><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/4302_glyphosate_complementary.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-07 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateHazmatCOM.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Renewables</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU could retake climate leadership under new EP plan to boost renewables</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-climate-leadership-boost-renewables/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	A new plan by key members of the European Parliament would help the EU retake global leadership on climate change, just as the US dithers on its commitments under the Paris climate agreement, said Greenpeace.


&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a response to a draft EU energy law by the European Commission, the MEPs leading on the file for the Parliament, Claude Turmes and Michele Rivasi, said the EU should produce 45 per cent of its electricity from renewables by 2030. The Commission’s draft of the ‘Governance of the Energy Union Regulation’ – one of a package of EU policy proposals on energy – suggests a 27 per cent target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate &amp;amp; energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“National governments and the Commission have so far failed to back up promises made in Paris with decisive action. The Parliament’s plan would set the EU on the necessary path towards 100 per cent renewable energy, and is the first sign that Europe will rise to the challenge of climate change. The EU must reclaim the mantle of world leader on climate change, as the new US administration dithers on climate action.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Parliament plan will be submitted to the industry and energy committee on 21 June. On 4 September, MEPs on the committee will discuss and amend the response. The committee is expected to vote on the final plan on 11/12 October, before a final plenary vote around the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate &amp;amp; energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1905,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-17 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Renewables</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Energy ministers give Europeans coal for Christmas</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Energy-ministers-coal-Christmas/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Council adopts preliminary agreement on energy reform package&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – European energy ministers have backed coal and other fossil fuels over renewable energy, in the ongoing reform of the EU’s energy laws.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The ministers moved to maintain controversial subsidies for energy utilities, including the most polluting coal plants. They also weakened European Commission proposals to empower households, cooperatives and municipalities to produce and sell their own renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://bit.ly/2BawpiF"&gt;**Print quality images from the media stunt outside the Council on 18 December available here**&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Energy ministers also ignored calls by the European Parliament to raise the EU’s 2030 target for renewable energy. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513749919335000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFIutYF0EeLI_vaJtY4MyMzX_jXNg"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Projections show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that the current target is too low to meet the EU’s commitments under the Paris climate agreement.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Europe’s coal plants will think Christmas has come early as EU energy ministers stand ready to offer them near limitless subsidies. But European citizens were left out in the cold when the same ministers gutted proposals to support their rights to produce and sell renewable energy, especially at a time when we need all the renewables we can get to meet our climate commitments. The Parliament must now back renewable energy in the hands of the many, not dirty energy in the hands of the few.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The text agreed by energy ministers would undermine European Commission proposals requiring national governments to justify public payments to power plants just to keep them on stand-by. Ministers also changed a Commission proposal to block existing coal plants from receiving these payments after 2025 if they emit over 550g of carbon dioxide per kilowatt hour, extending the subsidies until 2035. All new coal plants would be blocked from receiving these payments after 2025, while the Commission had proposed to cease payments in 2020.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament is expected to finalise its position on the renewable energy reform in a plenary vote during the third week of January 2018. The Parliament’s energy committee will vote on proposed changes to electricity market design on 21 February 2018, before a likely vote in plenary in March. Energy ministers are expected to confirm yesterday’s preliminary agreement on the full reform package at an energy council on 26 February before three-way negotiations with Commission and Parliament start in spring.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;**Print quality images from the media stunt outside the Council on 18 December available at: &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/2BawpiF" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://bit.ly/2BawpiF&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513749919335000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGhpsxzxN-sQLj45qij4Ev10QT0Kw"&gt;http://bit.ly/2BawpiF&lt;/a&gt;**&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%20477%2079%2004%2016" target="_blank"&gt;+32 477 79 04 16&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;tara.connolly@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Hyland, Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%20471%2075%2089%2085" target="_blank"&gt;+32 471 75 89 85&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513749919336000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGbF7Lu0zOsZqe4AVISWTWSUDdBBg"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-19 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>FossilFuels</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Leaked EU-Canada joint declaration has legal weight of a holiday brochure</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Leaked-EU-Canada-joint-declaration-has-legal-weight-of-a-holiday-brochure-Greenpeace/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Greenpeace has slammed a joint EU-Canadian declaration meant to reassure critics of a controversial trade deal between the two blocs. Greenpeace described the document as a PR exercise devoid of any legal content.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Stop%20CETA%201.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Stop%20CETA%201.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After analysing a &lt;a title="a leak of the declaration" href="http://diepresse.com/mediadb/pdf/cetazusatztext.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;leak of the declaration&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU legal strategist Andrea Carta &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“As it stands, this declaration has the legal weight of a holiday brochure. There is nothing in it that would guard against the threat of CETA to nature, our health and labour standards. Regrettably, this is a PR exercise, not a serious attempt to address the problems of CETA.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The declaration is a sloppy afterthought that can’t fix CETA and ignores the concerns of the public, trade unions and civil society organisations. It does nothing to bind or even guide arbitrators ruling over any future trade disputes between multinationals and states.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The mere fact that the EU and Canada have felt the need to cobble together a last-minute declaration is a recognition that the trade deal is defective. All it does is put the finger on a number of risky and sensitive areas, which should be read as a warning against the ratification of this trade deal. Actually improving CETA would have meant real renegotiations and changes in the treaty text itself."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace analysis of the leaked joint declaration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall assessment&lt;/strong&gt;: The draft declaration uses non-binding, non-enforceable descriptive text, which paints an unreasonably optimistic picture about CETA and fails to address the shortcomings of the agreement. There is no new commitment or clarification in the text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right to regulate&lt;/strong&gt;: The leak makes the general statement that “&lt;em&gt;CETA preserves the ability of the European Union and its Member States and Canada to apply their own laws and regulations that regulate economic activity in the public interest&lt;/em&gt;”, but fails to address the fact that the right to regulate in CETA’s chapters on investment, labour and the environment is not clearly defined and subject to limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulatory cooperation&lt;/strong&gt;: The leak says that regulatory cooperation “&lt;em&gt;will be voluntary&lt;/em&gt;”, but does not exclude that the European Commission and the Canadian government may engage in deregulation for the benefit of corporations and against the interest of EU and Canadian citizens - with no scrutiny from elected parliaments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public services&lt;/strong&gt;: The leak says that “&lt;em&gt;CETA will not require governments to privatise any service nor prevent governments from expanding the range of services they supply to the public&lt;/em&gt;”. But while there is no explicit requirement to privatise public services, this will not prevent them from being privatised. In fact, CETA increases the pressure on governments to privatise. It grants access to public procurement for all public services, including water, to Canadian companies. The leak of the joint declaration also fails to address the fact that CETA exposes local authorities to compensation claims from Canadian investors, if public authorities decide to bring local public services under their control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment protection&lt;/strong&gt;: The leaked text claims that, under CETA, “&lt;em&gt;governments may change their laws, regardless of whether this may negatively affect an investment or investor’s expectations of profits&lt;/em&gt;”. However, the statement does not change the fact that multinationals will still be entitled to sue governments and claim compensation before a special arbitration panel, circumventing the jurisdiction and scrutiny of national courts. The text is also meant to reassure citizens that shell or mailbox companies cannot take advantage of CETA to sue EU countries, saying that “&lt;em&gt;CETA requires a real economic link with the economies of Canada or the European Union”&lt;/em&gt;. The declaration does not exclude genuine subsidiaries of non-Canadian companies from suing states under CETA. This includes most Canadian subsidiaries of US companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precautionary principle&lt;/strong&gt;: The leak does not mention the precautionary principle, which protects Europeans from health risks and dangers to the environment. The text says that “&lt;em&gt;CETA commits the European Union and its member states and Canada to provide for and encourage high levels of environmental protection&lt;/em&gt;”, when, in reality, CETA contains a watered down version of the precautionary principle that threatens to weaken European environmental standards and pave the way for a race to the bottom. The leaked text also makes claims on &lt;em&gt;“commitments to cooperate on trade-related environmental issues of common interest such as climate change”&lt;/em&gt;, which are not backed up by the CETA text. The agreement does not contain, in this field, anything more than vague declarations and aspirational statements, devoid of any binding legal value. The text in the leak of the joint declaration does not change this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul type="disc"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustainable development&lt;/strong&gt;: The leak claims that “&lt;em&gt;CETA reconfirms the longstanding commitment of Canada and the European Union and its Member States to sustainable development&lt;/em&gt;”, but ignores the fact that CETA’s sustainable development chapter does not contain any binding rule and is, at best, aspirational.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade campaigner Susan Cohen Jehoram&lt;/strong&gt; said:&lt;em&gt; “A genuinely progressive trade agreement would require a radical shift in mindset among policymakers. Trade agreements should benefit people first and foremost, not only corporations. Our governments and the European Parliament must reject CETA - it can’t be fixed with this declaration.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU trade ministers will meet in Luxembourg on 18 October to decide whether to support CETA, in view of the joint declaration. If they do, the deal will be signed symbolically at an EU-Canada summit in Brussels on 27 and 28 October. The European Parliament is then expected to vote on ratification in late 2016 or early 2017. After that, CETA will need to be ratified by the national parliaments of all EU countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the European Parliament ratifies CETA, large parts of the agreement will ‘provisionally’ come into force,  even before the national parliaments have had their say. The investment court system (ICS), a controversial arbitration system for investment disputes between multinationals and states, could largely be excluded from provisional application. This means that ICS may still be rejected by national parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://diepresse.com/mediadb/pdf/cetazusatztext.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-10-06 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Stop%20CETA%201.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>TTIP: EU and US show signs of desperation, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/TTIP-EU-and-US-show-signs-of-desperation/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Growing opposition to a transatlantic trade deal (TTIP) and faltering negotiations mean talks cannot be wrapped up anytime soon, said Greenpeace as EU and US politicians attempt to show renewed resolve for a deal. Outgoing US president Barack Obama is today (Sunday) expected to promise progress in trade talks on the margins of a visit to Hannover in Germany, which was met by large anti-TTIP protests on Saturday. The next round of talks begins in New York on Monday.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160423%20Hannover%20TTIP%20protest%20march%204.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160423%20Hannover%20TTIP%20protest%20march%204.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Activists unfurl giant banner during Hannover anti-TTIP march on Saturday 23 April 2016.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade expert Juergen Knirsch &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“This trade deal is going nowhere. With opposition to TTIP growing on both sides of the Atlantic and talks faltering, President Obama and Chancellor Merkel are growing increasingly desperate. The EU and the US haven’t even laid out all their positions on the different aspects of a future deal, let alone started to negotiate compromises. Meanwhile, protests are growing and more and more people see TTIP for what it is: a threat for democracy, environmental and health standards, and social rights.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support for TTIP is plummeting in the EU and in the US. Recent &lt;a href="http://www.bertelsmann-stiftung.de/fileadmin/files/BSt/Publikationen/GrauePublikationen/NW_Attitudes_global_trade_and_TTIP.pdf"&gt;surveys&lt;/a&gt; conducted by YouGov for the Bertelsmann Foundation found that only 17 per cent of Germans and 18 per cent of Americans support TTIP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU and the US have stated their positions on &lt;a href="http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2015/march/tradoc_153263.pdf"&gt;only 13&lt;/a&gt; of the 25 TTIP ‘chapters’ up for negotiation and have steered clear of the controversial topic of trade dispute settlement through special courts. Next week’s talks in New York and the subsequent 2016 negotiation round in July are not expected to substantially change this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace warns that TTIP would represent a major transfer of power from people to big business, and calls for an immediate end to negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;TTIP Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; – unpacking EU-US trade talks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Juergen Knirsch&lt;/strong&gt; – Greenpeace trade expert: +49 171 8780 816, &lt;a href="mailto:juergen.knirsch@greenpeace.de" target="_blank"&gt;juergen.knirsch@greenpeace.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.bertelsmann-stiftung.de/fileadmin/files/BSt/Publikationen/GrauePublikationen/NW_Attitudes_global_trade_and_TTIP.pdf</value><value>http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/docs/2015/march/tradoc_153263.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201602%20comprehensive%20QandA%20TTIP%20FINAL.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-04-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160423%20Hannover%20TTIP%20protest%20march%204.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Leaked TTIP documents released</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Leaked-TTIP-documents-released/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Greenpeace EU press briefing – 14:30 – Residence Palace, Brussels &lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160502%20TTIPleaks%20Reichstag.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160502%20TTIPleaks%20Reichstag.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Greenpeace activists project #TTIPleaks documents on the Berlin Reichstag on 2 May 2016
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;*Greenpeace EU will hold a press briefing at 14:30 CET today in the Residence Palace in Brussels to discuss the findings from analysis of the negotiating texts*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jorgo Riss, director of Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“Greenpeace Netherlands has made these documents publically available to bring some much needed transparency to the debate on TTIP. We have seen grave concerns for environment and public health confirmed, and invite others with expertise in different areas to download these documents and analyse the impacts of this trade deal. The public has a right to know what is being traded away in their name.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classified documents cover 13 chapters addressing issues ranging from telecommunications to regulatory cooperation, from pesticides, food and agriculture to trade barriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Q&amp;amp;A document explaining the release of the documents, including a full list of the documents and what they contain, is available &lt;a href="http://www.ttip-leaks.org/#faq"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concise analysis of the content of the chapters of the negotiating texts relating to environment and public health is available here: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf"&gt;TTIP leaks analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*If you would like to attend the press briefing at 14:30 today in the Residence Palace in Brussels please contact the Greenpeace EU press desk*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk: &lt;/strong&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-02 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/20160502%20TTIPleaks%20Reichstag.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Pesticides</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission revises EU decision-making rules in move to avoid blame </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-revises-EU-decision-making-rules-in-move-to-avoid-blame-/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Today the European Commission presented a proposal to revise the decision-making rules under the so-called “comitology” procedure that is used, among other things, for approvals of products such as pesticides and GMOs. The proposal changes the voting rules for the Appeal Committee, which is invoked when there is no qualified majority of member states [1] for or against in the first committee mandated to vote. Appeal Committee abstentions would not be counted. This could open the door to regulatory approvals even when only a small number of countries support them, said Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The proposed voting rules will just make it easier for the Commission to take bad decisions without taking the blame. They won’t do anything to make the EU more democratic. If these proposals become law, the Commission will be able to say a majority of EU countries is backing the use of controversial products when in reality only a small number of countries are.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Democratic decision-making requires that the EU only allow the use of potentially harmful products, such as pesticides and GMOs, if our governments are confident that they will not cause harm. No such products should be allowed without the support of a real majority of countries.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a title="Comitology: Commission proposes more transparency and accountability in procedures for implementing EU law" href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-17-264_en.htm"&gt;Commission’s proposal&lt;/a&gt; was triggered by last year’s &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170208%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline%20ECI%20launch.pdf"&gt;glyphosate debate&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;In June 2016, the Commission held an Appeal Committee vote on an 18-month extension of the glyphosate licence. It failed to achieve a qualified majority in favour and subsequently took the decision to extend the licence unilaterally. Under the rules proposed today, not counting abstentions, it would have had a majority in favour.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends of the Earth Europe, Greenpeace, HEAL, IFOAM EU and Pesticide Action Network Europe are &lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170213_Open_Letter_Comitology.pdf"&gt;calling for&lt;/a&gt; a qualified majority of all EU countries to be mandatory when deciding to allow the use of potentially hazardous products and food preparation processes. This was one of the options considered by the Commission at an earlier stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/priorities/docs/pg_en.pdf"&gt;Political Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; of 2014, PresidentJuncker promised to change the &lt;strong&gt;decision-making rules for GMO authorisations&lt;/strong&gt; and that he “&lt;em&gt;would not want the Commission to be able to take a decision when a majority of Member States has not encouraged it to do so&lt;/em&gt;”. However, Juncker backed down on changing the EU authorisation process and, in April 2015, proposed that EU countries should be able to &lt;a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-15-4777_en.htm"&gt;ban GMO imports nationally&lt;/a&gt;. Commissioner Andriukaitis &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/2014-2019/andriukaitis/announcements/commissioner-andriukaitis-addressing-extraordinary-meeting-parliaments-committee-environment-public_en"&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; at the time that “&lt;em&gt;changing the Comitology Regulation only for GMOs could not be justified and would have been discriminatory&lt;/em&gt;”. The proposal is stuck in Council and likely to never become law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2016 &lt;strong&gt;glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt; battle made it clear that this decision-making problem is not just about GMOs. Juncker complained that national governments abstained or voted against the Commission proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed change to the comitology regulation must be agreed by Parliament and Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt; [1] A qualified majority requires the favourable vote of at least 16 countries, representing at least 65% of the EU population.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press release is also available on: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170208%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline%20ECI%20launch.pdf</value><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170213_Open_Letter_Comitology.pdf</value><value>http://ec.europa.eu/priorities/docs/pg_en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-14 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>EUaffairs</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Landmark ECJ ruling: research on dangers of pesticides must be made public</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Landmark-ECJ-ruling-research-on-dangers-of-pesticides-must-be-made-public/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Luxembourg/Brussels, 23 November 2016 – The European Court of Justice ruled today that safety tests conducted by the chemical industry and used by regulators to assess the dangers of pesticides must be disclosed. It argued that such research falls under “information on emissions into the environment”, as defined under the Aarhus Convention and the EU law implementing this Convention.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20apples.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20apples.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The ruling says that regulators must release all research used to evaluate the dangers of pesticides, and cannot keep it secret to protect industry interests. Based on the ruling, national and EU authorities should release these studies automatically, and not only following freedom of information requests. Transparency in pesticide assessments is vital, as public health and our environment are at risk.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="gmail_quote"&gt;
&lt;div dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;div dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hans Muilerman, Pesticide Action Network Europe chemical officer&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“Safety tests done by industry on their own products constitute a clear conflict of interest. Disclosure of the full tests will show if the summaries presented by industry to governments agree with the outcomes of the original tests conducted.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace and Pesticide Action Network Europe have called for EFSA scientific opinions, which form the basis of regulatory action, to be based on &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Joint-NGOs-letter-to-Commissioner-Andriukaitis/" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Joint-NGOs-letter-to-Commissioner-Andriukaitis/&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1479986520703000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH3T5ZdQx1HG_d1aCVnLOtW-ASRZw"&gt;publicly available scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt;, so that all EFSA assessments can be reproduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Contact: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="tel:%2B32%20%280%292%20274%201911" target="_blank"&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-2a88426b-90f4-8171-57f8-369aefbc229e"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hans Muilerman, Pesticide Action Network EU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +31 (0) 6 55807255, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:hans@pan-europe.info"&gt;&lt;span&gt;hans@pan-europe.info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1479986520703000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH1T-Su0ABAUBfDBV4AKZWZVNeTtQ"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-11-23 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20apples.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Food</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>CETA threatens food safety even before national parliaments sign off</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/ceta-food-safety-provisional-application/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	On the eve of the preliminary application of the EU-Canada trade deal, CETA, Greenpeace warned of threats to food safety and agricultural standards. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ictsd.org/bridges-news/bridges/news/eu-canada-confirm-ceta-provisional-application-date"&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="epi_dc_editBtn" href="#"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="epi_dc_previewBtn" href="#"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="epi_dc_editBtn" href="#"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="epi_dc_previewBtn" href="#"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; Around &lt;a href="https://www.ictsd.org/bridges-news/bridges/news/eu-canada-confirm-ceta-provisional-application-date"&gt;90 per cent of CETA&lt;/a&gt; will come into force on a provisional basis on 21 September, even before it gains approval from the EU’s national and regional parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace Netherlands trade campaigner Kees Kodde &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It is unacceptable for CETA to come into force before national parliaments have had their say. Canada has weaker food safety and labelling standards than the EU, and industrial agriculture more heavily dependent on pesticides and GM crops. CETA gives Canadian and US multinationals the tools to undermine rules concerning cloning, GM crops, growth hormones and country of origin labelling, among others. Europe’s national parliaments must reject this dangerous deal and protect our food and farming.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;On 6 September the Belgian government &lt;a href="https://diplomatie.belgium.be/en/newsroom/news/2017/minister_reynders_submits_request_opinion_ceta"&gt;asked the European Court of Justice&lt;/a&gt; to rule on the legality of CETA’s controversial investment protection mechanism, amid concerns that it may be in conflict with European legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For details on the risks of CETA to European food safety, please see three new briefing papers by the Institute for Agriculture and Trade Policy and Greenpeace Netherlands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Summary.pdf"&gt;executive summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Regco-factsheet.pdf"&gt;regulatory cooperation, growth hormones, GM crops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_COOL-factsheet.pdf"&gt;country of origin labelling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Cloning-factsheet.pdf"&gt;animal cloning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde, Greenpeace Netherlands trade policy campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +31 (0)6 53623818, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Summary.pdf</value><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Regco-factsheet.pdf</value><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_COOL-factsheet.pdf</value><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170920-CETA_Cloning-factsheet.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-09-20 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU 2030 energy package: community power holds key to renewables transition</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-2030-energy-package-community-power-renewables-transition/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	In the coming days and weeks, European governments and Members of the European Parliament (MEPs) will have a crucial say on the direction and pace of the European Union’s renewable energy transition.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Proschim%20solar%20panels%20against%20lignite%20mining.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Proschim%20solar%20panels%20against%20lignite%20mining.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the draft laws under discussion - on the development of renewable energy and the redesign of the European electricity market - could prove instrumental in boosting Europe’s role in the global fight against climate change and in ensuring the EU meets its commitment to help limit global temperature increase to 1.5°C. The new rules would apply between 2021 and 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The choice that MEPs and governments face is between an outdated energy model that relies heavily on centralised electricity production from coal, gas and nuclear energy, and a cutting-edge distributed system which would allow millions of individuals and local communities to produce, use and sell renewable electricity. The current system is controlled by a handful of heavily subsidised companies, but the transformation of Europe’s energy model would trigger a democratic breakthrough, with citizens across Europe producing their own affordable renewable energy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table style="border-color: #000000; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid;"&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Tara Connolly &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“It’s time for European governments to embrace the 21st century’s technical revolution in favour of a renewable-powered future for everyone. Clinging to the past would be a triple blow: denying citizens access to cheap, renewable energy, while using their taxes to subsidise power companies and pick up the tab for the health and climate impacts of fossil fuels.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;pre dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Some measures being considered would enable Europeans to take a more active role in the energy transition by, for example, installing smart meters or investing in solar panels. For the first time, the EU would recognise a universal right for citizens to produce, store and sell renewable electricity, free from punitive charges, including tariffs for access to the grid.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is campaigning for households to be entitled to a fair payment for the electricity they feed into the grid, and for renewable energy community projects to have equal access to project tenders and financing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br class="kix-line-break"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Community or citizen energy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; has an enormous and largely untapped potential. A &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;report by CE Delft&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, commissioned by Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth, REScoop.eu and EREF in 2016, showed that over 112 million energy citizens could meet 19 per cent of Europe’s electricity demand by 2030. By 2050, over 264 million Europeans - half of all EU citizens - could produce as much as 45 per cent of Europe’s electricity demand.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/1uf94XWmQ1-JSNQm6EYO8G7kPATPiADzzE8pt8qSYyQopv9e5NGlTQVsvHHpHQz0TROuLeCmKiMjLzgEloJ6g_5U9-FJlmSgixGdKE6yTlR9P4edJt9lPCTJMRMHm9FLxrlU-kz-" alt="" width="289" height="259"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;By making the right choices today, the next decade could see households, local cooperatives, cities and small businesses massively investing in renewables to power everything from schools to businesses. Citizen energy can also help tackle energy poverty through so-called ‘social solar’ public projects that provide low-income households with access to cheap, affordable renewable energy, instead of giving them money to heat their homes with fossil fuels.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fossil fuel subsidies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;European policymakers are also considering so-called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;capacity mechanisms&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, which would funnel taxpayers’ money to power companies just to keep uneconomic power plants on standby as backup for potential power shortages. However, Europe has more power plants than are necessary to meet its energy needs. This means subsidies are rarely justified and merely delay the inevitable shutdown of some of the most polluting and unsafe coal, nuclear and gas plants in Europe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Capacity mechanisms are costly. For instance, the UK has awarded capacity payments worth &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;£&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;4.8 billion (€5.4 billion) over a period of just three years. Poland’s planned capacity market is expected to cost as much as zł90 billion (€21.4 billion). This money could instead be used to accelerate the transition to renewable energy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Commission has proposed important but insufficient conditions on capacity mechanisms. These include regular mandatory European mapping of available energy resources to be carried out by European grid operators in order to identify legitimate needs. The Commission also proposes to include all technologies in capacity mechanisms (including renewables and batteries for energy storage) and to exclude new coal plants from 2020 but existing coal plants only after 2025.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does the European Parliament stand?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The EU’s 2030 climate and energy targets are far from adequate and incompatible with the objectives of the Paris climate agreement. Greenpeace supports a 2030 renewable energy target of at least 45 per cent, as a step towards an electricity system entirely powered by renewables by 2050. In addition, the EU should continue to set binding national renewables targets for the period after 2020, ensuring governments are accountable for their contributions to the overall EU target.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;On 28 November 2017, the European Parliament’s energy committee supported an increase of the renewables target from 27 to 35 per cent. However, it also recommended a 10 per cent leeway that would effectively reduce this target to 31.5 per cent. It did not back national renewable targets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;On the other hand, the committee recognised the right of Europeans to produce and sell their own renewable electricity, free from punitive charges, levies and taxes. It also recommended restrictions on access to capacity mechanisms to guard against market distortions. These restrictions include having to prove that there is a real risk of power cuts in the absence of payments.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are governments saying?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Council negotiations are ongoing. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greece&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Belgium&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hungary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; have expressed support for citizen energy. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germany&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;supported by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;France&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; and the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, have sided with power companies and are working against greater energy democracy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Many governments, including the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netherlands&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Denmark&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;are opposed to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;capacity mechanisms &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and want robust energy mapping. The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;France&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Italy&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ireland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; on the other hand want to set up long-term capacity schemes without robust mapping. The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netherlands &lt;/strong&gt;is siding with &lt;strong&gt;Denmark&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Sweden&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Finland&lt;/strong&gt; in wanting to exclude new coal plants from capacity mechanisms, while &lt;strong&gt;Spain&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Poland&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Greece&lt;/strong&gt; are strongly opposed to such restrictions. &lt;strong&gt;Germany&lt;/strong&gt; has stopped short of fully excluding coal from mechanisms as they want them to be eligible for certain types of schemes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy timeline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Commission releases package of policy proposals, dubbed the clean energy for all Europeans package, to achieve the 2030 targets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;28 November 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: European Parliament energy committee votes on renewable energy proposals.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18 December 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: European energy ministers meeting in Brussels expected to come to a preliminary agreement on renewable energy and power market reform proposals.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Parliament plenary votes on renewable energy proposals.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: European Parliament energy committee votes on electricity market reform.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;26 February 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Energy Council expected to adopt formal position on renewable energy and electricity market proposals.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: expected start of trialogue negotiations between the Parliament and Council on both files.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly - Greenpeace EU energy policy director&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)477 790416, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;tara.connolly@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang - Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)479 601289, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-01 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/1uf94XWmQ1-JSNQm6EYO8G7kPATPiADzzE8pt8qSYyQopv9e5NGlTQVsvHHpHQz0TROuLeCmKiMjLzgEloJ6g_5U9-FJlmSgixGdKE6yTlR9P4edJt9lPCTJMRMHm9FLxrlU-kz-</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Proschim%20solar%20panels%20against%20lignite%20mining.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Rush to adopt EU-Canada trade deal would increase distrust in mainstream politics</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Rush-to-adopt-EU-Canada-trade-deal-would-widen-distrust-in-mainstream-politics/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – The accelerated application of an EU-Canada trade deal (CETA) - as proposed today by the European Commission - would increase distrust in mainstream politics and threaten democracy and environmental protection, warned Greenpeace. The Commission is pressing for a swift application of CETA, before national parliaments are allowed to take a vote.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ceta%20pic.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ceta%20pic.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission recognises that the agreement requires the approval of national parliaments, but insists that the deal should apply even before parliaments can take a vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace calls on EU governments to reject CETA to protect environmental, health and labour standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace international executive director Jennifer Morgan&lt;/strong&gt; said:&lt;em&gt; “In the midst of widespread discontent with mainstream politics epitomised by Brexit, politicians should listen to growing public criticism of trade deals like CETA and TTIP. Applying CETA before national parliament approval would just add fuel to the fire.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU director Jorgo Riss &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“If the EU Commission and some national governments have their way, CETA would line up environmental and social protection like dominos in a row. Big business could easily send them tumbling using special courts designed to wipe out anything that stands in the way of private profits. The EU should instead protect people and nature against corporate privilege and safeguard democracy and environmental, health and social standards.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most contentious areas in CETA is the so-called Investment Court System, which allows multinationals to challenge government public policy outside existing national and EU courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU trade ministers are expected to discuss and then vote on the Commission proposal for CETA ratification at meetings in September and October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CETA is widely seen as a test for the troubled TTIP agreement - an EU-US trade deal that is currently under negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-07-05 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ceta%20pic.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU governments reject Commission push for glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-governments-reject-Commission-push-for-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - European governments have again refused to support a European Commission plan to grant a shortened but unrestricted licence for glyphosate, Europe’s most widely used weedkiller that has been linked to cancer and environmental harm.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STR9J0_Web_size.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STR9J0_Web_size.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission is now expected to take the same proposal to a vote in the so-called appeals committee, where it is also expected to fail. Thereafter, the Commission has the power to adopt its own proposal without the backing of European governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Reacting to the news, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Commission is trying to ram through a new glyphosate licence despite massive scandals surrounding its main maker and the EU’s own risk assessment. A new licence is a new licence, regardless of its length. If the Commission continues to allow this toxic chemical to contaminate our soils, water, food and bodies, it is simply rewarding Monsanto for obscuring the dangers linked to its weedkiller. The EU needs to ban it now, not in three, five or ten more years.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Since early 2016, the Commission has backed an unrestricted EU licence for glyphosate. On six occasions it failed to garner sufficient support for its proposal from European governments (on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Glyphosate-licence-renewal-suspended-in-light-of-health-concerns-/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;8 March 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Greenpeace-comment-on-EU-glyphosate-decision/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; 19 May 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Greenpeace-comment-EU-vote-on-glyphosate-extension/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;6 June 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Commission-must-prepare-glyphosate-exit-plan/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;24 June 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Growing-number-EU-governments-oppose-glyphosate/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;25 October 2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;). Nine countries representing 32.26% of the EU population voted against a five-year renewal of the glyphosate licence (Austria, Belgium, Greece, Croatia, Cyprus, France, Italy, Luxembourg, Malta), while five countries representing 30.79% of the EU population abstained (Bulgaria, Germany, Poland, Portugal and Romania). Fourteen countries voted in favour representing 36.95% of the EU population (Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Ireland, Spain, Latvia, Lithuania, Finland, Hungary, the Netherlands, Slovenia, Slovakia, Sweden and the U.K.).&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Serious concerns have been raised about the influence glyphosate manufacturers may have had on the EU’s evaluation of the risks linked to glyphosate. EFSA has come under fire after it was revealed that large sections of its glyphosate assessment rejecting independent scientific evidence were &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/sep/15/eu-report-on-weedkiller-safety-copied-text-from-monsanto-study"&gt;&lt;span&gt;copied&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; from an application submitted by Monsanto. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Monsanto Papers have also raised questions about the corporate capture of the glyphosate regulatory process. The inspector general of the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/epa-inspector-general-probing-collusion-with-monsanto_us_59372108e4b0aba888b99dca?ncid=engmodushpmg00000004"&gt;&lt;span&gt;launched an investigation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; into potential collusion between a former senior staff member and Monsanto.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament has called for a full glyphosate ban within five years, starting with immediate restrictions, including for non-professional uses and pre-harvest spraying. The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/foeeurope/status/928198158072582144"&gt;&lt;span&gt;governments&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of France, Belgium, Luxembourg, Slovenia and Malta have similarly called for a ban within the next few years but have not yet proposed immediate restrictions that would lend credibility to this commitment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Over one million people have signed a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;European citizen’s initiative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; calling for a glyphosate ban, while&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sumofus.org/media/new-glyphosate-polls-2017-en"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;polling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in Germany, France, Italy, Portugal and Greece shows growing concern and overwhelming support for a ban.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Experts, including Germany’s &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dw.com/en/farming-without-glyphosate-how-would-that-work/a-41104393"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Julius Kühn Institute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, have argued that farming without glyphosate does not need to come at an additional cost. Progressive farmers’ associations, such as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://confederationpaysanne.fr/actu.php?id=6342&amp;amp;PHPSESSID=a90ts088jka535u0sb75sio8q6"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Confédération Paysanne&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in France and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.abl-ev.de/apendix/news/details/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=1511&amp;amp;cHash=0eaa336578c01cc6a0e885a81d7ae96f"&gt;&lt;span&gt;AbL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in Germany, support a glyphosate ban and a transition to pesticide-free farming.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-09 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STR9J0_Web_size.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EUaffairs</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission green light for Paks state aid ignores Orbán takeover of nuclear regulator</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-Paks-state-aid-Orban-nuclear-regulator/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - The European Commission has given a green light to state subsidies for the construction of the Paks II nuclear power plant in Hungary. The decision is irresponsible and ignores prime minister Viktor Orbán’s takeover of Hungary’s nuclear regulator, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Paks%20Budapest%20protest.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Paks%20Budapest%20protest.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new law approved by the Hungarian Parliament in early December allows the government to overrule the country’s nuclear regulator on matters related to the construction of nuclear reactors and radioactive waste storage facilities. Greenpeace warned that government control threatens the regulator’s independence and its ability to enforce nuclear safety measures. The independence and transparency of national regulators is a basic safeguard enshrined in the Euratom Treaty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU legal adviser Andrea Carta &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“The Commission is being spectacularly irresponsible: it’s allowing massive subsidies for a project backed by a government that openly challenges the importance of independent oversight for nuclear safety. The EU competition watchdog uses the Euratom treaty to justify state aid, but ignores the treaty when it clearly conflicts with Hungary’s takeover of its nuclear regulator. The Commission’s decision means Paks will have an unfair advantage on the energy market, making it harder for renewable energy to compete.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hungary wants Rosatom – a state-owned Russian company – to build two new reactors at the Paks nuclear plant. The Commission launched an infringement case after Hungary awarded the contract without holding an open tender, but &lt;a href="http://www.politico.eu/article/eu-approves-hungary-nuclear-deal-amid-oettinger-controversy"&gt;Brussels approved&lt;/a&gt; the Rosatom deal in November 2016. The Commission has &lt;a href="https://www.asktheeu.org/en/request/3604/response/12207/attach/3/Access%20to%20documents%20request%20MAURO%20GESTDEM%202016%207131%20Redacted.pdf"&gt;refused&lt;/a&gt; to explain how it reached this decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia plans to finance the reactors through an international loan, as stipulated in a 2014 nuclear cooperation agreement with Hungary. Paks II is expected to cost around €12.5 billion. The Hungarian government has &lt;a href="http://www.kormany.hu/en/prime-minister-s-office/news/janos-lazar-expects-major-progress-in-case-of-paks-project"&gt;repeatedly denied&lt;/a&gt; that the project would require state aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace Hungary energy campaigner András Perger&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;With today’s decision&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;the Commission recognises that Paks can only go ahead with public subsidies. But it’s not over yet. We intend to challenge the project’s environmental license, &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;which breaches several national and international laws. The Hungarian government has mislead its people: Paks II is not economically viable and it will cost taxpayers dearly.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrea Carta&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU legal strategist: +32 (0)496 16 15 82, &lt;a href="mailto:andrea.carta@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;andrea.carta@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;András Perger&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace Hungary climate and energy campaigner: +36 20 371 1266, &lt;a href="mailto:andras.perger@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;andras.perger@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is also available on: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.asktheeu.org/en/request/3604/response/12207/attach/3/Access%20to%20documents%20request%20MAURO%20GESTDEM%202016%207131%20Redacted.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-06 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Nuclear</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Paks%20Budapest%20protest.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>PeoplePower</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU Parliament backs people-powered renewables but aims too low</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-parliament-backs-people-power/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Energy committee plan would undo Spain’s controversial ‘sun tax’&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Parliament’s energy committee voted today to recognise the right of Europeans to produce and sell their own renewable electricity.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/hanging%20solar_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/hanging%20solar_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee approved amendments to the EU’s renewable energy rules that would make self-consumed electricity free from punitive charges, levies and taxes. This would make Spain’s controversial ‘sun tax’ illegal under EU rules. The ‘sun tax’ forces Spanish solar panel owners to pay for the electricity they produce and consume themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Sebastian Mang&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The Parliament recognises that every European should have the right to produce, consume and sell renewable energy, but it’s unrealistically pessimistic when it comes to the EU’s renewables target. Just like nobody would force Messi to play in the Belgian third division, playing European citizens at the front of the energy transition only makes sense if they can reach their full potential.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy committee also said 35 per cent of the EU’s energy should come from renewables by 2030. In 2014, European governments suggested a target of 27 per cent and, in 2016, the European Commission supported this target. But the committee supported a loophole that would allow EU countries a ten per cent leeway on the proposed 35 per cent target. This could lower the mandatory share of renewables in 2030 to only 31.5 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee also failed to support binding renewables targets for each EU country. With no binding national targets after 2020, the EU could find it harder to hold governments accountable for insufficient contributions to the overall EU target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential of people-powered renewables&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf"&gt;report by CE Delft&lt;/a&gt; released by Greenpeace last year shows that, with the right support, half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity by 2050, meeting nearly half of the EU’s electricity demand. Power companies would provide the remainder of Europe’s renewable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To limit global temperature increase to 1.5 degrees, as agreed at the Paris climate conference in 2015, the EU must increase its renewable energy target to at least 45 per cent by 2030, and transition to a system entirely powered by renewables within a generation, warned Greenpeace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU is currently deciding the future of its energy system through the revision of wide-ranging legislation covering renewable energy policy, fossil fuel subsidies and the design of the electricity market. The European Commission’s proposals were published in November 2016, branded as the ‘&lt;em&gt;Clean energy for all Europeans’&lt;/em&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from today’s vote on the renewables directive, the Parliament’s energy committee is expected to vote on the reform of electricity market rules in February 2018. The full Parliament will then vote on both files in early 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy ministers from all EU countries will meet on 18 December 2017 in Brussels to come to a preliminary Council agreement on the planned reforms, in preparation for negotiations with the Parliament in the spring and summer of 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang - Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser: &lt;/strong&gt;+32 (0)479 601289, &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;:+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-28 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/hanging%20solar_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>ToxicChemicals</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU report on pesticide residues ignores toxic cocktail effect, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-report-on-pesticide-residues-ignores-toxic-cocktail-effect-Greenpeace/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – An EU report on pesticide residues in food released today again fails to assess the combined effects of pesticides in the human body, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p style="background: white; margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Fungicide_spraying_vinyard_Switzerland_2016.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Fungicide_spraying_vinyard_Switzerland_2016.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; The 2017 edition of the annual &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.2903/j.efsa.2017.4791/full"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0563c1; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;report&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; by the European Food Safety Authority, reports on almost 85,000 samples analysed for an average 220 pesticides per sample. Residues of multiple pesticides were found in all food categories tested and 28 per cent of samples overall.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="background: white; margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="background: white; margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;In unprocessed foods, the highest occurrence of multiple pesticide residues was found in hops, several soft fruits (including &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px; color: black;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;gooseberries, currants, limes, rocket, table grapes, grapefruits, strawberries, mandarins, and blackberries)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; and lamb’s lettuce. For processed food, the highest occurrence was found in samples of mushrooms, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px; color: black;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;processed grapes (e.g. raisins), peppers (e.g. paprika powder), wine grapes, vine leaves, processed apricots and potatoes (e.g. chips).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="background: white; margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px; color: black;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Dr. Paul Johnston, head of the Greenpeace Science Unit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;, said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;"In its latest report, EFSA has an overly up-beat interpretation of the data. The fact that so many samples contain more than one pesticide is a cause for concern and an indication that current regulation – based on the control of single pesticides – does not adequately protect people. We are all exposed to a cocktail of pesticides, rather than to single substances, and the toxicology of mixtures remains poorly understood.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Several studies have stressed the need to strengthen the risk assessment of chemical mixtures [1.2].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Notes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; Kienzler , A., Bopp, S.K. , van der Linden, S., Berggren, E. &amp;amp; Worth, A., (2016): &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Regulatory assessment of chemical mixtures: Requirements, current approaches and future perspectives&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology 80: 321-334.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; Kienzler, A., Berggren, E., Bessems, J., Bopp, S., van der Linden, S. &amp;amp; Worth, A., (2014): &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Assessment of mixtures – Review of Regulatory Requirements and Guidance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;. European Commission Joint Research Centre Report EUR 26675 EN, 123pp.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Contacts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Dr. Paul Johnston&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt; – Head of the Greenpeace Science Unit: +44 7813 8905492, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:paul.johnston@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;paul.johnston@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0563c1; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin: 0px; line-height: normal;"&gt;&lt;span style="margin: 0px;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri; font-size: medium;"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-04-11 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Fungicide_spraying_vinyard_Switzerland_2016.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>#TTIPleaks: confidential TTIP papers unveil US position</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/TTIPleaks-confidential-TTIP-papers-unveil-US-position/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Leaked text shows attempts to undermine EU environment and health protection laws&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 1 May 2016  – Greenpeace Netherlands has obtained 248 pages of leaked Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP) negotiating texts [1], which will be published on Monday 2 May at 11:00 CET. The documents unveil for the first time the US position and deliberate attempts to change the EU democratic legislative process.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GP%20NL%20pic.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GP%20NL%20pic.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classified documents represent more than two-thirds of the overall TTIP text as of April, at the 13th round of TTIP negotiations in New York. They cover 13 chapters addressing issues ranging from telecommunications to regulatory cooperation, from pesticides, food and agriculture to trade barriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jorgo Riss, director of Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“These leaked documents confirm what we have been saying for a long time: TTIP would put corporations at the centre of policy-making, to the detriment of environment and public health. We have known that the EU position was bad, now we see the US position is even worse. A compromise between the two would be unacceptable.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace identified four main issues of concern:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long standing environmental protection is dropped&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “General Exceptions” rule, enshrined in the GATT agreement of the World Trade Organisation (WTO), is absent from the text. This nearly 70-year-old rule allows nations to restrict trade “&lt;em&gt;to protect human, animal and plant life or health&lt;/em&gt;", or for "&lt;em&gt;the conservation of exhaustible natural resources&lt;/em&gt;" [2].             &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No place for climate protection in TTIP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the goals of the Paris Summit to keep temperatures increase under 1.5 degrees are to be met, trade should not be excluded from CO2 emissions reduction specifications. But nothing about climate protection can be found in the obtained texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precautionary principle is forgotten&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US wants the EU to replace the EU’s hazard approach with ‘risk management’, disregarding the precautionary principle, [3] which is enshrined in the EU Treaty but is never mentioned in the consolidated text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open door for corporate lobbying&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaked documents suggest that both parties consider giving corporations much wider access and participation in decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jorgo Riss&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The effects of TTIP would be initially subtle but ultimately devastating. It would lead to European laws being judged on their consequences for trade and investment – disregarding environmental protection and public health concerns.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Greenpeace Netherlands received a confidential document that was possibly edited in order to identify the source of a leak. Greenpeace retyped the document removing modifications that could have allowed to trace the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href="https://www.wto.org/english/docs_e/legal_e/gatt47_02_e.htm#articleXX"&gt;https://www.wto.org/english/docs_e/legal_e/gatt47_02_e.htm#articleXX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The precautionary principle also covers consumer policy, European legislation concerning food and human, animal and plant health:&lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=URISERV%3Al32042"&gt; http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=URISERV%3Al32042&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-01 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GP%20NL%20pic.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Renewables</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU energy plans won’t meet Paris climate commitments</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-energy-plans-wont-meet-Paris-climate-commitments/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Today the European Commission releases its report on the progress of the European Union’s energy plans, the ‘State of the Energy Union’. Greenpeace has criticised the EU’s energy plans as inadequate to meet the challenge of climate change and the commitments made at the 2015 Paris climate conference.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Portugal%20RES.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Portugal%20RES.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Sebastian Mang&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The EU’s current energy plans don’t come close to the scale of action needed to meet the threat of climate change. To keep global warming below 1.5 degrees, as agreed in Paris, the EU must accelerate its move to 100 per cent renewable energy, and it must scrap subsidies for fossil fuels. Most of all, the EU must ensure that all citizens can access, benefit from and contribute to renewable energy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;                                                &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace is calling on the European Union to:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respond with urgency to the climate change crisis, by accelerating its transition to 100 per cent renewables and the phase-out of coal. The EU must exceed its current climate and energy targets, in order to meet its commitments made at the Paris climate change conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prioritise and incentivise renewable energy and smart and efficient energy use, including by giving citizens control over their energy use and production. Not least, because this will deliver sustainable jobs and make economic sense: the renewable energy sector employed over one million people in Europe in 2015 and this figure is steadily growing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Divest from fossil fuels, not least by halting harmful subsidies for fossil fuel and nuclear power, e.g. in the form of ‘capacity payments’ that keep dirty power plants in business. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%20479%2060%2012%2089" target="_blank"&gt;+32 (0)479 60 12 89&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%202%20274%2019%2011" target="_blank"&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1485985321298000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFQGblnUCMeH-1lT6TKZPTOVXK5Eg"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-01 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Portugal%20RES.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU court ruling on Singapore trade deal is victory for democracy</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-court-ruling-singapore-trade-deal/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Court of Justice ruled today that the European Commission cannot conclude trade deals without the approval of EU national parliaments, when they contain investment dispute systems that supersede national courts.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2017-05/cp170052en.pdf" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2017-05/cp170052en.pdf&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1495014293366000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFqWzJVSek_tQFTq-psj5mXN1b9jQ"&gt; verdict on the EU trade deal with Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, Greenpeace calls on the European Commission to ensure transparency and respect democracy in future trade deals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade policy campaigner Kees Kodde&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This verdict is a victory for democracy. It forces the debate about the benefits and dangers of trade agreements out into the open. Without more transparency and accountability, the current trade system will continue harming people’s rights and our environment. Putting people and nature first could instead unlock trade as a force for good – not an end in itself, but a means to achieve social and environmental progress.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The ECJ said that EU trade agreements cannot remove investors’ disputes from the jurisdiction of the courts of the member states, without the member states’ consent. It confirms that the jurisdiction of national courts must be respected and that the Commission cannot negotiate a parallel court system for investors without the approval of national parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde, Greenpeace trade policy campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;: +31 (0)65 36 23 818, &lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%202%20274%2019%2011" target="_blank"&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1495014293366000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEzpo8WaRKFIIP7B7Tpdx1Lts-BXw"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2017-05/cp170052en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-16 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Political concerns delay agreement on CETA</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Political-concerns-delay-agreement-on-CETA/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Luxembourg/Brussels – CETA, a controversial EU-Canada trade deal, has suffered another major political setback today, as EU ministers did not agree on its ratification at a meeting in Luxembourg. As the meeting got underway on Tuesday morning, Greenpeace climbers and activists joined other NGOs and trade unions from across Europe to protest against the deal.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016-10-18_Greenpeace_Stop-Ceta-2788.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016-10-18_Greenpeace_Stop-Ceta-2788.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the ongoing disagreements over CETA, &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser Shira Stanton&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Public opposition to dangerous trade deals has sent a shockwave through the corridors of power. After years of secret negotiations and last-minute declarations to paper over the cracks, it’s no surprise that CETA does not have unanimous political support. The disagreements among ministers show how out of touch most of them are with their citizens. It’s time to hit the reset button and put people, health and environmental protection at the heart of trade policy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the ministers agree, CETA would provisionally come into force after the approval of the European Parliament - a vote is scheduled for late 2016 or early 2017. However, ministers are expected to exclude a controversial investment protection system - known as ICS - from provisional application. However, ICS could come into force after ratification by national and regional EU parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these continued uncertainties, the EU and Canada are still aiming to sign CETA at a summit in Brussels on 27 October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shira Stanton (in Luxembourg) &lt;/strong&gt;-Greenpeace EU trade policy adviser: +32 (0)477 790 415, &lt;a href="mailto:shira.stanton@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;shira.stanton@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is also available on:&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-10-18 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016-10-18_Greenpeace_Stop-Ceta-2788.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Bioenergy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU must stop palm oil deforestation, says European Parliament</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-stop-palm-oil-deforestation-Parliament/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Palm oil industry identified as major cause of forest destruction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Parliament voted in favour of a report calling on the EU to stop funding and contributing to deforestation. The report recognises the driving forces behind deforestation, in particular agricultural expansion and the production of palm oil. There were 640 votes in favour of the report, 18 against and 28 abstentions.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Sebastien Risso, Greenpeace EU forest policy director,&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The Parliament is right to recognise the huge responsibility that the EU has to stop deforestation, and how important this is for climate action and sustainable development. We are at one minute to midnight – the European Commission must not lose more time in putting forward an EU action plan to make Europe a deforestation-free economy and turn the tide on global forest destruction.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The parliamentary report adopted today:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Identifies the drivers of deforestation, highlights the crucial role of forests for climate mitigation and sustainable development, and the commitments made by the EU to take action to preserve and restore forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Analyses the magnitude of the environmental and social impacts resulting from palm oil production, and the particular responsibility of the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Recognises that industry self-regulation is not enough to stop deforestation, and points to the weak standards and enforcement levels of the main certification schemes for sustainable palm oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Recognises that it is possible to produce palm oil in a responsible way, e.g. with the use of the High-Carbon Stock approach and the standards developed by the Palm Oil Innovation Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Calls on the European Commission to develop an EU action plan on deforestation which would include concrete regulatory measures to make EU supply chains and financial transactions deforestation-free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Calls for a phase-out, by 2020, of the use of biofuels based on vegetable oils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Calls on the European Commission and EU member states to provide support to developing countries for implementing environmentally and socially responsible production practices, and for securing the rights and livelihoods of indigenous peoples and local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastien Risso, Greenpeace EU forest policy director:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)496 12 70 09, &lt;a href="mailto:srisso@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;srisso@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-04-04 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Industry ties raise questions about UN body assessing glyphosate cancer risk</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Industry-ties-JMPR-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – The FAO /WHO Joint Meeting on Pesticide Residues (JMPR) released an assessment today, which concludes that the controversial weedkiller glyphosate is “unlikely to pose a carcinogenic risk to humans from exposure through the diet” [1]. The finding contradicts an earlier assessment by the WHO’s International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), which stated that glyphosate was a probable cause of cancer. However, the industry ties of at least two experts involved in the JMPR’s evaluation call into question whether the organisation has ensured the independence of its advice. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20vienna.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20vienna.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt;: Since the publication of this press release, Alan Boobis, one of the scientists named below has been identified as the chair of the JMPR glyphosate panel. For more information see &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2016/may/17/unwho-panel-in-conflict-of-interest-row-over-glyphosates-cancer-risk"&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://abonnes.lemonde.fr/planete/article/2016/05/17/une-expertise-favorable-au-roundup-suscite-la-colere-des-ong_4920523_3244.html"&gt;Le Monde&lt;/a&gt; (paywall, in French).]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Boobis and Angelo Moretto (please see more information below) have ties to the International Life Sciences Institute (ILSI). ILSI Europe receives a &lt;a href="http://www.ilsi.org/Europe/Pages/FAQ.aspx"&gt;majority of its operating and research funding&lt;/a&gt; from private companies [2], including glyphosate producers &lt;a href="http://www.ilsi.org/Europe/Pages/currentmembers.aspx"&gt;Dow and Monsanto&lt;/a&gt;. ILSI’s Health and Environmental Sciences Institute (HESI) is &lt;a href="http://www.hesiglobal.org/i4a/pages/index.cfm?pageid=3386"&gt;primarily&lt;/a&gt; funded by private companies, including glyphosate producers &lt;a href="http://www.hesiglobal.org/i4a/pages/index.cfm?pageid=3644"&gt;Dow, Monsanto and Syngenta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;Most scientists involved in the glyphosate assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), which also contradicted the WHO cancer warning, &lt;a href="http://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/attachments/annex_i_.pdf"&gt;refused to be named&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said:&lt;em&gt; “The agencies contradicting the WHO cancer warning seem to either rely on officials who prefer not to be named, or lack a watertight policy to protect their impartiality. Any decision affecting millions of people should be based on fully transparent and independent science that isn’t tied to corporate interests. It would be irresponsible to ignore the warnings on glyphosate and to re-licence this pesticide without any restrictions to protect the public and the environment.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the WHO reportedly &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1570087/"&gt;barred ILSI&lt;/a&gt; from taking part in activities related to &lt;em&gt;“setting microbiological or chemical standards for food and water”&lt;/em&gt;. The EFSA no longer allows its panel members to &lt;a href="http://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/ilsi-article-final.pdf"&gt;also work with ILSI&lt;/a&gt;. In 2010/11, two people (Diana Banati and Milan Kovac) had to step down from ILSI roles in order to be part of the EFSA management board. The board viewed ILSI as “&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/corporate101021"&gt;representing interests of the food chain, other than public interests&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;Media reports indicate that the European Commission wants to extend the EU glyphosate licence &lt;a href="http://farmfutures.com/story-worlds-1-herbicide-said-face-shorter-eu-reauthorization-17-140898"&gt;by nine years or more&lt;/a&gt;, without EU-wide restrictions on its use, based on the EFSA assessment. The European Parliament requested restrictions to limit public exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;----------&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alan Boobis&lt;/strong&gt; is currently the &lt;a href="http://www.ilsi.org/Europe/Pages/Board-of-Directors.aspx"&gt;Vice-President of ILSI Europe&lt;/a&gt;. He is the &lt;a href="http://www.risk21.org/?page_id=82"&gt;co-chair of the RISK21&lt;/a&gt; project run by ILSI’s Health and Environmental Sciences Institute (HESI). Boobis has been an active member of ILSI over many years and also acted as a consultant for companies such as &lt;a href="http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/contacts/boobisa_DI.pdf"&gt;Sumitomo Chemical&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angelo Moretto&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;a href="http://www.risk21.org/?page_id=82"&gt;member of the steering team of the RISK21 project&lt;/a&gt;. He is also a &lt;a href="http://www.hesiglobal.org/i4a/pages/index.cfm?pageid=3477"&gt;member of the HESI Board of Trustees&lt;/a&gt;. Moretto resigned from an EFSA panel on pesticides after reportedly &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/corporate_publications/files/independencepolicyreport0712.pdf"&gt;failing to declare a financial interest&lt;/a&gt; related to the assessment of chemical substances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/foodsafety/jmprsummary2016.pdf?ua=1"&gt;http://www.who.int/foodsafety/jmprsummary2016.pdf?ua=1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Default"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2]&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://usrtk.org/pesticides/conflict-of-interest-concerns-cloud-meeting-as-international-experts-review-herbicide-risks/"&gt;US Right to Know&lt;/a&gt; have published a document that appears to be ILSI’s 2012 major donor list. It shows total contributions of $2.4 million (€2.12 million), with more than $500,000 (€442,000) each from CropLife International and from Monsanto. &lt;a href="https://t.co/zDqfzRJHrJ"&gt;https://t.co/zDqfzRJHrJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/attachments/annex_i_.pdf</value><value>http://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/ilsi-article-final.pdf</value><value>http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/contacts/boobisa_DI.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/corporate_publications/files/independencepolicyreport0712.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-16 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/glyphosate%20vienna.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission prepares to authorise three GM maize varieties</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-prepares-to-authorise-three-GM-maizes/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - The European Commission and a handful of EU governments want Europe to grow more genetically modified (GM) crops. In the coming months, they want to authorise the cultivation of two GM maize varieties (DuPont Pioneer’s 1507 and Syngenta’s Bt11), and to renew the licence for another maize (Monsanto’s maize MON810), the only GM crop currently grown in the EU. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATED - This briefing was updated on 24 January to reflect EFSA’s latest opinion, the European Parliament’ objections and the European Commission’s revised calendar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STPI5C_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STPI5C_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed authorisations would only be valid in 9 out of 28 European Union (EU) countries, as well as in three regions (England in the UK, Flanders and the Brussels region in Belgium). The other EU countries and the remaining four regions in the UK and Belgium have used the EU’s new &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/gmo/authorisation/cultivation/geographical_scope_en.htm"&gt;opt-out mechanism&lt;/a&gt; to prevent GMOs from being grown on their territories, regardless of EU authorisations. The Commission is hoping that national governments will accept EU approval of GM crops as long as they are able to rule out their cultivation in their own territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;GM crops have no place in sustainable farming. Rightly, the majority of EU governments and parliamentarians have rejected them. But now it’s time for all EU countries to think beyond their borders. Governments should oppose environmentally damaging GM crops anywhere, not just in their own backyard, to protect wildlife and allow farmers and consumers to go GM-free&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201701%20BR%20GM%20maize%20authorisations%20FINAL_teosinte_EP_vote.pdf"&gt;Read the full media briefing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201701%20BR%20GM%20maize%20authorisations%20FINAL_teosinte_EP_vote.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-01-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STPI5C_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU chemicals agency sweeps glyphosate cancer evidence under the carpet</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-chemicals-agency-sweeps-glyphosate-cancer-evidence-under-the-carpet/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Following in the footsteps of the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) has dismissed scientific evidence showing that the controversial weedkiller glyphosate could cause cancer.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ECHA assessment &lt;/strong&gt;could pave the way for a new 15-year EU licence for the world’s most heavily used weedkiller, which the World Health Organisation’s cancer research agency (IARC) has classified as a &lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;“probable” cause of cancer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reach its conclusion, ECHA rejected glaring scientific evidence of cancers in laboratory animals, ignored warnings by more than 90 independent scientists, and relied on unpublished studies commissioned by glyphosate producers, warned Greenpeace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;ECHA has gone to great lengths to sweep all evidence that glyphosate can cause cancer under the carpet. The data vastly exceeds what’s legally necessary for the EU to ban glyphosate, but ECHA has looked the other way. For the EU to make decisions based on science, it can’t distort the facts. If the EU doesn’t get this right, people and the environment will continue to be the lab rats of the chemical industry.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the EFSA assessment, the ECHA opinion was based on an initial dossier prepared by the German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment (BfR). BfR’s glyphosate assessment has been heavily criticised by &lt;a href="http://www.pan-germany.org/download/PAN_Germany_Addendum_analysis_09112015.pdf"&gt;NGOs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf"&gt;independent scientists&lt;/a&gt;, who said it contradicted the scientific evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ECHA is responsible for the EU’s classification and labelling of hazardous chemical substances. Under &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2008:353:0001:1355:en:PDF"&gt;EU criteria&lt;/a&gt;, a substance must be classified as a &lt;em&gt;“presumed”&lt;/em&gt; carcinogen if it is shown to increase cancer rates in at least two separate studies conducted on the same species. IARC found evidence of increased rates in two mouse studies, supported by further evidence. However, ECHA dismissed the increased cancer rates observed in these studies, as well as in three additional mouse studies that were not available to IARC. ECHA also dismissed the &lt;em&gt;“limited”&lt;/em&gt; evidence of carcinogenicity in humans, and evidence of two characteristics associated with carcinogens, all documented by IARC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:32009R1107&amp;amp;from=EN"&gt;EU pesticides law&lt;/a&gt;, substances classified as &lt;em&gt;“presumed”&lt;/em&gt; carcinogens cannot be allowed for use, unless the exposure of people is &lt;em&gt;“negligible”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health and environmental organisations have also &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-on-the-independence-and-transparency-of-ECHAs-Risk-Assessment-Committee/"&gt;raised concerns&lt;/a&gt; about conflicts of interest in the ECHA committee responsible for assessing glyphosate, and criticised ECHA’s reliance on unpublished industry studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2017, a coalition of civil society organisations launched a &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;European Citizens’ Initiative&lt;/a&gt; calling on the European Commission to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU. Almost &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/500000-people-EU-ban-glyphosate/"&gt;500,000 people&lt;/a&gt; have already signed the petition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.pan-germany.org/download/PAN_Germany_Addendum_analysis_09112015.pdf</value><value>https://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>POLLUTION</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transport</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission shows narrow vision on renewable-powered shared mobility, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-narrow-vision-renewables-mobility/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – A package of policy measures for the transport sector released by the European Commission fails to deliver an ambitious vision of shared mobility powered by renewable energy, said Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Berlin%20mobility.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Berlin%20mobility.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Greenpeace EU climate policy director Ansgar Kiene&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“These measures are fundamentally held back by the 20th-century obsession with the passenger car and the combustion engine. Cities and governments across Europe are way ahead of the game, exposing the car lobby’s influence on the Commission. Only with fewer cars on the roads, a firm commitment to renewable energy, and better access to clean, smart and shared modes of transport can the EU meet its climate change targets and improve the air we breathe.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2013, greenhouse gas emissions from the EU’s transport sector have been steadily increasing. According to the European Environment Agency, road transport accounts for 73 per cent of transport emissions in Europe and 44.5 per cent of that comes from passenger cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene,&lt;/strong&gt; Greenpeace EU climate and energy adviser: +32 (0)476 961375, &lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-08 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Berlin%20mobility.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>People can power the Energy Revolution</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/People-can-power-the-Energy-Revolution/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Over half of citizens in the European Union could be generating their own renewable electricity by 2050, according to new research released today.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/PageFiles/739516/EU%20proportion%20of%20people.png" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/PageFiles/739516/EU%20proportion%20of%20people.png" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845"&gt;The research outlines the potential for citizen-owned renewable energy projects in Europe,&lt;/a&gt; where 264 million “energy citizens” could generate 45% of the European Union’s electricity needs by 2050 – as part of a democratised energy system. [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly Walsh, community power campaigner for Friends of the Earth Europe,&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“This shows that people have the power to revolutionise Europe’s energy system, reclaiming power from big energy companies, and putting the planet first. We need to enshrine the right for people to produce their own renewable energy in European and national legislation.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly, energy policy adviser for Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: “&lt;em&gt;The EU should be clearing a path for forward-thinking, nimble energy citizens, not supporting big, polluting utilities. The age of energy dinosaurs is over.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dirk Vansintjan, president of REScoop.eu&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“Citizens are already playing a role in renewable energy projects across Europe – benefiting the local economy, as well as creating public support for the energy transition. Their potential is huge, and this research shows these projects could, and should, be the norm.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organisations are calling for a framework to protect, support and promote energy citizens at the core of the European Commission’s Energy Union package – specifically as part of the revised Renewable Energy Directive and the Market Design Initiative. This call is in line with President Juncker’s stated objective for &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/cwt/files/commissioner_mission_letters/arias-canete-mission_en.pdf"&gt;“the EU to become the world number one in renewable energies”&lt;/a&gt; and with the European Commission’s vision of &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/en/TXT/?uri=COM%3A2015%3A80%3AFIN"&gt;“an Energy Union with citizens at its core”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 477 79 0416, &lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;tara.connolly@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] For the purposes of the report, energy citizens are defined as individuals or households producing renewable energy or managing their electricity demand flexibly either individually or collectively. The definition also includes public entities such as cities and municipal buildings, schools, hospitals or government buildings, as well as small businesses with fewer than 50 employees. Examples include solar panels on the roof of a home or small business, or participation in a collective wind or solar farm project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/cwt/files/commissioner_mission_letters/arias-canete-mission_en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-26 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/PageFiles/739516/EU%20proportion%20of%20people.png</value></imagesB></item>
</items>