<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU Commission plan allows chemical producers to keep control of science behind pesticide approvals, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Commission-chemical-pesticides-producers-control-science/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – A European Commission proposal to reform EU risk assessments for pesticides and other products entering the food chain would allow the chemical industry to remain in charge of testing its own products, warned Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Hazmats.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Hazmats.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the Commission wants industry studies submitted to the European Food Safety Authority to be made public. Under current rules, EFSA can only release summaries of the studies that are provided to support a product application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU spokesperson Mark Breddy&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The publication of test results supporting applications for pesticide approvals is the bare minimum. But the Commission is just papering over the cracks. Pesticide producers should not be allowed to control the testing of their own products. As a rule, this should be the job of the EU – not only in controversial cases – and should not be funded by taxpayers but by the companies who want their products approved.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s attempt to improve EU risk assessments is in response to the European Citizens' Initiative (ECI) on the controversial herbicide glyphosate. The ECI demanded that &lt;em&gt;“all studies used to back up regulatory approval of pesticides must be published”&lt;/em&gt;. The petition also asked that public authorities, not the industry seeking approval for its products, should be in charge of running the studies. [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt; For more information on the glyphosate ECI: &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/citizens-initiative/public/documents/3496"&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/citizens-initiative/public/documents/3496&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact: Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is available on:&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt; www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-11 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Hazmats.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>FossilFuels</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace comment on One Planet climate summit</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Greenpeace-comment-One-Planet-climate-summit/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Paris/Brussels – A climate summit hosted by French president Emmanuel Macron on the second anniversary of the Paris climate agreement has ended with a surprise commitment from the World Bank but no major announcements from governments.

&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The World Bank said that it would end investments in gas and oil exploration and extraction. But president Macron failed to make any meaningful announcement, only days before European ministers are due to debate the future of the continent’s climate and energy policies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commenting on the World Bank announcement, Greenpeace International climate campaigner Gyorgy Dallos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The end is clearly coming for the oil and gas industry as the pace of change accelerates. After the historic announcement by the world’s largest sovereign wealth fund, NBIM, the World Bank – one of the world's most powerful financial institutions – has sent a damning vote of no confidence on the future of the fossil fuel industry. The world’s financial institutions now need to take note and decide whether their financing is going to be part of the problem or the solution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Critically, we also welcome the World Bank taking the challenge to set a unifying standard for green bonds. This is much needed especially considering the ongoing review of the China Green Bond Catalogue, which still includes coal.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commenting on the One Planet climate summit, Greenpeace EU director Jorgo Riss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt; “Macron put on a grand show, but political leaders assembled outside Paris have little to show at the end of the conference. Europe is playing well below its potential on climate change and Macron’s empty words are not going to make a whole lot of difference. In Brussels, France fights much harder for its nuclear industry than for a transition to renewable energy and stands by while the likes of Spain and Poland seek subsidies for coal plants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Governments need to roll up their sleeves and get to work if Europe is to regain some of its credibility on climate change. They should start by raising the EU’s 2030 targets to cut greenhouse gases and increase the share of renewable energy."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The One Planet Summit precedes a meeting of EU energy ministers on 18 December to discuss the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-2030-energy-package-community-power-renewables-transition"&gt;&lt;span&gt;future of the bloc’s energy policy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. Talks will be focussed on a new EU policy package which includes renewable energy, energy efficiency and climate goals for 2030.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;France has done nothing to prevent Spain and Poland from lobbying to allow coal plants to access subsidies under the EU’s energy policy package, and has opposed measures to make it easier for Europeans to produce, store and sell their own renewable energy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace France climate campaigner Sarah Fayolle &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;added:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Emmanuel Macron claims he wants to celebrate the two-year anniversary of the Paris Agreement. But this is no time to celebrate: his government isn’t even able to comply with the French energy transition law.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If France really wants to play a leading role in the development of renewable energy on a national, European and international scale, it must end its support for nuclear energy and shut down its reactors. Nuclear energy is now more expensive than most renewable energy sources across the world. Saving the climate, requires the most effective solutions. Nuclear is not part of it. What we need is concrete action, not communication operations.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace International press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +31 (0)20 718 2470, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.int@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.int@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace France&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;: Méryl Sotty&lt;/strong&gt; - +33 (0)6 73 89 48 90, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:meryl.sotty@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:meryl.sotty@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;meryl.sotty@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; - &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br class="kix-line-break"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-12 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20power%20plant%20in%20Germany.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Governments and citizens reject GMOs, Commission must follow – Greenpeace </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Governments-citizens-reject-GMOs-MON810-Bt11-1507/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Today, national government representatives failed to support the approval of three genetically modified (GM) maize crops for cultivation in Europe: two new ones and the only GM crop currently grown in the EU.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Maize%202.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Maize%202.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While no qualified majority was reached [1, 2], the number of rejections shows that GMO opposition clearly outweighs support. It was the second vote by national governments on the European Commission’s proposals to approve the three GM crops. The &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/No-GMO-support/"&gt;first vote&lt;/a&gt;, held in January 2017, had also failed to deliver a qualified majority. Therefore, it is now up to the Commission to take the final decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;When he was elected, Commission President Juncker promised more democratic decision-making. This vote leaves no doubt that approving these GM crops would break that promise. A majority of governments, parliamentarians and Europeans oppose them, and two thirds of European countries ban GMO cultivation on their lands. Instead of backing risky products peddled by multinational corporations, the Commission should support ecological farming and the solutions it provides for rural areas, farmers and the environment.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Juncker said he “would not want the Commission to be able to take a decision when a majority of Member States has not encouraged it to do so” [3].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, his Commission proposed authorising the cultivation of DuPont Pioneer’s 1507 maize and Syngenta’s Bt11 maize, and to renew the licence for Monsanto’s maize MON810, the only GM crop currently grown in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If approved, the three authorisations would only be valid in 9 out of 28 EU countries, as well as in three regions (England in the UK, Flanders and the Brussels region in Belgium). The other EU countries and the remaining regions in the UK and Belgium have used the EU’s new &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/gmo/authorisation/cultivation/geographical_scope_en.htm"&gt;opt-out mechanism&lt;/a&gt; to prevent GM crops from being grown in their territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament has repeatedly clashed with the European Commission over its policy on genetically modified organisms (GMOs). In December 2015, &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P8-TA-2015-0456+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN&amp;amp;language=EN"&gt;it called for a moratorium on all GMO import authorisations&lt;/a&gt; until new decision-making rules are in place. It has opposed the authorisation of several GMOs for import to the EU and rejected the proposed authorisations of GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1085%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize 1507&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1083%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize Bt11&lt;/a&gt; and GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1086%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize MON810&lt;/a&gt; for cultivation in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GM crops have no place in sustainable farming. They come with unacceptable risks created by the genetic engineering process and the traits they are engineered to express. At the same time, they have &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Agriculture/Twenty-Years-of-Failure/"&gt;failed to deliver&lt;/a&gt; on the promises made by their producers. To protect the environment and our health, the European Union should ban GMOs and promote ecological farming methods instead of following the example of the US and the handful of other countries where GM crops are grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt; [1] A qualified majority is achieved when at least 16 countries, representing at least 65% of the European population, vote in favour or against.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] On &lt;strong&gt;GM maize MON810&lt;/strong&gt;, 14 EU countries voted against (AT, BG, CY, DK, EL, FR, IE, IT, HU, LT, LU, LV, PL, SI) representing 43.29 per cent of the EU population, eight EU countries voted in favour (CZ, EE, ES, FI, NL, RO, SE, UK) representing 34.45 per cent, and six abstained (BE, DE, HR, MT, PT, SK) representing 22.26 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;GM maize 1507 and Bt 11&lt;/strong&gt;, 16 EU countries voted against (AT, BG, CY, DK, EL, FR, HU, IE, IT, LT, LU, LV, PL, PT, SI, SE) representing 47.27 per cent of the EU population, six voted in favour (EE, ES, FI, NL, RO, UK) representing 30.45 per cent, and six abstained (BE, CZ, DE, HR, MT, SK) representing 22.28 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/priorities/docs/pg_en.pdf"&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/priorities/docs/pg_en.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://ec.europa.eu/priorities/docs/pg_en.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-27 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Maize%202.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Lacklustre drive for renewables threatens energy transition </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Lacklustre-drive-for-renewables-threatens-energy-transition-/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – The energy package being discussed by EU energy ministers today could endanger the transition to renewable energy and falls well below the action needed, warned Greenpeace. The “Clean Energy for All” package is meant to be the main set of rules for the EU to help limit global temperature increase to 1.5°C, as agreed in Paris. This necessitates a phase-out of all fossil fuel uses and transition to renewables within a generation.  
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the Commission’s proposals would reduce support for renewables in comparison with existing legislation and would leave the door open to subsidies for coal, gas and nuclear power. The EU energy ministers are expected to broadly endorse the package. While a number of countries are likely to ask for more ambitious rules on renewables. Poland, on the other hand, is expected to reject the plans outright, demanding more room to subsidise coal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Sebastian Mang said:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;“Several European governments are promoting huge pay-outs for dirty fossil fuels in discussions on the next EU energy package. At the same time, EU investments in renewables decreased from 112 billion euros in 2011 to 54 billion in 2016. Renewables are better for the planet and they literally encourage people power – power generated by people. Instead of propping up a harmful, doomed industry, our governments should invest in a clean and just energy transition enabling all Europeans to reap the benefits of renewables.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Council debate will be streamed at &lt;a href="http://video.consilium.europa.eu/en/webcast/143ec926-a910-4bc7-87ee-5fa49fc7e10e"&gt;http://video.consilium.europa.eu/en/webcast/143ec926-a910-4bc7-87ee-5fa49fc7e10e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser: +32 (0)479 60 12 89, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-27 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Over 150 civil society groups call for reform of European agricultural policies</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Over-150-civil-society-groups-call-for-reform-of-European-agricultural-policies/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Over 150 European civil society organisations representing environmental and social justice networks, organic farmers, pastoralists, peasants, sustainable forestry groups, health groups, animal welfare organisations, consumer rights bodies, development, fair-trade, cultural heritage and rural development organisations, consumer co-operatives, sustainable tourism and crafts associations from 25 EU countries have today called on EU leaders to carry out a radical reform of the CAP and related policies.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Cows_Belgium.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Cows_Belgium.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; The call comes as agricultural ministers meet in Brussels [1] to discuss future reform of the EU’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) and also in light of the public consultation [2] launched by the European Commission on the future of the policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a common statement titled ‘Good Food, Good Farming – Now’ [3] the signatories state that the current food and farming system is no longer functioning, since it props up the agro-industrial status quo, and call for a fundamental reform of Europe’s broken agricultural policy. [4] Such a reform is urgently needed to enable a transition towards a food and farming system which supports fair and diverse food and farming economies, is underpinned by viable alternatives such as organic and agro-ecological farming, and which respects the environment and animal welfare, supports citizens’ health, and is publicly accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/CSO_Statement_CAP_20170303.pdf"&gt;Read the full statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; [1] &lt;a href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/en/meetings/agrifish/2017/03/06/"&gt;Agriculture and Fisheries Council, Agenda, 6 March 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; [2] The European Commission’s &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/eusurvey/runner/FutureCAP"&gt;Public Consultation on ‘Modernising and Simplifying the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP)’&lt;/a&gt; began on 2 February and is open until the 2 May 2017.&lt;br&gt; [3] Full statement: LINK &lt;br&gt; [4] Some problems with the food and farming system in the EU:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/documents/2995521/7089766/5-26112015-AP-EN.pdf/e18e5577-c2a4-4c70-a8c7-fd758ea7b726"&gt;Farms are disappearing at an alarming rate&lt;/a&gt;: 1 out of every 4 EU farms have vanished between 2003 and 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Globally, more than 90% of crop varieties have disappeared from farmers’ fields and 75% of the world’s food is generated from only 12 plants and 5 animal species (FAO (2004): Building on Gender, Agrobiodiversity and Local Knowledge ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Europe’s land footprint totals 269 million hectares - with 40% of this used outside of Europe - an area almost the size of France and Italy combined  (Fischer G., S. Tramberend, M. Bruckner and M. Lieber, forthcoming. Quantifying the land footprint of Germany and the EU using a hybrid accounting model. Dessau: German Federal Environment Agency).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eu-fusions.org/phocadownload/Publications/Estimates%20of%20European%20food%20waste%20levels.pdf"&gt;20% of the food produced in the EU (88 million tonnes) is wasted annually&lt;/a&gt;, while 43 million EU citizens (8.5%) are &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Templates/AppData/Roaming/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/Stanka/AppData/Local/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/INetCache/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/INetCache/Content.Outlook/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/INetCache/AppData/Local/Temp/ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/regions/data/database"&gt;not able to afford&lt;/a&gt; a quality meal every second day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High levels of &lt;a href="https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/160518_Final%20paper_with%20cover.pdf"&gt;antibiotic use in animal farming contributes to antimicrobial resistance (AMR)&lt;/a&gt;, which could evolve into a global crisis killing some 10 million people annually by 2050.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2014, almost 400,000 tonnes of pesticides (active ingredients) were sold in the EU, showing an increase compared to the three previous years, according to &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/Agri-environmental_indicator_-_consumption_of_pesticides"&gt;Eurostat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/en/meetings/agrifish/2015/10/22-23/"&gt;Agriculture currently represents approximately 10% of total EU greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emissions from livestock, such as ammonia, significantly contribute to air pollution, which is responsible for over 400,000 deaths in the EU annually according to the &lt;a href="http://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/air-quality-in-europe-2016"&gt;European Environment Agency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/CSO_Statement_CAP_20170303.pdf</value><value>http://www.eu-fusions.org/phocadownload/Publications/Estimates%20of%20European%20food%20waste%20levels.pdf</value><value>https://amr-review.org/sites/default/files/160518_Final%20paper_with%20cover.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-06 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Cows_Belgium.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>PeoplePower</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Environmental and health organisations launch European citizens’ initiative to ban glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/European-citizens-initiative-ECI-stop-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Campaigners and activists met in Brussels and other European cities (Madrid, Rome, Berlin and Paris) today to launch a European Citizens’ Initiative (ECI) to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU. The goal is to collect at least one million signatures from Europeans and submit the petition before the Commission’s next move to renew, withdraw or extend the EU licence of glyphosate.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div class="WordSection1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate – the most widely used weedkiller in Europe – is also known as Roundup, a Monsanto brand- name. In 2015, the World Health Organization (WHO) linked glyphosate to cancer. The European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) is currently working on a safety assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Génon K. Jensen, Executive Director at Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL) &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thousands of tonnes of glyphosate are sprayed each year on our fields, in our countryside and our neighbourhoods. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is defined as a ‘probable carcinogen’ by IARC, the international agency recognised as the gold standard in carcinogen identification. We should not be using any weedkiller linked to cancer. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;If we are serious about protecting people’s health, and giving our wildlife a chance to recover, then our governments must step in to ban the most toxic pesticides, and reduce the overall amount that is used&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU food policy director &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are told that pesticides are strictly regulated to prevent harm. Yet they continue to be approved in secret meetings, based on unpublished industry studies. This kind of secrecy panders to industry and prevents proper scrutiny of EU food safety decisions. Regulators – not industry – should be responsible for ensuring public safety based on published scientific evidence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oliver Moldenhauer, Executive Director at WeMove.EU &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;"This year we have a real opportunity to finally get glyphosate out of our fields and off our plates. Our politicians need to hear this message loud and clear: they must protect citizens and the environment by banning this dangerous weedkiller and put us on the path towards a pesticide-free future."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ECI is backed by a broad, pan-European coalition of 38 organisations from 15 countries, including Corporate Europe Observatory (CEO), Greenpeace, the Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL), Pesticide Action Network Europe (PAN-E), and WeMove.EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pictures of the actions will be available online at &lt;a href="http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJJ2SMKI"&gt;http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJJ2SMKI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To sign the #StopGlyphosate ECI, people can visit &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;www.stopglyphosate.org&lt;/a&gt; and follow a simple two-step procedure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glyphosate is one Europe’s most widely used pesticides&lt;/strong&gt;, and its negative impacts on people’s health and the environment are clearly documented. EU Regulation 1107/2009 prohibits the use of pesticides when there is sufficient evidence in laboratory animals that these substances can cause cancer, based on scientific criteria from the WHO’s International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC). In 2015, IARC classified glyphosate as “probably carcinogenic to humans.” Therefore, the EU approval for glyphosate must be withdrawn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, following an assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), the European Commission proposed to re-approve glyphosate for 15 years, shortly before its licence was supposed to expire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a public outcry and insufficient backing from national governments forced the Commission to issue only an 18-month extension until the end of 2017, pending a safety assessment by the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the rules of the &lt;strong&gt;European Citizens’ Initiative &lt;/strong&gt;(ECI) a petition must be signed by at least one million EU citizens within one year, with minimum thresholds reached in at least seven EU countries. To take part in an ECI, signatories must enter their address details, date and place of birth, and their ID number in some countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more information on the #StopGlyphosate objectives, please visit &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;www.stopglyphosate.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diana G. Smith – &lt;/strong&gt;Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL) communications and media advisor, +33 (0)6 33 04 29 43, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Europe Observatory (CEO) &lt;/strong&gt;is an independent research and campaign group working to expose and challenge the heavy influence of corporate interests on EU policies. &lt;a href="http://www.corporateeurope.org/"&gt;www.corporateeurope.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace &lt;/strong&gt;is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;/strong&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL) &lt;/strong&gt;is a leading European not-for-profit organisation addressing how the environment affects health in the European Union (EU). We demonstrate how policy changes can help protect health and enhance people’s quality of life. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.env-health.org/"&gt;www.env-health.org&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;/strong&gt;Follow us on Twitter: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/HealthandEnv"&gt;www.twitter.com/HealthandEnv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pesticide Action Network Europe (PAN-E) &lt;/strong&gt;is the European regional centre of a global network of more than 600 non-governmental organisations working together to eliminate the use of harmful pesticides in food production and public green areas. Based in Brussels, PAN E is following closely the regulatory developments in relation to pesticides used in Europe with the vision to replace all hazardous pesticides with ecological alternatives. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pan-europe.info/"&gt;www.pan-europe.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WeMove.EU &lt;/strong&gt;is a citizens’ movement, campaigning for a better Europe; for a European Union committed to social and economic justice, environmental sustainability and citizen-led democracy. We are people from all walks of life, who call Europe our home – whether we were born in Europe or elsewhere. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://wemove.eu/"&gt;wemove.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-08 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Nuclear</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>European Parliament committee restricts controversial subsidies to coal, gas and nuclear plants</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/European-Parliament-committee-restricts-controversial-subsidies-to-coal-gas-and-nuclear-plants/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - The European Parliament’s energy committee has proposed restrictions for controversial subsidies for energy utilities in its vote on the energy market reform. So-called capacity mechanisms - national subsidies to keep power plants on standby - would only be allowed as a “last resort” and would be heavily regulated.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/2d6ea548-a71a-41d6-aee8-d21304cfe872.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/2d6ea548-a71a-41d6-aee8-d21304cfe872.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Sebastian Mang, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser,&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;Today common sense has won over cronyism. While many governments are trying to prop up failing energy companies with massive handouts, the Parliament recognises the power of renewables and that taxpayer money should not be wasted on old, polluting power plants. This energy reform must be an investment in our future and empower the millions of Europeans eager to combat climate change and produce their own energy.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee demanded an EU-wide evaluation of supply and demand. In case of energy security concerns, countries would be required to address shortfalls by increasing renewables, energy efficiency and the number of interconnectors. It also included strict time limits for standby payments and endorsed the Commission proposal to end such payments in 2025 for any plants emitting over 550g of carbon dioxide per kilowatt hour, which would exclude coal. These changes would require countries to remove or reform existing capacity mechanisms, such as the &lt;a href="http://www.caneurope.org/publications/press-releases/1543-commission-gives-go-ahead-to-poland-s-massive-coal-subsidies"&gt;recently approved Polish mechanisms&lt;/a&gt; that could cost Polish taxpayers &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/poland/PageFiles/763123/The_hidden_bill_for_coal_in_Poland_2017_WiseEuropa_report.pdf"&gt;over 8.9 billion euros by 2030&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the Council, the committee supported the Commission proposal to empower European citizens in the energy sector, for example by maintaining the rule that energy from small-scale renewables be taken up by the grid before energy from other sources such as coal and nuclear (priority dispatch). The committee also wants to make it easier for people to &lt;a href="https://www.euractiv.com/section/energy/news/community-energy-projects-in-greece-under-threat-activists-warn/"&gt;generate and share electricity in their communities.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="_anchor_1" name="_msoanchor_1" href="#_msocom_1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The committee negotiator, MEP Krišjānis Kariņš (EPP), also received the mandate to begin negotiations. Trialogue negotiations between the Council, Commission and European Parliament on new energy rules are expected to start at the end of March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 18 December 2017, in its preliminary position on the energy reform, the Council rejected requirements for national governments to justify capacity mechanisms. Ministers also proposed to extend the deadline from 2025 to 2035 for giving such payments to existing coal plants that emit over 550g of carbon dioxide per kilowatt hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 479 60 1289, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Ullmann, Greenpeace EU press officer: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;+32 471 75 89 85, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/poland/PageFiles/763123/The_hidden_bill_for_coal_in_Poland_2017_WiseEuropa_report.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-02-21 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>FossilFuels</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/2d6ea548-a71a-41d6-aee8-d21304cfe872.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EFSA confirms pesticides danger to bees</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EFSA-confirms-pesticides-danger-bees/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;National governments must now back EU neonicotinoid ban, says Greenpeace&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Three widely used neonicotinoid pesticides are a danger to bees, according to a report released today by the European Food Safety Authority, EFSA. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on a review of over 700 studies on imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam, EFSA confirms that these chemicals pose high risks to bees, and that EU restrictions imposed in 2013 are insufficient to control these risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU food policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The evidence is overwhelming that bees, and the crops and plants they pollinate, are at dire risk from neonicotinoid pesticides. National governments must stop dithering and back the proposed EU neonicotinoid ban as the first step to prevent the catastrophic collapse of bee populations.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;In March 2017, the European Commission&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-takes-major-step-to-ban-three-neonics"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;proposed a ban&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; on the three neonicotinoids, except when they are used in greenhouses. National governments will vote on this measure on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/plant/docs/planning_sc_meetings_2018.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;22 March&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, following the postponement of a vote in December 2017.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/180228"&gt;Today’s review of the scientific evidence&lt;/a&gt; is a result of partial EU restrictions, introduced in 2013, on the use of the three neonicotinoid pesticides in agriculture. It follows five EFSA reports in 2015 and 2016, which consistently highlight the dangers these pesticides pose for managed honeybees and wild bees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/plant/docs/planning_sc_meetings_2018.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-02-28 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Monsanto’s view of independent science copied into EU evaluations </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Monsantos-view-of-independent-science-copied-into-EU-evaluations-/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 15 September 2017 – According to media reports, large sections of the EU report evaluating the independent science on glyphosate’s potential risk to human health have been copied, word for word on many pages, from Monsanto’s application for the renewal of glyphosate’s licence, filed on behalf of the Glyphosate Task Force (a consortium of more than 20 companies). The sections concerned address the potential genotoxicity, carcinogenicity and reproductive toxicity as reported in the scientific literature. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EFSA_report_cover.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EFSA_report_cover.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Commenting on the discovery Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU Food Policy Director&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;said&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Whether this is a question of negligence or intent, it is completely unacceptable for government bodies to pass off industry analysis as their own. It calls into question the entire EU pesticide approval process. If regulators rely on the industry’s evaluation of the science without doing their own assessment, the decision whether pesticides are deemed safe or not is effectively in the industry’s hands. Voting against glyphosate is the last opportunity our governments have to fulfil their duty to protect us from this dangerous chemical." &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Throughout the discussions about glyphosate, the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) and the relevant German national authority (Bundesinstitut für Risikobewertung, BfR) have emphasised that they have done their own evaluations of the studies&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref1" href="#_ftn1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;However, an initial comparison of the Monsanto application and the EU report shows this is not the case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It suggests that BfR and consequently EFSA have failed to conduct their own review of an important number of independent scientific studies on potential human health impacts of glyphosate, including genotoxicity, carcinogenicity and reproductive toxicity. Entrusted with delivering an independent scientific assessment, the authorities have effectively passed Monsanto’s interpretation off as their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EFSA evades responsibility for its role&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EFSA is claiming that the Renewal Assessment Report (RAR) is not its own work; and that instead the health risk assessment in the RAR is the work of the BfR. It is correct that authorities from the Rapporteur Member State (RMS), Germany, drafted the RAR, but their work was subsequently reviewed by other national authorities, the European Commission and EFSA. None commented on the excessive copying from Monsanto’s submission. EFSA then drafted its conclusion based on the 4,300-page report. The RAR and the EFSA conclusion are therefore inherently related. EFSA’s own description of the process is &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Glyphosate-infographic.pdf"&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has the BfR and EFSA been transparent about copying the descriptions of studies?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RAR &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2015/may/13/chemical-reactions-glyphosate-and-the-politics-of-chemical-safety)"&gt;discloses&lt;/a&gt; that the BfR copied sections concerning unpublished &lt;em&gt;industry studies&lt;/em&gt; from the Monsanto’s glyphosate application, and provided its own comments on them in italics (“RMS comments”). However, the report does not disclose that the BfR also copied Monsanto’s description &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; analysis of the &lt;em&gt;independent studies&lt;/em&gt; published in peer-reviewed scientific journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the report explicitly states that the BfR evaluated and commented on these studies: “&lt;em&gt;The publications on subject areas 1-4 are presented in the chapters on Genotoxicity, Long term toxicicity [sic] and carcinogenicity, Reproductive Toxicity and Neurotoxicity of the report. (…) Important publications are presented in summaries as quoted from the articles followed by Klimisch ratings and by RMS comments on the paper&lt;/em&gt;" &lt;a title="" name="_ftnref2" href="#_ftn2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(page 515 of the 4,300-page report).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box big-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/3_comparison.PNG" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl04_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Large/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/3_comparison.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EFSA has issued a &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/topic/20170608_glyphosate_statement.pdf"&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; saying: “Every scientific study is scrutinised for relevance and reliability by EU risk assessors based on the evidence contained within the study.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Peter Bleser, State Secretary at the German Federal Ministry of Food, Agriculture and Consumer Protection (BMELV) which oversees the BfR, stated in &lt;a href="http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/054/1805455.pdf"&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; to a written question by a German member of parliament that all studies were evaluated by the BfR. He went on to say that only the descriptions of the "original studies submitted by the applicants", not the published studies, were taken from the Glyphosate Task Force (GTF) and commented on in italic by the Rapporteur Member State (i.e. the BfR). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As reported in the media, a comparison of the documents has now called these statements into question. It appears that the regulatory authorities responsible for reviewing the evidence have instead taken Monsanto's interpretation and presented them as their own – a flagrant and unacceptable failure on the part of the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2"&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review of the published literature on genotoxicity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review of the published literature on reproductive toxicity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review of the published literature on carcinogenicity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_4%20Genotoxicity_Published%20data.pdf"&gt;In the GTF application for glyphosate renewal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_1%20Reprotox_Published%20data.pdf"&gt;In the GTF application for glyphosate renewal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_3%20Carcinogenicity_Published%20data.pdf"&gt;In the GTF application for glyphosate renewal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Genotoxicity_B.6.4.8%20Published%20Data_marked.pdf"&gt;In the EU report (copied text highlighted in orange)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Reprotox_B.6.6.12%20Published%20data_marked.pdf"&gt;In the EU report (copied text highlighted in orange)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left" valign="top"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Carcinogenicity_B.6.5.3%20Published%20data_marked.pdf"&gt;In the EU report (copied text highlighted in orange)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Ullmann&lt;/strong&gt;: Greenpeace communications officer: +32 (0)2 274 1915, +32 (0)486 88 52 12 &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press release is available on: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br clear="all"&gt;&lt;hr align="left" size="1" width="33%"&gt;
&lt;div id="ftn1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title="" name="_ftn1" href="#_ftnref1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; European Food Safety Authority, &lt;em&gt;EFSA Statement regarding the EU assessment of glyphosate and the so-called “Monsanto papers”&lt;/em&gt;, June 2017, p. 3 &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/topic/20170608_glyphosate_statement.pdf"&gt;http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/topic/20170608_glyphosate_statement.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bleser, State Secretary at the German Federal Ministry of Food, Agriculture and Consumer Protection (BMELV), in response to a written question (7 September 2015), page 40 &lt;a href="http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/059/1805977.pdf"&gt;http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/059/1805977.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bleser, State Secretary at the German Federal Ministry of Food, Agriculture and Consumer Protection (BMELV), in response to a written question (29 June 2015), page 38 &lt;a href="http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/054/1805455.pdf"&gt;http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/054/1805455.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ftn2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title="" name="_ftn2" href="#_ftnref2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/3_comparison.PNG</value></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Glyphosate-infographic.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/topic/20170608_glyphosate_statement.pdf</value><value>http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/054/1805455.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_4%20Genotoxicity_Published%20data.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_1%20Reprotox_Published%20data.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/GTF_Section%20IIA%205.10_3%20Carcinogenicity_Published%20data.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Genotoxicity_B.6.4.8%20Published%20Data_marked.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Reprotox_B.6.6.12%20Published%20data_marked.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/2017/RAR%20Vol%203%20Carcinogenicity_B.6.5.3%20Published%20data_marked.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/topic/20170608_glyphosate_statement.pdf</value><value>http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/059/1805977.pdf</value><value>http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/18/054/1805455.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-09-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Large/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/3_comparison.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EFSA_report_cover.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>European Parliament fires up Europe’s energy transition</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/parliament-fires-up-energy-transition/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	European Parliament proposals to increase the EU’s share of renewable energy to a minimum of 35 per cent, and to set binding targets for each EU country, are a step in the right direction, said Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The European Parliament’s draft opinion on the proposed overhaul of EU renewables laws, to be published later today by rapporteur José Blanco López, could pave the way towards meaningful climate action in the EU.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate and energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: “&lt;em&gt;The Parliament is right to ramp up the EU’s renewable energy targets and to require each country do their share to fight climate change. But Mr Blanco López is in danger of compromising too soon, he can and should prioritise access for renewables and give people real control of their energy bills. Renewable energy ranks amongst the cheapest in Europe, and decentralised ownership in solar and wind generation allows communities to switch off dirty coal and nuclear while maximising the benefits of producing and consuming energy locally.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Mr Blanco López’s draft report proposes a 35 per cent renewable energy target for the EU, compared to the EU’s current 27 per cent target. But it falls short of the&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-climate-leadership-boost-renewables/"&gt; 45 per cent target proposed by a sister report&lt;/a&gt;, co-authored by MEPs Claude Turmes and Michele Rivasi. Mr Blanco López also proposes to remove taxes and charges which block people from producing and consuming their own electricity at home, such as Spain’s controversial ‘sun tax’.&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Media-briefing-Potential-for-citizen-produced-electricity-in-the-EU/"&gt; With the right support, half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity by 2050, meeting 45 per cent of the EU’s electricity demand.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The plan fails to restore ‘priority access’, the system by which electricity grids draw power from renewable sources first, and increases the role of auctioning in renewable energy support schemes. The latter would force energy cooperatives to compete on uneven terms with big utilities for government support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The Parliament response to the revision of the renewable energy directive will be submitted to the industry and energy committee on 21 June. MEPs on the committee are due to discuss the proposals on 4 September and to submit their position to plenary, after a Committee vote scheduled on 11/12 October. The plenary is likely to vote around the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate &amp;amp; energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1905, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-22 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Climate%20paris.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Bratislava summit: Europe at a crossroads</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Bratislava-summit-Europe-at-a-crossroads/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Letter to EU leaders by environmental organisations ahead of special summit in Bratislava.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/PeopleB4Profit.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/PeopleB4Profit.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU is at a crossroads. It can either continue on the current path of deregulation and ‘less Europe’ – a path which has clearly failed to convince citizens both in the UK and across the Union – or it can embark on something new, answering to the needs and aspirations of European citizens. On this new path, instead of focussing on promoting globalisation, the EU would direct its efforts towards managing its impacts on our planet and ensuring that all its citizens can live a good life, well within the planetary boundaries.[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To read the full letter click on the link below&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/Bratislava_summit_Green10_priorities.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Bratislava_summit_Green10_priorities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/file/Bratislava_summit_Green10_priorities.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-08-30 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>EUaffairs</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/PeopleB4Profit.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>How does CETA stand up to S&amp;D’s ten progressive principles for trade?</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/CETA-SandD-progressive-trade-principles/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	As the European Parliament prepares for a crucial vote on the EU-Canada trade and investment protection deal (CETA), the group of socialists and democrats MEPs (S&amp;D) has released a list of “ten progressive principles for a new era of trade agreements”. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/European%20Parliament%20plenary%20Strasbourg.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/European%20Parliament%20plenary%20Strasbourg.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These principles call for a fairer international trade system, with agreements that put public protection and transparency ahead of corporate power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how CETA stands up to the ten principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201611%20CETA%20and%20SandD%20progressive%20trade%20principles.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;201611 CETA and SandD progressive trade principles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/201611%20CETA%20and%20SandD%20progressive%20trade%20principles.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-11-30 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/European%20Parliament%20plenary%20Strasbourg.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission study makes pressing case for EU action on deforestation</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Commission-study-action-deforestation/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Despite promises, Commission remains silent on EU plans to tackle deforestation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – A long awaited European Commission study, released late on Friday, lays out policy options for the EU to tackle the impact on global deforestation caused by the trade in crop and animal products like beef, soy and palm oil. [1] The study also points out the EU’s high level of meat consumption, its dependence on imported animal feed, and the inadequacy of controls on finance and investments flows as drivers of deforestation.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Deforestation.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Deforestation.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU’s failure to act to reduce its forest footprint is jeopardising chances of avoiding the worst impacts of climate change, warned Greenpeace. Although the Commission&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/NGO-statement-on-deforestation/"&gt;had promised to take a decision&lt;/a&gt; on a deforestation action plan, it has yet to announce how it intends to follow up on this study and what action, if any, will be taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU forest policy director Sébastien Risso&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Europe has ignored its role in global deforestation for long enough. The EU must act swiftly to ensure that the food we eat, the energy we use and the banks we save in are no longer destroying forests, fuelling climate change and trampling on indigenous peoples’ rights. It’s time for the Commission to break its silence and come forward with strong rules and policies to curb the EU’s forest footprint and support global efforts to halt deforestation.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European governments and the European Parliament&lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32013D1386"&gt;have repeatedly called&lt;/a&gt; on the Commission to develop an action plan on deforestation and to deliver on the goal of ending deforestation by 2020. [2] On 5 March, again, at the last Environment Council, five EU countries called on the Commission to &lt;em&gt;“propose an ambitious strategy to combat imported deforestation”&lt;/em&gt;. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission study released today recognises that &lt;em&gt;“the EU is clearly part of the problem of global deforestation”&lt;/em&gt;, but can be part of the solution. It sets out a series of policy measures that could form the basis of an EU action plan on deforestation. In particular, these include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new legislative measures to ensure sustainable and deforestation-free agricultural supply chains, and oblige financial institutions to take action to eliminate the risk of deforestation resulting from financial investments;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;initiatives to encourage lower consumption of meat and dedicated actions to reduce imports of feed, such as soy, for the EU livestock sector by increasing vegetable protein production in Europe;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a complete phase-out of crop-based biofuels by 2030 under the renewable energy directive;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;financial and technical assistance to help countries whose forests are at risk to meet their international commitments on forest protection, including by supporting sustainable agricultural production and supply chains, strengthening forest protection, securing the rights of indigenous and forest communities, and improving forest and land use planning, governance and law enforcement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agricultural expansion is responsible for 80 per cent of global deforestation, with devastating effects on the planet’s climate and biodiversity. Deforestation is also associated with violence and human rights abuses. Almost 40 percent of the land used to satisfy&lt;a href="http://www.foeeurope.org/true-cost-consumption-land-footprint-report"&gt;EU consumption&lt;/a&gt; is situated outside Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forests are essential for life on the planet. They guard against the worst effects of climate change byabsorbing and storing massive amounts of carbon dioxide, are home to a vast diversity of plants, animals and insects, and provide shelter and livelihoods for hundreds of millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission also released a study on the environmental impact of palm oil consumption and on existing sustainability standards. [4] In 2017, the EU imported over 3,410,000 tonnes of palm oil from Indonesia and over 1,781,000 tonnes from Malaysia. The oil palm and wood fibre sector is the biggest driver of deforestation in &lt;a href="http://www.wri.org/blog/2017/07/drivers-deforestation-indonesia-inside-and-outside-concessions-areas"&gt;Indonesia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.cifor.org/library/6227/rapid-conversions-and-avoided-deforestation-examining-four-decades-of-industrial-plantation-expansion-in-borneo/"&gt;Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;. In Indonesia alone around 24 million hectares of rainforest was destroyed between 1990 and 2015 – an area almost the size of the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Commission study &lt;em&gt;on the feasibility of options to step up EU action to combat deforestation and forest degradation&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/feasibility_study_deforestation_kh0418199enn_main_report.pdf"&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/feasibility_study_deforestation_kh0418199enn_main_report.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] World leaders recognised the crucial&lt;a href="http://newsroom.unfccc.int/nature-s-role/forests-as-key-climate-solution"&gt;role of forests&lt;/a&gt; in climate change mitigation in the 2015 Paris climate agreement and&lt;a href="http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/biodiversity/"&gt;pledged to halt deforestation by 2020&lt;/a&gt;. In 2013, European governments and the European Parliament asked the Commission to develop policy proposals and consider the development of an action plan on deforestation and forest degradation in the context of the 7th EU environment action programme. Several European governments (France, Germany, Italy, the Netherlands, Denmark, the United Kingdom and Norway) have reiterated their call for action in the&lt;a href="https://www.euandgvc.nl/documents/publications/2015/december/7/declarations"&gt;Amsterdam Declaration&lt;/a&gt;. Members of the European Parliament also called for an EU action plan, including concrete regulatory measures to ensure that no supply chains and financial transactions linked to the EU result in deforestation and forest degradation, most recently, in the&lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P8-TA-2017-0098+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN"&gt;Parliament’s resolution&lt;/a&gt; on palm oil and deforestation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Note from the French, Danish, German, Netherlands and United Kingdom delegations on &lt;em&gt;“combating imported deforestation”&lt;/em&gt;, discussed at the Environment Council on 5 March 2018. &lt;a href="http://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-6528-2018-INIT/en/pdf"&gt;http://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-6528-2018-INIT/en/pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Commission study on the environmental impact of palm oil consumption and on existing sustainability standards &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/palm_oil_study_kh0218208enn_new.pdf"&gt;http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/palm_oil_study_kh0218208enn_new.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU forest policy director Sébastien Risso:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)496 127009, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is also available on:&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/feasibility_study_deforestation_kh0418199enn_main_report.pdf</value><value>http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/palm_oil_study_kh0218208enn_new.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-19 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Deforestation.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>WaterPollution</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Investigation: EU subsidises Europe’s most polluting livestock farms</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-subsidises-polluting-livestock-farms/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;CAP payments fund factory farms leaking ammonia into air and water&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Subsidies from the European Union’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) are supporting some of Europe’s most polluting livestock farms, a Greenpeace investigation has revealed.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Over half (51%) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;of the farms examined in seven EU countries received CAP payments totalling €104 million &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;in the last year reported&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, despite being the highest emitters of ammonia in their countries. The research compared CAP direct payments and the EU’s registers of pollution from industrial facilities. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Ammonia runoff from fertilizers or manure slurry leads to the rapid growth of algae in rivers, lakes and seas, choking plants and animals of oxygen. Ammonia also causes air pollution from fine particulate matter, which impacts human health.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/investigation-CAP-promotes-pollution/"&gt;**A detailed overview of the research is available here**&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Environmental protection is one of the objectives of Europe’s farm policy, but the evidence shows that bad behaviour is constantly rewarded. Ammonia pollution is just the tip of the iceberg. Europe continues to pump cash into livestock factory farms despite their disastrous impact on the local environment, the climate and public health. The EU’s Common Agricultural Policy must instead support agriculture that works with nature, not against it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/investigation-CAP-promotes-pollution/"&gt;**A detailed overview of the research is available here**&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The research, which was carried out in collaboration with investigative journalists, examined farms in Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, Poland and the Netherlands listed in the European Pollutant Release and Transfer Register (E-PRTR). Agricultural installations are required to submit data to the E-PRTR if they emit more than 10,000 kg of ammonia per year, and to the Industrial Emission Directive register if they have space for over 40,000 poultry, 2,000 pigs or 750 sows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Of the 2,374 livestock farms in these countries emitting high enough levels of ammonia to be included in the European Pollutant Release and Transfer Register &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;in the last year reported&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1,209&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; received CAP payments totalling at least €104 million per year. The CAP annually allocates €59 billion in subsidies, roughly 40 per cent of the EU’s total budget. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The research also exposed the lack of a proper monitoring system to provide data on agricultural pollution in Europe. For ammonia, the only pollutant consistently reported at EU level, existing data covers only a small percentage of total emissions from agriculture. Farms in Austria in the Industrial Emissions Directive register were also examined, but none individually met the ammonia threshold to be included in the E-PRTR, despite high levels of ammonia emissions in the country. 36 of these farms received €1.6 million in CAP payments.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps for CAP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;On 2 May, the European Commission is expected to publish a draft of the next EU budget, starting in 2020, which will include CAP spending. By early June, the Commission is also expected to publish its proposal for a reform of the CAP. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk: &lt;/strong&gt;+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)2 274 1906, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open and honest look at the EU’s trade practices needed</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/open-honest-look-eu-trade/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	EU trade commissioner Malmström today published a package of proposals on trade and investment policy. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20161018%20CETA%20protest%20Luxembourg.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20161018%20CETA%20protest%20Luxembourg.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission also published draft mandates for trade negotiations with Australia and New Zealand, and announced it would release its mandate from the European Council for the negotiations of the EU Japan trade deal (JEFTA). Greenpeace had previously made a &lt;a href="https://trade-leaks.org/jefta-leaks/"&gt;leaked version of the JEFTA mandate&lt;/a&gt; public on 23 June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-a09dd161-8021-bb75-903f-f3cc5759799c"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade campaigner Kees Kodde&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Today’s proposals for an updated approach to trade and investment are no substitute for an open and honest look at the EU’s trade practices. The plan for a multilateral investment court is in fact a proposal for a global system that will lock in special rights for investors. We demand that the EU focuses its trade policy on the interests of people and the planet, not the investment interests of big business.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-a09dd161-8022-070a-81c4-8361080f614e"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde, Greenpeace trade policy campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;: +31 (0)6 53623818, &lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-09-14 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20161018%20CETA%20protest%20Luxembourg.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Climate change activists call on EU energy ministers to unlock rooftop revolution </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Climate-change-activists-call-on-EU-energy-ministers-to-unlock-rooftop-revolution-/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Luxembourg/Brussels - Climate change activists urged EU energy ministers meeting in Luxembourg to live up to their climate commitments and stop restricting the rights of people to produce and share their own renewable energy. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*** High-res photos &amp;amp; video available &lt;a href="https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJWX3Z1O"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. ***&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STS2NN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STS2NN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU energy ministers are gathering two days ahead of final negotiations with the European Parliament and the European Commission on the EU’s Renewable Energy Directive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group of 35 activists from 8 countries [1] confronted ministers with banners reading: &lt;em&gt;“Our sun. Our power. Our future.” &lt;/em&gt;and&lt;em&gt; “People-Powered Renewables = Climate Action”.&lt;/em&gt; Ministers arriving at the meeting were greeted at the main entrance, the underground drop-off area and the back-access road. The activists also unfurled a giant sun covered with selfie messages from hundreds of Europeans calling on the EU to power a swift transition away from fossil fuels and nuclear energy to citizen-owned renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Ansgar Kiene&lt;/strong&gt; said: “Politicians like using bold words on climate change, but they refuse to fulfil their promises when they have the chance. Without a rapid increase in renewable energy driven by a solar rooftop revolution, Europe cannot be a climate leader. Governments now need to set high renewables targets and provide the means to achieve them. You can't have one without the other, just like you can’t ride a bicycle that’s missing a wheel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belgium, France, Luxembourg, the Netherlands and Sweden have &lt;a href="https://www.ecologique-solidaire.gouv.fr/france-lallemagne-suede-pays-bas-finlande-portugal-et-luxembourg-appellent-ambition-climatique"&gt;publicly supported&lt;/a&gt; the need to tackle climate change. The change of governments in Spain and Italy is expected to affect the negotiations. &lt;a href="https://elpais.com/economia/2018/06/05/actualidad/1528193291_786828.html?id_externo_rsoc=TW_CC"&gt;According to reports&lt;/a&gt;, the new Spanish government has already indicated that it will change the Spanish position, support renewables, and leave the group of conservative countries that includes Poland. It will also &lt;a href="http://www.climatechangenews.com/2018/06/06/spain-joins-call-strengthen-eu-climate-targets/"&gt;join the coalition of EU governments calling for climate ambition&lt;/a&gt;. A change of position by the new Italian government could further split European governments. Italy’s new deputy prime minister and energy minister advocated &lt;a href="http://www.ansa.it/canale_ambiente/notizie/energia/2017/05/30/di-maio-finanziare-di-piu-ecobonus-per-rinnovabili_192e6762-f407-4bb2-a802-6fee731c8c55.html"&gt;support for people-powered renewables&lt;/a&gt; during the election campaign. While Germany is a member of the climate-ambition group, it is also among the countries – including Poland and Hungary – that are blocking efforts to raise the EU's renewable energy target for 2030 and to cut fees and red tape which discourage households and small businesses from investing in renewables like solar energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Council negotiating position and the final Renewable Energy Directive will determine the role of renewables in Europe’s energy system up to 2030 and beyond, as well as the potential for Europeans to self-generate, consume, share and sell electricity. Having more renewable energy in the mix would reduce carbon emissions and, according to scientific &lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Climate-Reports/Energy-Revolution-2015/"&gt;projections&lt;/a&gt;, a renewables target of at least 45 percent by 2030 would bring the EU in line with its commitments under the Paris climate agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Council has shown openness to move beyond its initial 27 per cent target, but is demanding the Parliament back down from its support for a minimum 35 percent target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU ministers and the Parliament also disagree on the rights of individuals, cooperatives and cities to produce and sell their own renewable energy. The position so far agreed among EU energy ministers could seriously penalise people generating their own energy. For example, it would allow national governments to impose punitive fees and to heavily restrict how and where people can produce and share energy, with additional burdens on those who do not own their own roof, such as tenants. Governments could also burden these small-scale energy producers with the same registration requirements as large power companies, if they feed any amount of electricity into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final negotiating session between the European Parliament, EU governments and the European Commission will take place on 13 June in Strasbourg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*** High-res photos &amp;amp; video available &lt;a href="https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJWX3Z1O"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. ***&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Belgium, France, Germany, Italy, Luxembourg, Portugal, the Netherlands and the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;, +32 476 961375&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-06-11 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STS2NN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Media Advisory: European Parliament and #StopGlyphosate coalition to challenge Andriukaitis over weedkiller approval </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/European-Parliament-and-StopGlyphosate-coalition-to-challenge-Andriukaitis/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Formal hearing for European Citizens’ Initiative at 3:30 pm CET today
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosate_COM1.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosate_COM1.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representatives of the #StopGlyphosate European Citizens’ Initiative will present their demands at a &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/cmsdata/132169/draft-programme-eci-glyphosate-20-11-2017%202.pdf"&gt;hearing&lt;/a&gt; in the European Parliament at 3:30 pm today. EU commissioner for health and food safety Vytenis Andriukaitis will present an opening and closing statement at the meeting. This hearing comes one week before the &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/safety/docs/app-comm_gmffer_20171127_agenda.pdf"&gt;final vote&lt;/a&gt; by EU governments on the future of glyphosate, which follows a number of failed attempts by the Commission to renew the EU glyphosate licence, &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/EU-governments-reject-Commission-push-for-glyphosate/"&gt;most recently for a proposed five years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over one million people across Europe have demanded a ban on glyphosate, more transparent and independent EU risk assessments of pesticides, and an overall reduction in pesticide use. The European Commission &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/citizens-initiative/public/initiatives/successful/details/2017/000002"&gt;officially received&lt;/a&gt; their petition on 6 October. The European Parliament has also &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?type=TA&amp;amp;reference=P8-TA-2017-0395&amp;amp;format=XML&amp;amp;language=EN"&gt;called&lt;/a&gt; for a full glyphosate ban within five years, starting with a partial ban this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commenting before the hearing, &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Health commissioner Andriukaitis is now resorting to lame legal excuses to renew the licence for glyphosate. The EU is supposed to protect Europeans and the environment, but Andriukaitis’ main concern seems to be Monsanto’s threats of a lawsuit. Instead of cowering to corporate bullying, he should listen to independent scientists, parliamentarians and over a million Europeans calling for an immediate ban on glyphosate.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) has recognised &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4302"&gt;serious environmental &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/4302"&gt;risks&lt;/a&gt; linked to glyphosate, such as high long-term risk to birds and mammals from common uses such as spraying before planting or before cereal harvesting. The European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) has &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/-/glyphosate-not-classified-as-a-carcinogen-by-echa"&gt;classified glyphosate&lt;/a&gt; as “toxic to aquatic life with long lasting effects”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both agencies have said glyphosate is unlikely to cause cancer. However, the World Health Organisation’s cancer research agency (IARC) has classified it as a&lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt;“probable” cause of cancer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/ep-live/en/committees/video?event=20171113-1900-COMMITTEE-AGRI"&gt;Last week&lt;/a&gt; EU health commissioner Andriukaitis said the EU could not phase out glyphosate as the Parliament &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?type=TA&amp;amp;reference=P8-TA-2017-0395&amp;amp;format=XML&amp;amp;language=EN"&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; because there were “no legal grounds” and because the Commission would risk fines and being taken to court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32009R1107&amp;amp;from=en"&gt;pesticide rules&lt;/a&gt; require that pesticides do not harm human health and “have no unacceptable effects on the environment”. It also states that any decision on the renewal or non-renewal of an active substance should take into account the scientific evaluation by EFSA, scientific uncertainties that persist (precautionary principle) and “other factors legitimate to the matter”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on the glyphosate decision-making process, please refer to this &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171115_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf"&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;: Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.europarl.europa.eu/cmsdata/132169/draft-programme-eci-glyphosate-20-11-2017%202.pdf</value><value>https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/safety/docs/app-comm_gmffer_20171127_agenda.pdf</value><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171115_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-11-20 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosate_COM1.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>PeoplePower</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>More than one million Europeans stand up against glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/One-million-Europeans-stand-against-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Fastest-growing European Citizens’ Initiative demonstrates huge societal concern about pesticides&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels, 15 June 2017 – Today, the European Citizens’ Initiative (ECI) to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU surpassed one million signatures.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateECI_1M.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateECI_1M.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ECI has fulfilled the requirements set by the EU in less than five months, making it the fastest-growing ECI since the EU introduced this tool in 2012. The ECI organisers call on the European Commission to respect the signatories’ demands by refusing a new licence for glyphosate. The petition will remain open for sign-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Schwartz, ECI Coordinator at WeMove.EU &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;"European citizens aren’t fooled by the pesticide industry’s lobbying efforts or the faulty science it’s peddling. In less than five months, more than one million EU citizens have joined our call for a glyphosate ban and reduced pesticide use throughout the EU. Our politicians need to hear this message loud and clear: they must protect citizens and the environment by banning this dangerous weedkiller and putting us on the path towards a pesticide-free future."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU Food Policy Director &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“Monsanto and other producers of glyphosate are doing all they can to get governments around the world to approve their product. They have allegedly paid independent scientists to sign studies they wrote and cosied up with government officials to ‘kill’ unwanted investigations. Yet the Commission continues to maintain that everything is fine. Greenpeace demands an investigation into whether Monsanto has improperly influenced the EU assessment.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission has recently announced its intention to renew the EU glyphosate licence by another 10 years. It is expected to issue a formal proposal ahead of a discussion with EU government representatives on 19 and 20 July. EU governments will be asked to vote on this proposal after the summer. Based on the outcome, the Commission will take a final decision before the end of the year when the current EU glyphosate licence runs out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ECI organisers will submit the signatures at the beginning of July, in order to require the Commission to formally respond before the final decision on a new glyphosate licence is made. Until then, people still have the opportunity to speak out against glyphosate and in favour of reduced pesticide use in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The #StopGlyphosate ECI is backed by a pan-European coalition of over 100 organisations throughout the EU, and coordinated by WeMove.EU. For more information or to sign, please visit &lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;www.stopglyphosate.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Schwartz – &lt;/strong&gt;ECI Coordinator, WeMove.EU, +32 (0)486 07 83 42; &lt;a href="mailto:david@wemove.eu" target="_blank"&gt;david@wemove.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/StopGlyphosateECI_1M.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU farming plan could spell disaster for environment, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-farming-plan-disaster-environment/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Commission proposal for the new common agricultural policy (CAP) fails the environment and the climate, according to Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The new CAP proposal gives national governments the responsibility to define national agriculture plans, but does not set the safeguards necessary to ensure that these plans protect public health, the environment and the climate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The Commission also proposes to heavily cut CAP funds available for environmental protection, reducing the rural development budget by 25 per cent and ending the ring-fencing of 30 per cent of direct payments for farmers who adopt environmentally beneficial practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The Commission’s plans offer almost no protection for health, the environment and climate. The EU props up the agriculture industry with billions every year. The least people can expect is that these investments help achieve climate and environment goals, and deliver healthy, nutritious food. The European Parliament and our governments must fix the CAP’s priorities and stop funneling money to a few large landowners and factory farms. Every one of us has a right to know that what we eat is isn’t cruel to animals, polluting our water, warming the planet or making us ill.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The CAP proposal fails to specifically address the environmental and health impacts of Europe’s intensive meat and dairy sector. Animal farming in Europe contributes&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23504717"&gt; 12-17 per cent&lt;/a&gt; of the EU’s greenhouse gas emissions. It is also a major source of water, soil and air pollution, in particular from nitrogen and phosphorus in water, and ammonia and fine particulate matter in the air. Nitrogen pollution alone costs the EU&lt;a href="http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf"&gt; up to €320 billion every year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The European Food Safety Authority and the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control described antibiotic resistance as “one of the biggest threats to public health”, echoing statements by the World Health Organization.&lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/180227"&gt; A joint report by the two agencies&lt;/a&gt; confirmed the presence of bacteria in farmed animals that have developed resistance to crucial antibiotics used to treat people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is calling for&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision"&gt; a 50 per cent reduction in global meat and dairy production&lt;/a&gt; by 2050, to protect the climate, environment and public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 477 777034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-06-01 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Activists set up solar panels on European Parliament as EU talks on renewables enter crucial stage</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/solar-panels-European-Parliament-renewables/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Activists have installed solar panels on the European Parliament in Brussels on the day EU talks on renewable energy enter a crucial stage. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/European%20Parliament%20solar%20panels.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/European%20Parliament%20solar%20panels.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Parliament is hosting the penultimate round of negotiations on the EU’s Renewable Energy Directive. The outcome of the negotiations will determine the role of renewables in Europe’s energy system through 2030 and beyond, as well as the potential for Europeans to self-generate, consume, share and sell electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group of 20 activists and climbers from seven countries [1] also unfurled a banner covering the front of the European Parliament’s information centre and placed a giant sun in front of the Parliament, reading: &lt;em&gt;“Our sun. Our power. Our future.” &lt;/em&gt;The banner and the sun were covered with hundreds of selfies, sent in by people all over Europe, calling on the European Union to power a swift transition away from fossil fuels and nuclear energy to citizen-owned renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activists are using the electricity generated by the solar panels installed on the Parliament to make and distribute free vegan ice-cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;a href="https://es.greenpeace.org/es/noticias/placasolares/?utm_medium=social_network&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Energia&amp;amp;utm_content=ministerio&amp;amp;utm_term=movida"&gt;activists in Spain&lt;/a&gt; have installed solar panels on a building belonging to the energy ministry in Madrid, demanding that the Spanish government stop penalising people who produce their own energy. Research by Greenpeace Spain released on Wednesday revealed that the Spanish government uses only 1.25 percent of the space available for solar panels on ministry buildings, wasting around €27 million in public money to buy electricity from power utilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Ansgar Kiene&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The sun and wind belong to everyone but our governments want to discourage people from putting solar panels on their roof or joining cooperative wind farms. All the while, they continue to bankroll coal, gas and nuclear power stations, filling the pockets of a few giant power companies. The European Parliament needs to stay firm in its support for a greener, healthier and more democratic future. The time for energy monopolies is over. It’s time for energy democracy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament is set to clash with European governments over the rights of households, cooperatives and cities to produce and sell their own renewable energy without punitive fees or excessive red tape. For example, the Parliament would like to see an end to measures like the Spanish ‘sun tax’, which imposes steep fees on anyone placing solar panels on their roof and using the electricity in their own home. Other rules favoured by governments would, for example, place additional burdens on tenants living in apartment blocks and require those feeding even small amounts of electricity into the power grid to comply with the same obligations as large power companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Parliament also disagrees with governments over the minimum share of Europe’s energy that must come from renewables by 2030. Most governments favour a 27 percent target, but some countries, such as Sweden, have backed a minimum 35 percent target, while others have said they can go beyond 30 percent [2]. The Parliament is also calling for a minimum 35 percent target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having more renewable energy in the mix would improve air quality [3] and reduce carbon emissions. Greenpeace warns that a renewables target of at least 45 percent by 2030 would be in line with the EU’s commitments under the Paris climate agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845" target="_blank"&gt;A 2016 report commissioned&lt;/a&gt; by Greenpeace and others showed that, with the right support, almost &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf"&gt;half of all Europeans&lt;/a&gt; could produce their own electricity from renewables by 2050, meeting nearly half of the EU’s electricity demand. Power companies would provide the remainder of Europe’s renewable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final negotiating session between the European Parliament, EU governments and the European Commission will take place on 29 May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*** First high-res photos available &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJX53KVQ"&gt;&lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;. More photos and video available soon. ***&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Belgium, the Czech Republic, Finland, France, Hungary, Italy and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Austria, Denmark, France, Portugal, Lithuania and Luxembourg have indicated they can support an EU 2030 renewable energy target beyond 30 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The European Commission is expected to refer several European governments to the European Court of Justice over breaches of the EU’s air pollution limits today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;, +32 476 96 13 75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press release is also available on: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-17 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/European%20Parliament%20solar%20panels.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Activists call out EU ministers for failing to support renewable energy development</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Activists-call-out-EU-ministers-for-failing-to-support-renewable-energy-development/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Sofia/Brussels, 19 April 2018 – Climate change activists demonstrating outside a meeting of EU energy ministers in the Bulgarian capital Sofia urged European governments to stop restricting the rights of people to produce and share their own renewable energy.


&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div style="color: #222222; font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: small; font-variant-ligatures: normal; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; word-spacing: 0px; text-decoration-style: initial; text-decoration-color: initial;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="color: #222222; font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: small; font-variant-ligatures: normal; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; word-spacing: 0px; background-color: #ffffff; text-decoration-style: initial; text-decoration-color: initial; float: none; display: inline;"&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRUPV_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRUPV_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** First high-res photos available &lt;a href="https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJXTF2WL?"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;More photos and video available soon **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The ministers were meeting to discuss the final stages of talks with the European Parliament and the European Commission on the EU’s Renewable Energy Directive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activists unfurled a giant sun-shaped banner outside the Bulgarian National Palace of Culture, where the meeting was taking place, reading &lt;em&gt;“Our Sun. Our Power. Our Future.”&lt;/em&gt; The 25 activists, from nine countries [1], delivered messages from people across Europe calling on ministers to power the transition away from fossil fuel and nuclear energy production to clean, renewable energy. The banner was covered with hundreds of selfies sent in by people all over Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Ansgar Kiene&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Europe could be a real leader on renewables, but energy ministers are trying to keep us in the dark ages of corporate monopolies and dirty energy production. They are actively blocking people from participating in Europe’s energy transition and siding with power companies who refuse to give up control. Instead, they should recognise the right for people to produce, consume and share their own renewable energy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final negotiating sessions between EU governments, the European Parliament and the European Commission will be held on 17 and 29 May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main points of contention is the rights of individuals, cooperatives and cities to produce and sell their own renewable energy. The position agreed among EU energy ministers could seriously penalise people generating their own energy. For example it would allow national governments to impose punitive fees and to heavily restrict how and where people can produce and share energy, with additional burdens on those who do not own their own roof, such as tenants. Governments could also burden prosumers with the same registration requirements as large power companies, if they feed any amount of electricity into the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point under discussion is what share of Europe’s energy should come from renewables by 2030. The Commission originally proposed a target of at least 27 per cent, but seems open to at least 34 per cent. Most governments want to stick to a minimum 27 per cent target, but some countries, such as Sweden, have backed a minimum 35 per cent target. The Parliament is calling for a minimum 35 per cent target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845" target="_blank"&gt;A 2016 report by CE Delft&lt;/a&gt; showed that, with the right support, half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity from renewables by 2050, meeting nearly half of the EU’s electricity demand. Power companies would provide the remainder of Europe’s renewable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** First high-res photos available at &lt;a href="https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJXTF2WL?"&gt;https://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJXTF2WL?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;More photos and video available soon **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Bulgaria, Austria, Croatia, Germany, Hungary, the Netherlands, Poland, Romania and Slovakia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ansgar Kiene, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt; (English, German): &lt;a href="mailto:ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;ansgar.kiene@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;, +32 476 96 13 75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meglena Antonova, Greenpeace Bulgaria spokesperson&lt;/strong&gt; (Bulgarian): &lt;a href="mailto:meglena.antonova@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;meglena.antonova@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="tel:+359(885)5454797"&gt;+359 (885) 545 4797&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bojidar Nikolov, Greenpeace press officer&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="mailto:bojidar.nikolov@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;bojidar.nikolov@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="tel:+35(998)8908507"&gt;+35 (998) 890 8507&lt;/a&gt;, +359 (885) 545 4797&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;:+32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-19 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRUPV_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>European Parliament backs biodiversity over pesticides</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/European-Parliament-backs-biodiversity-over-pesticides/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Today the European Parliament agreed with the European Commission that agricultural land dedicated to the preservation of biodiversity must not be treated with pesticides, rejecting an attempt by the Parliament’s agriculture committee to block this ban.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/agriculture%20for%20CAP.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/agriculture%20for%20CAP.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“It is high time that the use of pesticides is banned on agricultural lands that have been dedicated to biodiversity protection. It would have been outrageous not to. The EU is about to enter into an indispensable reform of its agriculture policy, so today’s decision will not be the last in the battle for ecologically sound farming that sustains people, animals and the planet.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the 2013 reform of the common agriculture policy, farmers have to identify so-called ecological focus areas, covering 5 per cent of EU farmland. In these areas, farming practices must benefit biodiversity and protect the climate. These rules were progressively weakened and now allow for the planting of certain crops (legumes and catch crops) and the spraying of chemical pesticides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February, the Commission used its delegated powers to change these rules, prohibiting pesticide-use in ecological focus areas. Two members of the European Parliament’s agriculture committee, Albert Dess and John Stuart Agnew, subsequently proposed a Parliamentary veto to this ban, which was narrowly rejected by today’s plenary vote. The proposed veto received 363 votes, falling short of the required qualified majority of 376.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director: +32 (0)477 777 034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-14 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/agriculture%20for%20CAP.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transport</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace activists bare their lungs for clean air</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Greenpeace-activists-bare-their-lungs-for-clean-air/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Commission ordered Member States to explain inaction on dangerous air pollution&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Nine Greenpeace activists baring their lungs on their chests demanded “Clean Air Now” outside a closed-door emergency meeting called by EU Environment Commissioner, Karmenu Vella. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRIGN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRIGN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the European Commission &lt;a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-17-238_en.htm"&gt;warned&lt;/a&gt; five countries, namely Germany, France, Spain, Italy and the United Kingdom, of imminent court action over continuous breaches of European air quality standards, in place since 2010. The Czech Republic, Romania, Hungary and Slovakia were also called into &lt;a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-18-348_en.htm"&gt;today’s meeting&lt;/a&gt; for breaches of the EU’s air quality laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace air quality campaigner&lt;/strong&gt; Benjamin Stephan said: “Car fumes are killing tens of thousands across Europe. While there are laws to protect us, for years our governments have simply not been taking the action necessary to stop illegal levels of air pollution. That is criminal, and should be penalised. Every day of delay in switching from diesel and petrol cars to clean forms of transport, will result in more deaths and make driving bans inevitable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen dioxide (NO2) is one of several toxic air pollutants emitted from the internal combustion engine of automobiles. It can cause cardiovascular and respiratory diseases like asthma. The European Environmental Agency estimates that NO2 causes 75,000 premature deaths across the EU annually (1). The toxic gas mainly originates from traffic, particularly from diesel cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nine countries have been violating EU air quality thresholds for nitrogen dioxide since 2010. The &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/air/quality/"&gt;EU’s air quality law&lt;/a&gt; obliges Member States to limit the exposure of citizens to harmful air pollutants and sets an annual average threshold of 40 µg/m3 for NO2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;(1)   Report on air quality in Europe published by the European Environment Agency, 2017, &lt;a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/air-quality-in-europe-2017"&gt;https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/air-quality-in-europe-2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Gregor Kessler – Greenpeace press officer: &lt;a href="tel:+49%201517%202702918" target="_blank"&gt;+49 (151) 72 70 29 18&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="mailto:gregor.kessler@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;gregor.kessler@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Benjamin Stephan – Greenpeace air quality campaigner: &lt;a href="tel:+49%201515%207208151" target="_blank"&gt;+49 (151) 57 20 81 51&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:benjamin.stephan@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;benjamin.stephan@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photos:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://act.gp/2nltieU"&gt;http://act.gp/2nltieU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-01-30 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>AirPollution</tags1><categories>POLLUTION</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRIGN_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Three neonicotinoids down, more bee-killing pesticides to go</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/neonicotinoids-down-bee-killing-pesticides/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	European governments have backed a European Commission plan for a near-total ban of three bee-killing neonicotinoid insecticides. Representatives from 16 countries meeting in Brussels voted in support of the EU ban.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Four countries opposed the ban and eight abstained. The countries supporting the ban were: France, Germany, Spain, Italy, the United Kingdom, the Netherlands, Austria, Sweden, Greece, Portugal, Ireland, Slovenia, Estonia, Cyprus, Luxembourg, Malta, representing 76.1 per cent of the EU population. Those opposing were: Romania, the Czech Republic, Hungary and Denmark. Those abstaining were: Poland, Belgium, Slovakia, Finland, Bulgaria, Croatia, Latvia and Lithuania.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy adviser Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“This is great news for pollinators and our wider environment, but there was never any question that these three neonicotinoids had to go. Now the EU must make sure that they are not simply swapped with other harmful chemicals. These three neonicotinoids are just the tip of the iceberg – there are many more pesticides out there, including other neonicotinoids, that are just as dangerous for bees and food production. Governments must ban all bee-harming pesticides and finally shift away from toxic chemicals in farming.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ban will extend a 2013 &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2013/485/oj"&gt;partial ban&lt;/a&gt; of three neonicotinoids – Bayer’s imidacloprid and clothianidin, and Syngenta’s thiamethoxam – to cover all open-field uses, but allows their use in permanent greenhouses [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research indicates that several other insecticides are a threat to bees and other beneficial insects, including four neonicotinoids currently authorised in the EU - &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-017-0394-3"&gt;acetamiprid, thiacloprid, sulfoxaflor and flupyradifurone&lt;/a&gt; - and other insecticides, like &lt;a href="http://bees-decline.org/"&gt;cypermethrin, deltamethrin and chlorpyrifos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to address the wider chemical burden on bees could mean that farmers simply replace banned chemicals with other permitted chemicals that may be just as harmful, warned Greenpeace. To avoid this, the EU must:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ban all neonicotinoids, as France is considering [2];&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;apply the same strict testing standards to all pesticides [3];&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;dramatically reduce the use of synthetic pesticides and support the transition to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Agriculture/Food-and-Farming-Vision/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ecological methods of pest control&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/approval_active_substances/approval_renewal/neonicotinoids_en"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ban&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; says that “[EU] Member States must pay particular attention to […] the exposure of bees via the consumption of contaminated water from the permanent greenhouses”, but recommends no restriction. However, scientific evidence shows that neonicotinoids leach into the soil around greenhouses, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Bee-killing-pesticides-dangerous-greenhouses/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;contaminating watercourses&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and threatening bees.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2] &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Neonicotinoids will be&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexteArticle.do;jsessionid=C8F8021D2E27C42F343E85B837944DE7.tpdila09v_2?idArticle=JORFARTI000033016345&amp;amp;cidTexte=JORFTEXT000033016237&amp;amp;dateTexte=29990101&amp;amp;categorieLien=id"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;banned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in France from 1 September 2018 onwards, with certain uses allowed until 1 July 2020. The ban covers the three chemicals already restricted at EU level, as well as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;acetamiprid &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;thiacloprid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;. It may also include &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sulfoxaflor &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;flupyradifurone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, depending on the outcome of ongoing discussions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[3] &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;EFSA has applied a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/3295"&gt;&lt;span&gt;more comprehensive approach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in its latest assessments of the risks chemicals pose to bees. The Commission has proposed using this method for all pesticide risk assessments, but European governments are yet to agree.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-27 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Giant weedkiller bottle torn down as Europe debates future of glyphosate </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Giant-weedkiller-bottle-torn-down-as-Europe-debates-future-of-glyphosate-/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;1.3 Million Europeans call for ban in fastest growing citizens initiative&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - Citizens toppled a giant glyphosate bottle at the Schuman roundabout outside the European Commission to symbolise the demand of over 1.3 million people across Europe calling for a ban of the controversial weedkiller [1]. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Campact_Felix_Kindermann.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Campact_Felix_Kindermann.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, EU members states were meeting to discuss the licensing of glyphosate in the European Union [2]. The debate over its future prompted the fastest growing European Citizens’ Initiative in history; it demands an end to its use, an overall reduction in pesticide use, and more transparency in their safety assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Schwartz, ECI Coordinator at WeMove.EU said&lt;/strong&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;There is more than enough scientific evidence of glyphosate’s health and environmental harm to justify a ban. Over one million Europeans are asking for a glyphosate ban and a transition to a pesticide-free future. Every day, organic farmers are showing that it is possible to be productive and profitable without pesticides. It is high time our governments listen to their citizens, dismiss industry-peddled information and reject the Commission’s proposal to keep glyphosate on the market for another ten years.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission is proposing relicensing glyphosate for ten years, despite the UN’s independent cancer experts, IARC, saying that it is a&lt;a href="http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf"&gt; “probable” cause of cancer&lt;/a&gt;. California has recently added glyphosate to its list of chemicals that can cause cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious concerns have also been raised about the corporate capture of the glyphosate regulatory process. The inspector general of the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/epa-inspector-general-probing-collusion-with-monsanto_us_59372108e4b0aba888b99dca?ncid=engmodushpmg00000004"&gt; launched an investigation&lt;/a&gt; into potential collusion between a former senior staff member and Monsanto, the world’s biggest glyphosate producer.&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/may/24/eu-declared-monsanto-weedkiller-safe-after-intervention-from-controversial-us-official"&gt; Additional information&lt;/a&gt; suggests that that the same EPA employee played an improper role in the European safety assessment of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) and the European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) have said glyphosate is unlikely to cause cancer, but have pointed to serious environmental damage caused by the chemical. EFSA is also currently assessing evidence that glyphosate disrupts the human hormone system [3].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Christopher Portier, one of ninety-six independent scientists who publicly stated that the EFSA assessment is&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf"&gt; not supported by the evidence submitted&lt;/a&gt;, also warned that EFSA and ECHA failed to identify&lt;a href="https://usrtk.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/Portier-Letter28May2017-5.pdf"&gt; numerous tumour findings&lt;/a&gt; in the confidential industry-submitted animal studies. EFSA and ECHA &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/documents/10162/23294236/portier_echa_efsa_response.pdf/?utm_source=POLITICO.EU&amp;amp;utm_campaign=5433d0f45a-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2017_07_06&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_term=0_10959edeb5-5433d0f45a-189810753"&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt; that the studies “have been adequately considered and therefore [they] see no need for [their] evaluations to be revisited”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] In February 2017, a coalition of civil society organisations launched a&lt;a href="http://www.stopglyphosate.org/"&gt; European Citizens’ Initiative&lt;/a&gt; calling on the European Commission to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU. In just four months, over 1.3 people have called on the European Commission to ban the use of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] The EU licence for glyphosate runs out at the end of 2017. The European Commission has proposed renewing EU approval for another 10 years, based on the EFSA and ECHA evaluations. For more detailed information, please refer to this&lt;a href="https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20170605%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline_update.pdf"&gt; timeline&lt;/a&gt; of past and future events in the glyphosate decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.2903/j.efsa.2015.4302/epdf"&gt; European Food Safety Authority (EFSA)&lt;/a&gt; has identified a high long-term risk to mammals, and a high long-term risk to birds arising from pre-planting and pre-harvesting uses. The&lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/-/glyphosate-not-classified-as-a-carcinogen-by-echa"&gt; European Chemicals Agency (ECHA)&lt;/a&gt; has classified glyphosate as “toxic to aquatic life with long lasting effects”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Schwartz – &lt;/strong&gt;ECI Coordinator, WeMove.EU, +32 (0)486 07 83 42, &lt;a href="mailto:david@wemove.eu" target="_blank"&gt;david@wemove.eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daniel Boese&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;– &lt;/strong&gt;Media Campaigner, Avaaz, +49 177 840 5700, &lt;a href="mailto:daniel.boese@avaaz.org" target="_blank"&gt;daniel.boese@avaaz.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo: Felix Kindermann / Campact - Creative Commons &lt;a class="photo-license-url" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/" rel="license cc:license" target="_newtab" data-rapid_p="32"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/MonographVolume112.pdf</value><value>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/Prof_Portier_letter.pdf</value><value>https://usrtk.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/Portier-Letter28May2017-5.pdf</value><value>https://secured-static.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/20170605%20BR%20glyphosate%20timeline_update.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-07-17 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Campact_Felix_Kindermann.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>European Parliament resoundingly votes to end glyphosate use</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/European-Parliament-resoundingly-votes-to-end-glyphosate-use/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - Today the European Parliament resoundingly voted for an end to glyphosate use by 2022, with 355 in favour, 204 against and 111 abstentions.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Glypho_protest.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Glypho_protest.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution calls for a staged ban. From 16 December 2017, these uses should be banned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•    Use of glyphosate by non-professionals.&lt;br&gt; •    Use in or close to public parks, public playgrounds or public gardens.&lt;br&gt; •    Use to chemically dry out crops before harvest.&lt;br&gt; •    Agricultural use “where integrated pest management systems are sufficient for the necessary weed management”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 16 December 2022, all remaining uses should be ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important shift in the Parliament's position. While today's vote is for a ban, &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P8-TA-2016-0119+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN"&gt;in 2016&lt;/a&gt; the Parliament had voted for a seven year licence coupled with restrictions on the uses of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU food policy director said: “The Parliament clearly says that glyphosate has got to go. Although the phase out periods are longer than technically needed, the Parliament’s proposal is a breath of fresh air. More than one million Europeans and now the Parliament are calling for ban on this dangerous chemical. It’s time for the Commission and national governments to hear this message.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg &lt;/strong&gt;– Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Ullmann&lt;/strong&gt;: Greenpeace communications officer: +32 (0)2 274 1915, +32 (0)486 88 52 12 &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press release is available on: &lt;a class="zoom" href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a class="zoom" href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-10-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Glypho_protest.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU budget leaves environment in the cold</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-budget-environment-cold/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Commission has slashed funding earmarked for environmental protection in a draft seven-year EU budget released today.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The Commission has removed environmental funding under the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP), which is the biggest part of the EU budget, accounting for almost 40 percent of the EU’s expenditure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Under the current budget (2014-2020), 30 percent of direct CAP payments to farmers (which take up about 80 percent of CAP funding) is conditional on meeting minimum environmental standards. This is by far the largest EU funding stream for environmental protection.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“It’s shocking that the Commission hasn’t ring-fenced money for environmental protection in the EU’s direct payments to farmers, especially considering the damage done by industrial farming. The EU is already lagging behind in its commitments to tackle climate change, water and air pollution, and environmental destruction – to have nothing set aside to address these failures in its single largest expenditure is unacceptable. European governments and the EU Parliament need to fix this budget so that the EU can back up its promises for greener and fairer farming.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The EU budget, known as the Multiannual Financial Framework, outlines the total budget of the European Union for the next seven years (2021-2027) and allocates funds to different sectors and policies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 47 777 7034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU/"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-02 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Food</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Halve meat and dairy production to protect climate, nature and health</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/halve-meat-protect-climate-nature-health/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Global meat and dairy production and consumption must be cut in half by 2050 to avoid dangerous climate change and keep the Paris climate agreement on track, says a new Greenpeace report.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;**Read our vision, Less is more: reducing meat and dairy for a healthier life and planet, and the scientific background here: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision"&gt;www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;** &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;In Europe, the reform of the common agricultural policy must help facilitate a transition away from industrial animal farming, while supporting the increasing numbers of farmers shifting towards ecological plant, meat and dairy production, said Greenpeace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EU agricultural policies have been driving us towards an environmental cliff edge. Industrial animal farming is a major source of carbon emissions, water and air pollution, and causes major health problems like antibiotic resistance. Our governments must ensure that the upcoming reform of farm rules accelerates a shift to ecological vegetable farming and less, but sustainable, animal farming, while withdrawing support from intensive animal production.”&lt;/em&gt;                                                             &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Three out of every four animals reared in Europe are kept in a small number of very large farms, while the smallest farms have reduced their herds by 50 per cent.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;If left unchecked, agriculture is projected to produce 52 per cent of global greenhouse gas emissions in the coming decades, 70 per cent of which will come from the meat and dairy sector. Animal farming in Europe already contributes 12-17 per cent of the EU’s greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;It is also a major source of water and air pollution, in particular from nitrogen and phosphorus in water, and ammonia and fine particulate matter (known as PM2.5) in the air. Nitrogen pollution alone costs the EU up to €320 billion every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Last week, the European Food Safety Authority and the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control described antibiotic resistance as “one of the biggest threats to public health”, &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2017/running-out-antibiotics/en/"&gt;echoing statements&lt;/a&gt; by the World Health Organization. &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/180227"&gt;A joint report&lt;/a&gt; by the two agencies confirmed the presence of bacteria in farmed animals that have developed resistance to crucial antibiotics used to treat people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-250b44cb-f541-0ea7-59f2-a05b0ac6af23"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pete Smith, former convening lead author for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The need to reduce demand for livestock products is now a scientifically mainstream view. Only a significant decrease in meat and milk consumption will allow us to deliver a food system fit for the future – for the benefit of humans and the planet as a whole. Producing the same mix of foods as we consume now, even if we were to do so more sustainably, cannot deliver the reduction in environmental impacts we need to protect the planet for our children and their children.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Read our vision,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Less is more: reducing meat and dairy for a healthier life and planet,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; and the scientific background here:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)477 777034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-05 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Industrial%20pig%20farming%20in%20Germany.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Glyphosate: a licence is a licence, no matter how long it’s for</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Glyphosate-a-licence-is-a-licence-no-matter-how-long-its-for/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Greenpeace comment
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;Brussels&lt;/strong&gt; - Commenting on the European Commission’s new plan to push for a five- or seven-year licence for the weedkiller glyphosate, &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;“What matters is how much glyphosate is used and how it’s used, not how long the licence is for. The European Parliament and Europeans want a ban, not a fudge that changes nothing about how much people are exposed and how much the environment is contaminated.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;Over one million people signed a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="https://stopglyphosate.org/en/"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;European citizen’s initiative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt; calling for a glyphosate ban, while recent &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="https://www.sumofus.org/media/new-glyphosate-polls-2017-en/"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;polling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt; shows overwhelming support for a ban across Europe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;Contacts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;Laura Ullmann&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;: Greenpeace EU communications officer: +32 (0)486 88 52 12, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="mailto:laura.ullmann@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:laura.ullmann@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;laura.ullmann@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;This press release is available on: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a style="text-decoration: none;" href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #1155cc; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-10-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/stop_glyphosate_logo.png</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>First pan-European field study confirms neonicotinoid pesticides harm bees </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/First-pan-EU-field-study-confirms-neonic-harm/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Greenpeace’s comment on new findings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Exeter, 29 June 2017 - A major industry-funded field study [1] assessing the impacts of neonicotinoid pesticides clothianidin and thiamethoxam on honeybees and wild bees confirms that these chemicals harm these species. The study is due for publication in the international journal Science on 30 June.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; Commenting on the findings, Dr David Santillo, senior scientist with the Greenpeace Research Laboratories at Exeter University, said&lt;/strong&gt;: "&lt;em&gt;This novel study confirms that adverse effects on individual bees and bee colonies found in high-dose laboratory studies are also observed in the fields. It shows that industry claims that neonicotinoids do not harm bees at field-relevant concentrations are baseless&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg, Greenpeace EU Food Policy Director&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;said&lt;/strong&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;This industry-funded study adds to the mounting evidence that neonicotinoid insecticides harm managed and wild bees. The case for a complete ban on these pesticides is now unassailable. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bees are a vital pillar of our ecosystem and food chain - we cannot afford to take any chances with their well-being.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March, the European Commission proposed an almost complete ban on imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam [2]. The proposals are based on an assessment by the European Food Safety Agency (EFSA) that bees could be harmed not only via the treated crop but also via residues that persist in the wider landscape. Today’s study confirms this concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Woodcock, B.A., Bullock, J.M., Shore, R.F., Heard, M.S., Pereira, M.G., Redhead, J., Ridding, L., Dean, H., Sleep, D., Henrys, P., Peyton, J., Hulmes, S., Hulmes, L., Sárosspataki, M., Saure, C. &amp;amp; Pywell, R.F., ‘Country-specific effects of neonicotinoid pesticides on honeybees and wild bees,’ &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, VOL 356, ISSUE 6345, DOI: 10.1126/science.aaa1190, published online 30 June 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Greenpeace press release, 23 March 2017: &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-takes-major-step-to-ban-three-neonics/"&gt;http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Commission-takes-major-step-to-ban-three-neonics/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace ‘food for life project’, EU communications coordinator​&lt;/strong&gt;: Luisa Colasimone, +32 (0)479 100 067, &lt;a href="mailto:luisa.colasimone@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;luisa.colasimone@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace Research Laboratories, Senior Scientist: &lt;/strong&gt;Dr David Santillo&lt;strong&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;+44 1392 247920, &lt;a href="mailto:david.santillo@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;david.santillo@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-29 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Bee_Eco-farm_GP0STPA99_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Growing number of EU governments oppose re-approval of glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Growing-number-EU-governments-oppose-glyphosate/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - Amid mounting political and public opposition to glyphosate, representatives of European governments have again rejected the Commission’s proposal to grant the controversial and widely used weedkiller a new licence. A final vote has been postponed to November.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Stop%20glifosato.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Stop%20glifosato.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Glyphosate protest at the ministry of health in Rome
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Reacting to the news,&lt;strong&gt; Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“Glyphosate is the asbestos of our generation. It’s everywhere and the dangers are known. The damage it causes to the environment and our health has been exposed. Monsanto’s interference in the science has been exposed. Today the Commission failed for the fifth time in a row to get sufficient support from European governments to renew glyphosate’s licence. The tables are turning and unless the Commission backs a ban, it will continue to fail.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;There is growing opposition to a renewal of glyphosate’s licence. According to media &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/eu-vote-to-renew-glyphosate-for-10-years-fails/?utm_content=buffer4f16a&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;amp;utm_campaign=buffer"&gt;&lt;span&gt;reports&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, since the last vote in 2016, four countries supporting a licence now oppose it (Belgium, Croatia, Slovenia, Sweden) and four countries who abstained now oppose it (Austria, Greece, Italy, Luxembourg). Bulgaria has moved from abstaining to supporting.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Today, media reports indicate that ten countries said that they would vote against a ten-year renewal of the glyphosate licence (Belgium, Greece, Croatia, France, Italy, Luxembourg, Malta, Austria, Slovenia and Sweden), while two countries abstained (Germany and Portugal). Sixteen countries said they would vote in favour (Bulgaria, Denmark, Czech Republic, Estonia, Ireland, Spain, Cyprus, Latvia, Lithuania, Hungary, the Netherlands, Poland, Romania, Slovakia, Finland and the U.K.).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament has also called for a full glyphosate ban within five years, starting with a partial ban this year. In 2016 the Parliament had supported a new seven-year licence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Over one million people have signed a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://stopglyphosate.org/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;European citizen’s initiative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; calling for a glyphosate ban, while recent &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sumofus.org/media/new-glyphosate-polls-2017-en"&gt;&lt;span&gt;polling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; shows growing concern and overwhelming support for a ban across five EU countries (Germany, France, Italy, Portugal and Greece).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Since early 2016, the Commission has backed an unrestricted EU licence for glyphosate. On five occasions it failed to garner sufficient support from European governments (on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Glyphosate-licence-renewal-suspended-in-light-of-health-concerns-/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;8 March 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Greenpeace-comment-on-EU-glyphosate-decision/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;19 May 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Greenpeace-comment-EU-vote-on-glyphosate-extension/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;6 June 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2016/Commission-must-prepare-glyphosate-exit-plan/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;24 June 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press release is available on:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-10-25 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Stop%20glifosato.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission fails to muster support for 3 GMOs</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/No-GMO-support/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – National government representatives voting today did not provide the support needed by the European Commission to approve two new genetically modified (GM) crops and extend approval of the only GM crop currently grown in the EU. The vote shows that the Commission is a long way from achieving the qualified majority [1] needed for the approval of the three pesticide-producing GM maizes [2].
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STOC8M_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STOC8M_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; said: “&lt;em&gt;Today’s vote is a clear sign that there is still no appetite for GM crops in Europe. Most countries failed to support the Commission’s proposals,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;despite the fact that they can now ban their cultivation nationally. Given the widespread opposition to GM crops among EU citizens and parliamentarians, the Commission would be blind to interpret this as a green light. GM crops are nothing but a prop for the harmful, intensive agriculture that is promoted by agrochemical companies. Europe should turn the page on GMOs once and for all, and focus its efforts on the urgently needed shift to ecologically sound farming.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission has proposed authorising the cultivation of DuPont Pioneer’s 1507 maize and Syngenta’s Bt11 maize, and to renew the licence for Monsanto’s maize MON810, the only GM crop currently grown in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If confirmed, the three authorisations would only be valid in 9 out of 28 EU countries, as well as in three regions (England in the UK, Flanders and the Brussels region in Belgium). The other EU countries and the remaining regions in the UK and Belgium have used the EU’s new &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/gmo/authorisation/cultivation/geographical_scope_en.htm"&gt;opt-out mechanism&lt;/a&gt; to prevent GM crops from being grown in their territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission has indicated that it will take the decision on the three GMOs to an appeals committee of EU country representatives this spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament has repeatedly clashed with the European Commission over its policy on genetically modified organisms (GMOs). In December 2015, &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P8-TA-2015-0456+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN&amp;amp;language=EN"&gt;it called for a moratorium on all GMO import authorisations&lt;/a&gt; until new decision-making rules are in place. It has opposed the authorisation of several GMOs for import to the EU and rejected the proposed authorisations of GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1085%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize 1507&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1083%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize Bt11&lt;/a&gt; and GM &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-%2f%2fEP%2f%2fNONSGML%2bMOTION%2bB8-2016-1086%2b0%2bDOC%2bPDF%2bV0%2f%2fEN"&gt;maize MON810&lt;/a&gt; for cultivation in the EU.&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GM crops have no place in sustainable farming. They come with unacceptable risks created by the genetic engineering process and the traits they are engineered to express. At the same time, they have &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Agriculture/Twenty-Years-of-Failure/"&gt;failed to deliver&lt;/a&gt; on the promises made by their producers. To protect the environment and our health, the European Union should ban GMOs and promote ecological farming methods instead of following the example of the handful of other countries where GM crops are grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For more information about the authorisation of the three GM maize varieties, read our &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201701%20BR%20GM%20maize%20authorisations%20FINAL_teosinte_EP_vote.pdf"&gt;media briefing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt; [1] The Commission was seeking support from a qualified majority of countries. This requires the favourable vote of at least 16 countries, representing at least 65% of the EU population.                                                                                                                         &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] On &lt;strong&gt;GM maize MON810&lt;/strong&gt;, 12 EU countries voted against approval (AT, BG, CY, DK, EL, FR, HU, IE, LU, LV,  PL, SI), representing 31 per cent of the EU population; 10 EU countries voted in favour (CZ, EE, ES, FI, IT, LT, NL, RO,  SE, UK), representing 47 per cent; and six abstained (BE, DE, HR, MT, PT, SK), representing 22 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;GM maize 1507 and Bt 11&lt;/strong&gt;, 13 EU countries voted against (AT, BG, CY, DK, EL, IE, FR, HU, LU, LV, PL, SI, SE), representing 33 per cent of the EU population; eight voted in favour (EE, ES, FI, IT, LT, NL, RO, UK), representing 43 per cent; and seven abstained (BE, CZ, DE, HR, MT, PT, SK), representing 24 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – &lt;/strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director, +32 (0)498 362403, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt; Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201701%20BR%20GM%20maize%20authorisations%20FINAL_teosinte_EP_vote.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-01-27 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP0STOC8M_Low_res_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU court: protecting people and nature takes precedence over business interests</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-court-protecting-people-nature-precedence/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Bayer and Syngenta lose court cases against  2013 partial neonicotinoid ban&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The General Court of the European Union has ruled that the European Commission was right to impose restrictions on the use of three bee-killing neonicotinoid pesticides – imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The court upheld the 2013 restrictions on the three pesticides, rejecting two separate legal challenges by Bayer and Syngenta, makers of imidacloprid and clothianidin, and thiamethoxam respectively. In its &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/jcms/p1_1035809/en/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;press statement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, the court asserted that the European Union’s precautionary principle “gives precedence to the requirements relating to the protection of public health, safety and the environment over economic interests.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace intervened in the Bayer and Syngenta cases to provide evidence and legal arguments in support of the restrictions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy adviser Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The ruling sets the EU’s priorities straight – its primary duty is to protect people and nature, not company profit margins. It’s an indictment against corporate bullying that should spur the Commission to act on other dangerous pesticides without fear of being challenged in court.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Research indicates that several other pesticides are a threat to bees and other beneficial insects, including four neonicotinoids currently authorised in the EU –&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-017-0394-3"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;acetamiprid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;thiacloprid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sulfoxaflor &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;flupyradifurone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; – and other insecticides, like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://bees-decline.org/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;cypermethrin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;deltamethrin &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;chlorpyrifos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Failure to address the wider chemical burden on bees could mean that farmers simply replace banned chemicals with other permitted chemicals that may be just as harmful, warned Greenpeace. To avoid this, the EU must:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; ·        ban all neonicotinoids, as France is considering [1];&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;·        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;apply the same strict testing standards to all pesticides [2];&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;·        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;dramatically reduce the use of synthetic pesticides and support the transition to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Agriculture/Food-and-Farming-Vision/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ecological methods of pest control&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The pesticide producers are expected to appeal the ruling.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[1] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Neonicotinoids will be &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexteArticle.do;jsessionid=C8F8021D2E27C42F343E85B837944DE7.tpdila09v_2?idArticle=JORFARTI000033016345&amp;amp;cidTexte=JORFTEXT000033016237&amp;amp;dateTexte=29990101&amp;amp;categorieLien=id"&gt;&lt;span&gt;banned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in France from 1 September 2018 onwards, with certain uses allowed until 1 July 2020. The ban covers the three chemicals already restricted at EU level, as well as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;acetamiprid &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;thiacloprid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;. It may also include &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sulfoxaflor &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;flupyradifurone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, depending on the outcome of ongoing discussions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;[2] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EFSA has applied a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/3295"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;more comprehensive approach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in its latest assessments of the risks chemicals pose to bees. The Commission has proposed using this method for all pesticide risk assessments, but European governments are yet to agree.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg – Greenpeace EU food policy director&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-17 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/bees%20in%20flight%20for%20twitter.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace Netherlands leaks EU-Mercosur trade papers</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Greenpeace-Netherlands-leaks-EU-Mercosur-trade-papers/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Increase in meat and soy trade would drive deforestation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Amsterdam/Brussels - Greenpeace Netherlands has released 171 pages of previously undisclosed documents from secret talks for an EU-Mercosur trade agreement.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Soy%20plantation%20in%20the%20Brazilian%20Cerrado.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Soy%20plantation%20in%20the%20Brazilian%20Cerrado.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Soy plantation in the Brazilian Cerrado region
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The parties to the agreement – Argentina, Brazil, Uruguay, Paraguay, and the EU – hope to announce a political agreement at a new round of talks taking place this week.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.trade-leaks.org/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;leaks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; expose the failure of the European Commission and European governments to stick to commitments on transparency, said Greenpeace. NGOs warn that the EU-Mercosur trade deal is a major threat for the climate and the preservation of natural habitats in South America, including the Amazon and Cerrado regions in Brazil.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;EU negotiators have offered Mercosur countries a 78,000-tonne increase in beef imports. Observers expect this offer to increase to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pressreader.com/uk/the-scotsman/20171121/282140701679491"&gt;&lt;span&gt;100,000 to 130,000 tonnes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. Mercosur countries currently export about 200,000 tonnes of beef to the EU. According to media reports, the EU is in return seeking access for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/latin-america-may-be-where-malmstroms-luck-runs-out/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;car exports&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade campaigner Kees Kodde&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt; “Backroom trade talks undermine democracy and public trust in politicians. This trade deal in particular is overshadowed by serious corruption allegations in Brazil, the murders of environmental activists and indigenous leaders, and a major threat to the environment: Mercosur countries want to boost meat exports to Europe, which would push cattle farming into pristine habitats in the Amazon and the Cerrado regions in Brazil and the Chaco in Argentina.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The biggest export from Mercosur countries to the EU is soy, representing 22 per cent in export value. 94 per cent of the EU’s soybean meal imports comes from these countries. Researchers expect imports of soy from Mercosur countries to increase as a result of the trade deal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="m_4435973582468184367gmail-m_-1897019930340712957gmail-MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;The impact of cattle ranching in the Amazon forest and related ecosystems is well documented. Cattle is the biggest driver of deforestation in the Amazon, with &lt;a href="http://ipam.org.br/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/A-Pathway-to-Zero-Deforestation-in-the-Brazilian-Amazon-full-report.pdf" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://ipam.org.br/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/A-Pathway-to-Zero-Deforestation-in-the-Brazilian-Amazon-full-report.pdf&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513188754362000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH48DdoNBzjyZW3oxVJjTDYXXO-nQ"&gt;65% of deforested areas occupied by animal pastures&lt;/a&gt;. Brazil's Amazon region lost &lt;a href="http://www.inpe.br/noticias/noticia.php?Cod_Noticia=4344" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.inpe.br/noticias/noticia.php?Cod_Noticia%3D4344&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513188754362000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEv_ijoqH1EqRGsO43aBl_WjFo-Ug"&gt;&lt;span&gt;7.893 km²&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt; in&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt; 2016. The average rate of deforestation between 2013 and 2017 was &lt;a href="http://www.obt.inpe.br/prodes/dashboard/prodes-rates.html" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.obt.inpe.br/prodes/dashboard/prodes-rates.html&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513188754362000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH1Vdj0uQk_GoPogSj2Vpcmv4Zvuw"&gt;38% higher than in 2012&lt;/a&gt;, the year with the lowest rate recorded.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="m_4435973582468184367gmail-m_-1897019930340712957gmail-MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;Meanwhile, soy expansion for animal feed and other crops are endangering another ecosystem in the Brazilian Cerrado region, &lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;the world’s most biodiverse savannah. The Cerrado &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt; the birthplace of many of Brazil's great water systems and has already &lt;a href="https://d3nehc6yl9qzo4.cloudfront.net/downloads/cerradomanifesto_september2017_atualizadooutubro.pdf" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=https://d3nehc6yl9qzo4.cloudfront.net/downloads/cerradomanifesto_september2017_atualizadooutubro.pdf&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513188754362000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHIY8CeRSEykrW6tVTwlFXNyNqRQA"&gt;lost 50% of its original area&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt; In 2015, the land conversion in the Brazilian Cerrado was &lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ccst.inpe.br/perda-do-cerrado-e-50-maior-que-da-amazonia/" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.ccst.inpe.br/perda-do-cerrado-e-50-maior-que-da-amazonia/&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1513188754362000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH1SeBo6KjJRrnWxTLzsOjbjyo-TA"&gt;9.483 km2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span lang="EN-US"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Brazil is in the midst of a political crisis which has dismantled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.mongabay.com/2017/10/temer-offers-amnesty-erasing-up-to-2-1-billion-in-environmental-crime-fines/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;environmental&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.globalwitness.org/en/campaigns/environmental-activists/defenders-earth/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;human rights safeguards&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, and exposed previously protected areas of rainforest to deforestation from agriculture.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The leaked EU-Mercosur papers published by Greenpeace Netherlands are dated July 2017 (plus one document from 2016). If it is concluded, the EU-Mercosur agreement could be the EU’s biggest ever trade deal, covering a trade volume similar to the EU’s trade with Japan.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ENDS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This press release was amended on 12 December 2017 to incorporate new figures on deforestation and land use in Brazil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde - Greenpeace trade campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;: +31 6 53623818, &lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press release and the leaked chapters from the EU-Mercosur trade deal are also available on: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.trade-leaks.org/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.trade-leaks.org&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://ipam.org.br/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/A-Pathway-to-Zero-Deforestation-in-the-Brazilian-Amazon-full-report.pdf</value><value>https://d3nehc6yl9qzo4.cloudfront.net/downloads/cerradomanifesto_september2017_atualizadooutubro.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-07 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Soy%20plantation%20in%20the%20Brazilian%20Cerrado.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EUaffairs</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Joint letter on changes to EU decision-making concerning health, agriculture and food</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Improved-EU-decision-making-in-the-area-of-health-and-consumer-protection/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Five environmental, health and agriculture organisations (Friends of the Earth Europe, Greenpeace, HEAL, IFOAM EU and Pesticide Action Network Europe) wrote to EU Commission President Juncker to propose ways to improve the EU decision-making process in the area of health and consumer protection, including on agricultural products such as pesticides and genetically modified organisms (GMOs).
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Under current rules, the Commission can approve pesticides, biocides, GMOs and other regulated food and agricultural products without the support of a qualified majority of EU member states, and has done so frequently. This situation is untenable. It compromises the EU’s democratic credentials, and undermines the protection of public health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission is reviewing the decision-making process and on the eve of its publication, the organisations call for the EU to allow the use of potentially hazardous products and food preparation processes only when it is confident that this will not harm people or the environment, in line with the precautionary principle. And, to take different approaches to decisions in favour of such products and processes and those against such substances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170213_Open_Letter_Comitology.pdf"&gt;open letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/banners/2017/20170213_Open_Letter_Comitology.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-13 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Health</tags1><categories>POLLUTION</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>WaterPollution</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU court tells Germany to cut the crap</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-court-Germany-cut-crap/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Industrial farming to blame for manure polluting water, Greenpeace&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The Court of Justice of the EU (CJEU) has ruled that Germany breached EU law by allowing manure runoff from farms to pollute water.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;The court found that Germany allowed an excessive use of manure as a fertiliser, in violation of the limits set out in the EU’s nitrates directive, which aims to reduce water pollution caused by nitrates from agricultural sources.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manure doesn’t appear out of nowhere – industrial livestock farming is the clear culprit. We’re up to our necks in crap and the solution is not to stand on our tippy toes, but to drain the slurry. The manure problem isn’t only in Germany, a good start would be for the EU to stop funding the factory farms that pump it out.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The ruling by the Court of Justice echoes warnings by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;scientific institutions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/environmental-indicator-report-2014"&gt;&lt;span&gt;environmental authorities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; about the need to stop nitrate pollution from manure. Nitrate pollution of waterways can cause blooms of algae, which drain the water of oxygen, choking fish and other wildlife. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/dwq/chemicals/nitratenitrite2ndadd.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Nitrates can also be converted into toxic nitrite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in the human body, which is particularly dangerous for children and pregnant women. Researchers &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;have estimated that nitrogen pollution costs the EU &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;up to €320 billion every year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Germany will now have to comply with the Court decision, or face a new infringement procedure from the European Commission. This infringement procedure could result in a second Court ruling imposing Germany to pay fines, if it is found to still be in breach of EU law.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero - Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 477 777034, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf</value><value>http://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/dwq/chemicals/nitratenitrite2ndadd.pdf</value><value>http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-06-21 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/dairy%20farm%20milking_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU overturns barriers to rooftop revolution but renewable target falls short of serious climate action</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-overturns-barriers-to-rooftop-revolution-but-renewable-target-falls-short-of-serious-climate-action/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Solar panels could soon cover millions more rooftops in Europe, after the EU reached a deal on Wednesday to make it easier for households to play a part in the renewable energy transition, said Greenpeace.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Solar_on_roof_BG_GP0STQ6M3_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Solar_on_roof_BG_GP0STQ6M3_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Renewable installation at “Tuzha” Mountain Hut in Bulgaria
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, European governments curbed the Parliament’s efforts to increase the share of renewables in the EU’s energy system, with a review of the target in 2023, and rejected important safeguards against the harmful effects of bioenergy and biofuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EU energy policy adviser Sebastian Mang &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“This deal, for the first time, recognises the rights of ordinary people to participate in Europe’s energy revolution and overturns some very big barriers to the fight against climate change. It gives people and communities greater control over their energy use, empowering them to accelerate the development of renewable energy and challenge energy giants across the continent. But the renewables target of 32 percent is far too low and allows power companies to cling onto fossil fuels and false solutions.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal between the European Parliament and European governments establishes the right of European citizens, local authorities, small businesses and cooperatives to produce, consume, store and sell their own renewable energy, without being subject to punitive taxes or excessive red tape. It bans punitive measures that some countries introduced to prevent their citizens from participating in the energy transition, such as the requirement that individuals in Romania set up a company and meet fiscal requirements before they can sell any energy they produce to the grid. Another example is the Spanish ‘sun tax’, which hampers small-scale renewable energy production with steep fees and administrative hurdles. Ending punitive measures was one of the European Parliament’s core demands throughout negotiations with European governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time, EU law will acknowledge the role democratically controlled cooperatives play in the energy transition, making it easier for people to set up their own renewable energy projects and putting safeguards in place to protect them from the market dominance of major power companies. According to a recent &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.erneuerbareenergien.de/local-added-value-from-a-community-wind-farm/150/437/96249/"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, cooperative-owned projects bring eight times more revenue into the local economy than a project by a major power company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace also warned that the minimum renewable-energy target of 32 percent in 2030 falls dangerously short of the level necessary to prevent catastrophic climate change. The deal will also allow countries and companies to continue labelling harmful bioenergy as renewable energy, paving the way for more trees to be cut down and rainforests cleared for biofuel crops to fuel power plants, factories and cars. Negotiators agreed to freeze the use of of biofuels that significantly harm biodiversity, such as palm oil, at current levels, gradually phase them out by 2030 and end the current obligation for EU countries to include crop-based biofuels in their transport mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang - Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)407 623167, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 2741911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-06-14 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Solar_on_roof_BG_GP0STQ6M3_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU moves closer to ban of three bee-killing neonicotinoid insecticides</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-vote-ban-three-bees-neonicotinoids-insecticides/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	On 27 April 2018, representatives of EU governments meeting in Brussels will vote on a European Commission plan to ban three neonicotinoid insecticides: Bayer’s imidacloprid and clothianidin, and Syngenta’s thiamethoxam. The Commission has based its plan on an assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), which concluded that the neonicotinoids pose a risk to bees.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Dead%20bees%20in%20Austria.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Dead%20bees%20in%20Austria.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy adviser Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;: “The vote tomorrow is still touch and go, with some countries seemingly prepared to ignore the evidence on the impact of these neonicotinoids. To protect bees and their vital contribution to food production, governments must support a ban. But they must also recognise that these three neonicotinoids are just the tip of the iceberg. The use of four other neonicotinoids and other insecticides with similar effects on bees is completely unrestricted in Europe. Only France is moving towards a blanket ban on all neonicotinoids. A chemical-by-chemical approach can no longer guarantee the protection of the environment or health.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are neonicotinoids?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neonicotinoids are a relatively new class of insecticides, which are chemically similar to nicotine and affect the central nervous system of insects. Farmers apply them as seed coating, foliar spray or granules. Neonicotinoids have systemic properties, meaning that plants absorb and release them as they grow, including via their pollen and nectar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced in the 1990s, neonicotinoids have become the most widely used class of insecticide in the world. The neonicotinoid family now includes 13 compounds, including fourth-generation neonicotinoids and new derivatives [1]. Seven of these, including imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam are authorised in the European Union (EU).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Existing EU restrictions &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the EU imposed a &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2013/485/oj"&gt;partial ban&lt;/a&gt; on imidacloprid, clothianidin and thiamethoxam. The ban applies to crops such as maize, sunflower, oilseed rape, wheat, barley and oats, among others. It also covers uses in orchards before fruit trees have flowered. However, farmers can still apply neonicotinoids to crops harvested before flowering or not considered as attractive to bees, such as sugar beet and potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://curia.europa.eu/juris/fiche.jsf?id=T%3B429%3B13%3BRD%3B1%3BP%3B1%3BT2013%2F0429%2FP&amp;amp;language=en"&gt;Bayer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://curia.europa.eu/juris/fiche.jsf?id=T%3B451%3B13%3BRD%3B1%3BP%3B1%3BT2013%2F0451%2FP&amp;amp;language=en"&gt;Syngenta&lt;/a&gt; have challenged the EU’s partial ban at the European Court of Justice. A ruling is expected on 17 May 2018. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Near-total ban&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, the Commission proposed to extend the partial ban to a &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/approval_active_substances/approval_renewal/neonicotinoids_en"&gt;near-total ban&lt;/a&gt;. The Commission proposal is based on an EFSA analysis of studies commissioned by neonicotinoid producers. Based on these studies, EFSA concluded in 2016 that all uses of the three neonicotinoids as seed coating or granules either posed a high risk to bees or that a high risk could not be excluded. According to the &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/approval_active_substances/approval_renewal/neonicotinoids_en"&gt;Commission&lt;/a&gt;, “the currently still possible outdoor usage can no longer be considered safe”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU cancelled a vote planned for December 2017, after several countries wanted to delay the vote until results of the EFSA evaluation of the science were made public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/180228"&gt;EFSA&lt;/a&gt; published this evaluation on 28 February 2018. It confirmed that the three chemicals threaten both managed and wild bees, and that the restrictions imposed in 2013 are insufficient to control these risks. The &lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-science-europe-pesticides/pesticides-put-bees-at-risk-european-watchdog-confirms-idUSKCN1GC18G"&gt;Commission&lt;/a&gt; acknowledged that the EFSA report “[strengthened] the scientific basis for the Commission's proposal to ban outdoor use of the three neonicotinoids”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continued use in greenhouses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission proposal would still allow the use of the three neonicotinoids in permanent greenhouses. The &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/approval_active_substances/approval_renewal/neonicotinoids_en"&gt;Commission&lt;/a&gt; considers that “there is no risk to bees for all uses where the plants are treated in a permanent greenhouse and remain there during the whole lifecycle”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, EFSA has not assessed the risk to bees consuming contaminated surface water. Studies show that neonicotinoids contaminate &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Bee-killing-pesticides-dangerous-greenhouses/"&gt;watercourses&lt;/a&gt; around greenhouses, most likely through leaching into the soil or leakage from irrigation systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of imposing a total ban, the &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/approval_active_substances/approval_renewal/neonicotinoids_en"&gt;Commission proposal&lt;/a&gt; asks EU countries to “pay particular attention to […] the exposure of bees via the consumption of contaminated water from the permanent greenhouses”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EU government wavering &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2017, when the Commission first &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/plant/docs/sc_phyto_20171212_pppl_agenda.pdf"&gt;planned to hold a vote&lt;/a&gt;, 11 EU countries were in support of measures to restrict the use of the three neonicotinoids. Eleven countries are again expected to support the Commission’s proposal, including Germany, France, the UK, the Netherlands, Austria, Ireland, Croatia, Slovenia, Cyprus, Luxembourg and Malta. However, the Commission needs the backing of at least 16 EU countries, representing 65 per cent of the EU’s total population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Commission fails to garner sufficient support in a formal vote at the meeting on 27 April, it will schedule another vote in an &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/committees/appeal_en"&gt;appeals committee&lt;/a&gt;. If the vote again fails to deliver the required majority, the Commission has the power to adopt the measures it proposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many more bee-harming chemicals &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these three neonicotinoids, many other chemicals are a threat to bees and other beneficial insects. They include other neonicotinoids, such as thiacloprid and sulfoxaflor, as well as older insecticides, such as cypermethrin and chlorpyrifos. Failure to address the broader impact of insecticides on bees will likely lead many farmers simply to replace banned chemicals with other permitted chemicals that may be just as harmful. To avoid this, the EU must:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ban all neonicotinoids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A substance-by-substance approach is not appropriate when the evidence suggests that a whole class of chemical is potentially harmful. As &lt;a href="http://www.chemtrust.org/wp-content/uploads/chemtrust-toxicsoup-mar-18.pdf"&gt;ChemTrust&lt;/a&gt; has said: “As a point of principle, when substances of the same chemical group are likely to be similarly acting, and used in the same situation as that of a known harmful chemical in that group which has been regulated for use, regulation should be extended to cover that and all other similar compounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French government will &lt;a href="https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexteArticle.do;jsessionid=C8F8021D2E27C42F343E85B837944DE7.tpdila09v_2?idArticle=JORFARTI000033016345&amp;amp;cidTexte=JORFTEXT000033016237&amp;amp;dateTexte=29990101&amp;amp;categorieLien=id"&gt;ban&lt;/a&gt; all neonicotinoids from 1 September 2018 onwards, with certain uses allowed until 1 July 2020. The ban covers the three chemicals restricted in the EU, as well as acetamiprid and thiacloprid. It may also include sulfoxaflor and flupyradifurone, depending on the outcome of ongoing discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply the same standards to all pesticides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EFSA has applied a &lt;a href="http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/3295"&gt;more comprehensive approach&lt;/a&gt; in its latest assessments of the risks chemicals pose to bees. The Commission has proposed using this method for all pesticide risk assessments, but European governments still have to agree to this. The Commission should make this a priority in 2018 to ensure that all pesticides are evaluated to the same high standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce the use of synthetic pesticides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European governments and the Commission should ensure the application of EU legislation to &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/food/plant/pesticides/sustainable_use_pesticides_en"&gt;reduce the use of harmful pesticides&lt;/a&gt;, and guarantee that farm subsidies are dependent on the use of &lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/publications/Campaign-reports/Agriculture/Food-and-Farming-Vision/"&gt;ecological methods of pest control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt; This includes imidacloprid, clothianidin, thiamethoxam, nitenpyram, acetamiprid, thiacloprid, dinotefuran, cycloxaprid, imidaclothiz, paichongding, sulfoxaflor, guadipyr and flupyradifurone, according to &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-017-0394-3"&gt;Gioro et al&lt;/a&gt;, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/plant/docs/sc_phyto_20171212_pppl_agenda.pdf</value><value>http://www.chemtrust.org/wp-content/uploads/chemtrust-toxicsoup-mar-18.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-26 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Dead%20bees%20in%20Austria.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>EU must not waste second shot to come good on climate change, Greenpeace</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-climate-change-second-shot/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - Heads of government meeting in Brussels have asked the European Commission to review the European Union’s efforts on climate change in view of pledges made under the 2015 Paris climate agreement.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Drought%20in%20Spain%20Ebro.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Drought%20in%20Spain%20Ebro.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The request comes as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iea.org/geco/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;new research&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; by the International Energy Agency showed an increase in EU carbon emissions for the second year in a row in 2017, and as the growth of renewable energy in Europe has &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://windeurope.org/wp-content/uploads/files/about-wind/statistics/WindEurope-Annual-Statistics-2017.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;slowed significantly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Reacting to the news, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU climate and energy policy adviser Tara Connolly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Governments are effectively admitting that Europe’s climate change policy needs a reality check. This is good news, but real change needs more than just words. To be a climate leader, Europe must act fast, ditch fossil fuels and fully embrace renewables and energy efficiency.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The EU’s current target to cut carbon emissions by at least 40 per cent by 2030 (compared to 1990 levels) is based on efforts to limit global warming to 2°C. But scientists and environmentalists have warned that the EU target falls short. The Paris Agreement commits the EU to determine its emissions target based on a more ambitious objective to limit global temperature increase to 1.5°C.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The leaders have given the Commission a year to draft a plan on how EU countries can meet their obligations under the global climate deal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The statement released in Brussels on Thursday evening reads: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“The European Council invites the Commission to present by the first quarter of 2019 a proposal for a Strategy for long-term EU greenhouse gas emissions reduction in accordance with the Paris Agreement, taking into account the national plans.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press release is also available on: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://windeurope.org/wp-content/uploads/files/about-wind/statistics/WindEurope-Annual-Statistics-2017.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-22 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Drought%20in%20Spain%20Ebro.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Tighten rules on subsidies for coal, says European Parliament draft plan</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/tighten-rules-subsidies-coal/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Rules governing subsidies for coal power plants should be tightened, according to a draft plan published today by MEP Krišjānis Kariņš. Kariņš said that so-called ‘capacity mechanisms’, whereby governments pay old coal and nuclear plants to stay on standby, are subsidies which “make little to no sense when there is overcapacity in the EU”.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20kills_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20kills_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;In his plan, he further tightens the requirements that member states must fulfil prior to giving taxpayers’ money to coal and nuclear energy. Kariņš’s plan kicks off discussions in the European Parliament’s industry and energy committee on the EU’s reform of the electricity market. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate &amp;amp; energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;, said: &lt;em&gt;“Mr Kariņš rightly recognises that it makes absolutely no sense to subsidise old, polluting power stations. In fact, the Parliament should rule out any use of fossil fuel subsidies. However, Kariņš proposal to remove priority dispatch and access for renewables is beyond nonsensical. To meet its climate change commitments, the EU must run on 100 per cent renewable energy before mid-century. Only if the EU prioritises renewable energy can it achieve this.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Kariņš’s proposal fails to restore ‘priority dispatch’ and ‘priority access’, rules that ensure that electricity grid operators draw power from renewables first, reducing the use of fossil fuels. Removing these rules would mean that, in times of overproduction, wind turbines could be switched off while fossil fuel plants stay online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;The draft position will be presented to the industry and energy committee on 10/11 July. On 10/11 October, MEPs on the committee will discuss and amend the position. The committee is expected to vote on 27 or 28 November, before the Parliament finalises its position in a plenary vote in the first half of 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, climate &amp;amp; energy policy adviser with Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+32 (0) 22 74 1905,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastian.mang@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-21 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>FossilFuels</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Coal%20kills_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Investigation: Majority of EU Parliament agriculture committee linked to industry</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/investigation-majority-agriculture-committee-linked-industry/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Involve other committees in EU agriculture policy reform or risk health and environment, Greenpeace&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	A majority of MEPs on the European Parliament’s agriculture committee have strong links to the farming industry, Greenpeace research has revealed.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/out-of-balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee/"&gt;*Read the full study here*&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace warned that public health and the environment could be at risk if the European Parliament gives the agriculture committee an exclusive lead role in the reform of the EU’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP). Greenpeace is calling for the meaningful involvement of MEPs with a wider range of expertise.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Researchers found that 25 of the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;46&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; MEPs on the agriculture committee are farmers, former farmers, shareholders in agricultural businesses, have represented the farming lobby or otherwise have strong ties to the farming industry. A further four MEPs on the committee have looser links to the farming industry, such as close family members who are farmers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director Marco Contiero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“There is no question that farming expertise has a vital role to play in the reform of EU agriculture rules, but farming affects a lot more than the farming industry and this should be reflected in the policy process. The European Parliament should give policy-makers with expertise on public health and the environment a real say on the future of agriculture in the EU.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The next CAP, which will cover the years 2021-2027, will be negotiated between national governments and the European Parliament. The European Parliament has not decided yet whether the agriculture committee will again play a solo leading role in determining the Parliament’s position on CAP, or whether the environment, health and food safety committee will have joint responsibility. The Parliament is expected to reach a final decision on this shortly after the European Commission publishes its policy proposal for the new CAP, which is scheduled for 1 June.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/out-of-balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee/"&gt;*Read the full study here*&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 477 777034, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt; www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/pig%20in%20farm.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>European Parliament votes to increase renewable energy target</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-parliament-votes-renewable-energy/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Bad bioenergy still counts towards renewable target&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Strasbourg – Today the European Parliament voted to increase the EU’s 2030 renewable energy target to 35 per cent.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/nice%20one.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/nice%20one.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content hidden-paragraph"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;17 January 2018&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNF-FYBfB36Lli2nRqVwKleM0P--iQ"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Projections&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; show that the current target of 27 per cent, supported by the European Council and Commission, is too low to meet the EU’s commitments under the Paris climate agreement to limit global temperature increase to 1.5 degrees.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament also strengthened rules supporting people producing renewable energy at home or through joining a cooperative. This includes rules that would make self-consumed electricity free from punitive charges, levies and taxes. This would make &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.renewableenergyworld.com/articles/2015/10/spain-approves-sun-tax-discriminates-against-solar-pv.html" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.renewableenergyworld.com/articles/2015/10/spain-approves-sun-tax-discriminates-against-solar-pv.html&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEcuhpGIPBQOaM3hiRYkq43SOzrlQ"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Spain’s controversial ‘sun tax’&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; illegal under EU rules. The ‘sun tax’ forces Spanish solar panel owners to pay for the electricity they produce and consume themselves.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Sebastian Mang&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Parliament has rightly recognised that the EU must boost renewables to meet its climate commitments, but should have kept the focus on real solutions, not bad bioenergy. Unlike governments across Europe that are blocking communities from phasing out dangerous coal and nuclear in favour of renewables, the Parliament strongly backs citizens’ rights to harvest and sell their own energy from sun and wind.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNFuYocmUuWaOpb0i7rHeOo3u5vdCA"&gt;&lt;span&gt;A 2016 report by CE Delft&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; shows that, with the right support, half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity from renewables by 2050, meeting nearly half of the EU’s electricity demand. Power companies would provide the remainder of Europe’s renewable electricity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Parliament backed the continued use of bad bioenergy in the EU. Their proposal would, for example, allow member states to burn whole trees to meet their renewable energy targets, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/dec/14/eu-must-not-burn-the-worlds-forests-for-renewable-energy" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/dec/14/eu-must-not-burn-the-worlds-forests-for-renewable-energy&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNG5j7OxmdDM0G8WLJX-lUgOabEv7w"&gt;&lt;span&gt;which scientists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;agree&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; will increase emissions for decades and significantly contribute to forest degradation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Energy ministers, who reached their &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Energy-ministers-coal-Christmas/" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Energy-ministers-coal-Christmas/&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGE5l1bWpFAXQyhG45DcfrxQExGwQ"&gt;&lt;span&gt;preliminary agreement on the full energy reform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; package on 18 December, backed controversial subsidies for coal, nuclear and gas and weakened proposals to empower households, cooperatives and municipalities to produce and sell their own renewable energy. Three-way negotiations between the Council, Parliament and Commission will begin in the coming months.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ENDS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts in Strasbourg:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian Mang, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%20479%2060%2012%2089" target="_blank"&gt;+32 479 60 1289&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sebastian.mang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;@&lt;a href="http://greenpeace.org/" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://greenpeace.org&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEr5Ib0kEGKD9T6zeXvquGaLP16ww"&gt;greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Hyland, Greenpeace EU press officer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &lt;a href="tel:+32%20471%2075%2089%2085" target="_blank"&gt;+32 471 75 89 85&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For media interviews in Brussels, please contact&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly, Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;a href="tel:+32%20477%2079%2004%2016" target="_blank"&gt;+32 477 79 0416&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;tara.connolly@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?hl=en-GB&amp;amp;q=http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&amp;amp;source=gmail&amp;amp;ust=1516280625660000&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGgyt6OVIDB-8HVlsejPB1U3TFUQw"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://newclimateinstitute.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/cobenefits-of-indcs-october-2015.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-01-17 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/nice%20one.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace investigation: EU imports of Amazon timber tainted by widespread fraud in Brazil</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/investigation-EU-imports-Amazon-timber-fraud-Brazil/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels/Manaus, Brazil– A Greenpeace investigation has exposed widespread fraud in the Brazilian forestry sector, which may have allowed massive quantities of illegal timber to reach the EU. Under the EU timber regulation, importers are obliged to take action to prevent illegal timber from entering the supply chain [1].
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180320%20Greenpeace%20Amazon%20Para%20investigation.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180320%20Greenpeace%20Amazon%20Para%20investigation.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Greenpeace investigates in Pará state, Brazil
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this wood comes from Pará state in the Brazilian Amazon, which is one of the largest producers and exporters of tropical timber in Brazil, and where experts estimate that more than three-quarters of all logging is illegal [2]. The investigation by Greenpeace Brazil, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/international/publication/15432/imaginary-trees-real-destruction/"&gt;Imaginary trees, real destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, reveals a system that allows the laundering of illegally harvested timber with legal paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU forest policy director &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Risso &lt;/strong&gt;said:&lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Logging in the Brazilian Amazon is out of control. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s practically impossible to guarantee that timber from the region comes from legal operations. National authorities in the EU should review the evidence and take urgent action to stop the sale of timber that does not meet the standards required by EU law. The European Commission should see that enforcement at national level is swift and effective”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loggers particularly target ipe trees, whose high value [3] makes it profitable to penetrate deep into the Amazon rainforest, causing major environmental damage and an intensification of violence against local communities [4].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Greenpeace investigation exposes fraudulent forest inventories. Inventories are required in the Brazilian licensing process for forest management plans. The documents frequently overestimate the volumes of valuable trees, misidentify undesirable trees as commercially valuable species, or simply list non-occurring specimens [5]. Once forest management plans are approved, state agencies issue credits for the harvesting of this non-existent timber. These credits can then be used to cook the books of sawmills that process illegally logged trees from forests on indigenous lands, protected areas or public lands. Once laundered in this manner, illegal timber becomes indistinguishable from timber that has been harvested legally [6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation found that 11 EU countries imported 9,775m³ of ipe timber from forest management plans with indications of fraud between March 2016 and September 2017. France imported the largest amount (3,002m³), followed by Portugal (1,862m³), Belgium (1,754m³) and the Netherlands (1,549m³).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite several earlier Greenpeace investigations exposing deficiencies in Brazil’s control system and the inadequacy of official documentation as a guarantee of the legal origin of Brazilian Amazon timber, [6]  many operators in Europe continue to import ipe wood from the region. It is unclear what kind of measures they are taking to mitigate the risks of illegality inherent in the timber. Companies in Europe should stop buying timber from the Brazilian Amazon unless they can provide credible independent evidence that the timber is legal, beyond the simple presentation of official documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] The EU timber regulation bans illegal timber in the EU. It obliges companies to conduct due diligence to ensure there is no more than a negligible risk that timber has been illegally harvested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Imazon (2013), Forest Management Transparency Report - State of Pará (2011 to 2012): &lt;a href="http://imazon.org.br/publicacoes/forest-management-transparency-report-state-of-para-2011-to-2012/?lang=en"&gt;http://imazon.org.br/publicacoes/forest-management-transparency-report-state-of-para-2011-to-2012/?lang=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Once processed into flooring or decking, ipe timber can fetch up to €2,000 per cubic meter at export ports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Greenpeace Brazil’s report, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org.br/hubfs/Greenpeace_BloodStainedTimber_2017.pdf"&gt;Blood-stained timber: rural violence and the theft of Amazon timber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, shows how illegal logging in the Amazon is one of the main engines of violence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] The investigation is based on an analysis of 586 logging authorisations (derived from forest management plans) issued by the Department of the Environment of Pará state between 2013 and 2017, and field research conducted in the southwest of the state. The density of ipe trees was compared to scientific papers and to forestry inventories used in concessions in Pará state. The investigation showed that 77 per cent of those inventories registered volumes of ipe trees above the levels identified by recent research. In some cases, this ‘super filling’ of trees led to inventories with ten times more trees than what science says is likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] See visual on page 6 of the Greenpeace investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[7] See Greenpeace Brazil reports: &lt;em&gt;The Amazon’s Silent Crisis&lt;/em&gt; (May 2014), &lt;em&gt;The Amazon’s Silent Crisis: Night Terrors&lt;/em&gt; (October 2014), &lt;em&gt;The Amazon’s Silent Crisis: Licence to Launder&lt;/em&gt; (June 2015) and &lt;em&gt;The Amazon’s Silent Crisis: Partners in Crime&lt;/em&gt; (November 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Risso – Greenpeace EU forest policy director:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)496 127009, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.greenpeace.org.br/hubfs/Greenpeace_BloodStainedTimber_2017.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-20 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180320%20Greenpeace%20Amazon%20Para%20investigation.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Health</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Environment and health concerns ignored by EU agriculture ministers</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/environment-health-ignored-agriculture-ministers/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	A statement by European agriculture ministers on the EU’s common agricultural policy (CAP) ignores the impacts on public health and the environment, according to Greenpeace. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/vegetable%20basket_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/vegetable%20basket_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The text comes ahead of the EU Commission’s proposed CAP reform, due in May. Agriculture ministers failed to address the environmental and health impacts of Europe’s farming system, and in particular of its intensive meat and dairy sector.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marco Contiero, agriculture policy director at Greenpeace EU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;, said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Animal farming contributes as much as 17 per cent of the EU’s greenhouse gas emissions, and is a major source of water, soil and air pollution. The upcoming reform of EU farming rules is as important for citizens’ health, Europe’s climate action and nature protection, as it is for farmers. Our food and farming system needs a cure, not a sticking plaster, and yet today’s meeting of agriculture ministers looked little more than that.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environment and health impact of meat and dairy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Animal farming in Europe contributes &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23504717"&gt;12-17 per cent&lt;/a&gt; of the EU’s greenhouse gas emissions. It is also a major source of water, soil and air pollution, in particular from nitrogen and phosphorus in water, and ammonia and fine particulate matter in the air. Nitrogen pollution alone costs the EU up to &lt;a href="http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf"&gt;€320 billion every year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Food Safety Authority and the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control described antibiotic resistance as “one of the biggest threats to public health”, echoing statements by the World Health Organization. &lt;a href="https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/180227"&gt;A joint report by the two agencies&lt;/a&gt; confirmed the presence of bacteria in farmed animals that have developed resistance to crucial antibiotics used to treat people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is calling for a &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/livestock_vision"&gt;50 per cent reduction in global meat and dairy production&lt;/a&gt; by 2050, to protect the climate, environment and public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 3 May, the European Commission will publish its proposal for the EU budget, the so-called multiannual financial framework. The common agricultural policy makes up almost 40 per cent of the budget. On 29 May, it will table its proposal for the reform of the CAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament’s agriculture committee is set to vote on an non-binding opinion on the CAP on 17 May. Once the Commission has published its CAP proposals, the Parliament will decide which committees will debate and amend the proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marco Contiero – Greenpeace EU agriculture policy director: +32 (0)477 777034, &lt;a href="mailto:marco.contiero@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;marco.contiero@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.nine-esf.org/files/ena_doc/ENA_pdfs/ENA_policy%20summary.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-19 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/vegetable%20basket_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Leaked trade papers</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2017/Leaked-trade-papers/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;EU backtracks on transparency and environment pledges&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels/Amsterdam, 23 June 2017 - Greenpeace Netherlands is releasing 205 pages of previously undisclosed chapters from secret talks for an EU-Japan trade agreement (known as JEFTA).
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Leaked_trade_papers_201706.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Leaked_trade_papers_201706.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The papers expose the failure of the European Commission and European governments to stick to their &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/trade/policy/in-focus/new-trade-strategy/"&gt;commitments&lt;/a&gt; on transparency, warned Greenpeace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaked papers, which can be found on &lt;a href="http://www.trade-leaks.org/"&gt;trade-leaks.org&lt;/a&gt;,  expose a lax approach to environmental protection, despite Commission assurances that it would uphold the highest standards in EU trade agreements, said Greenpeace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade policy campaigner Kees Kodde &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“The leaked papers show that the EU and European governments are still doing secret trade deals that trample all over the environment, despite promising that they wouldn’t. After millions of people opposed trade deals with Canada and the US because of their impact on democracy and the environment, the Commission has learnt nothing from its mistakes. To broker trade deals that benefit society and nature, the EU must stand by its values and principles, not sacrifice them for the sake of a handful of multinationals. Trade must not be an end in itself, but a means to achieve social and environmental wellbeing that keeps us within our planetary boundaries. It’s time for a new approach to trade that protects people and planet.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New approaches to trade will be the focus of discussions on the future of EU trade policy with NGOs, policymakers and experts at the &lt;a href="http://www.tradelab.eu/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trade Lab&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an event organised by ten civil society organisations in Brussels on 26 June. Greenpeace has laid out &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf"&gt;ten principles&lt;/a&gt; for a fairer trade policy that upholds social and environmental standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JEFTA papers leaked by Greenpeace Netherlands are mostly dated between late 2016 and early 2017, just ahead of the 18th round of negotiations. Negotiators hope to wrap up the new deal over the coming weeks. If it is concluded, the agreement with Japan could be the EU’s biggest ever trade deal, covering a trade volume twice as large as the trade agreement with Canada (known as CETA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on the leaked papers, please consult the &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Greenpeace-media-briefing-JEFTA_20170623.pdf"&gt;media briefing&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Greenpeace-QA-JEFTA_20170623.pdf"&gt;Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kees Kodde&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace trade policy campaigner&lt;/strong&gt;: +31 (0)6 53623818, &lt;a href="mailto:kees.kodde@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;kees.kodde@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milo Laureij - Greenpeace communications&lt;/strong&gt;: +31 (0)6 29001159, &lt;a href="mailto:milo.laureij@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;milo.laureij@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This press comment is also available on: &lt;a href="http://www.trade-leaks.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.trade-leaks.org&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Greenpeace-media-briefing-JEFTA_20170623.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Greenpeace-QA-JEFTA_20170623.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-23 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Leaked_trade_papers_201706.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
</items>