<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Tackling illegal logging, deforestation and forest degradation</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Tackling-illegal-logging-deforestation-and-forest-degradation/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;An agenda for EU action&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	This briefing is the contribution of a group of non-governmental
organisations to the policy debate related to the evaluation of the
European Union Forest Law Enforcement, Governance and Trade (FLEGT)
Action Plan, the review of the EU Timber Regulation (EUTR), and the EU’s
commitment to halt deforestation and restore degraded forests by 2020.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Herakles%20project%20Cameroon.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Herakles%20project%20Cameroon.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            The palm oil project managed by Herakles Farms has wiped out a large portion of forest in the South West of Cameroon. The region is home to not only the chimpanzee, but also the forest elephant, rare primates such as the endangered drill and the critically endangered Preuss’s red colobus monkey, plus a number of fish species, many endemic to the region.

        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FLEGT Action Plan was established in 2003 as an innovative first attempt by the EU to curb illegal logging and related trade, promote sustainable forest management, and address some of the underlying causes of deforestation and forest degradation. [...] Nonetheless, illegal logging remains a persistent problem across the world. In some countries, 90% of all logging activities are illegal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/briefingnote_deforestation_designed.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;briefingnote_deforestation_designed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/briefingnote_deforestation_designed.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-03-30 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Herakles%20project%20Cameroon.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Letter to EU presidents on animal farming</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/letter-presidents-animal-farming/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Europe's farming system heavily favours industrial agriculture and intensive meat and dairy farming.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;We wrote to EU Commission President Juncker, EU Council President Tusk and EU Parliament President Tajani – along with our allies working to protect the environment, public health, animal welfare, small farmers and consumers. We asked them to ensure that the upcoming reform of the EU's common agricultural policy shifts our food and farming system to one with less meat and dairy, but better meat and dairy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180326-animal_farming_letter_to_eu_presidents.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180326-animal_farming_letter_to_eu_presidents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180326-animal_farming_letter_to_eu_presidents.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-27 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Paris agreement: statement from the Coalition for higher ambition</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Paris-agreement-statement-from-the-Coalition-for-higher-ambition/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Save%20the%20climate.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Save%20the%20climate.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/CAN%20statement%20from%20the%20Coalition%20for%20Higher%20Ambition%2019042016.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;CAN statement from the Coalition for Higher Ambition 19042016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/CAN%20statement%20from%20the%20Coalition%20for%20Higher%20Ambition%2019042016.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-04-19 00:00:00</date><type>Statement</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Save%20the%20climate.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Make or break for renewable energy in Europe</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/Make-or-break-for-renewable-energy-in-Europe/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Negotiations on EU renewables directive enter final stage&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Greenpeace EU media briefing

On 17 May, negotiators representing European governments, the European Parliament and the European Commission will hold crunch talks on Europe’s renewable energy laws. 

The talks will determine the EU's 2030 renewable energy target, as well as the laws governing renewable energy projects involving power companies, local communities and households. The negotiators are meeting for a third round of talks. A fourth, and potentially last, session will take place on 29 May.

&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRW4M_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRW4M_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A decision to boost renewables could accelerate the transformation of Europe’s energy system, leading to almost &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf"&gt;half of all Europeans&lt;/a&gt; producing their own renewable energy by 2050, and helping the European Union fulfil its obligations under the Paris climate agreement. But most governments are reluctant to take away control of the energy system from a handful of heavily subsidised power companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" cellspacing="3"&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU energy policy adviser Ansgar Kiene &lt;/strong&gt;said: &lt;em&gt;“Our governments like to talk about Europe’s leadership on climate change, but they are attacking the rights of ordinary citizens to participate in a transition to renewable energy. All the while, &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;they continue to bankroll coal, gas and nuclear power companies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;. It’s time to turn words into action.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is at stake?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negotiators are debating what Europe’s 2030 renewable energy target should be. The target will set the minimum amount of energy that should be delivered by renewables across Europe by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, EU leaders backed a minimum 27 percent target. However, this does not take into account EU commitments under the Paris climate agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament supports a minimum 35 percent target, while NGOs have called for a minimum &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2012/ER-2012/"&gt;45 percent renewables target&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other measures under consideration, which are backed by the European Parliament, would enable Europeans to take a more active role in a renewable energy transition by, for example, encouraging the use of smart meters and solar panels. For the first time, the EU could recognise the right for citizens to produce, store and sell renewable electricity, free from red tape and punitive charges, including taxes on the renewable energy that people produce and consume themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite some support from countries like &lt;strong&gt;Greece&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Belgium&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Ireland&lt;/strong&gt;, EU governments, led by &lt;strong&gt;Germany&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spain&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;France&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;UK&lt;/strong&gt;, are strongly opposed to any meaningful measures to encourage households, local communities or small businesses to play a growing role in Europe’s energy system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spain has itself introduced one of the most restrictive regimes on solar power in the world, which has led to a &lt;a href="https://unef.es/wp-content/uploads/dlm_uploads/2017/07/informe-anual-unef-2017_web.pdf"&gt;dramatic reduction in investments in rooftop solar&lt;/a&gt;. The Parliament’s lead rapporteur, José Blanco Lopez, has said it is his priority to put an end to the Spanish ‘sun tax’, and ensure a minimum set of rights for European citizens to play an active role in Europe’s energy transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other controversial issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another controversial issue is electricity sharing or ‘virtual net metering’, which allows people who do not own their own roof to participate in renewable energy projects elsewhere. For example, electricity generated by solar panels on one roof could be credited to the bills of people in other buildings participating in the project. Municipalities can also use this electricity sharing to place solar panels on the most suitable roofs and give the electricity credits to those who need them most. For example, the Greek city of Thessaloniki has installed solar panels on the roof of a high school and gave the electricity credits to a domestic abuse shelter nearby. Belgium and Slovenia are also considering introducing legislation that would allow electricity sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EU negotiators are also discussing rules on bioenergy, including a new renewable target for transport, which risks being filled with unsustainable biofuels made from palm oil and soy. Rules to improve the sourcing and use of wood from forests to produce electricity, including restricting the burning of biomass to highly efficient power plants, are too weak to prevent forest degradation, while doing little to cut carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rooftop revolution potential&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community or citizen energy has an enormous and largely untapped potential. A&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf"&gt;report by CE Delft&lt;/a&gt;, commissioned by Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth, REScoop.eu and EREF in 2016, showed that over 112 million citizens could meet 19 percent of Europe’s electricity demand by 2030. By 2050, over 264 million Europeans – half of all Europeans – could cover as much as 45 percent of Europe’s electricity demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By making the right choices today, the next decade could see households, local cooperatives, cities and small businesses massively investing in renewables to power everything from schools to businesses. Citizen energy can also help tackle energy poverty through so-called ‘social solar’ public projects that provide low-income households with access to cheap, affordable renewable energy, instead of giving them money to heat their homes with fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tara Connolly&lt;/strong&gt; - Greenpeace EU energy policy director: +32 (0)477 790416, &lt;a href="mailto:tara.connolly@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;tara.connolly@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911 &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning network that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value><value>https://unef.es/wp-content/uploads/dlm_uploads/2017/07/informe-anual-unef-2017_web.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-15 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GP0STRW4M_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGO statement on deforestation</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/NGO-statement-deforestation-2017/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Forests are essential for life on earth. Three hundred million people worldwide live in forests and 1.6 billion depend on them for their livelihoods. Forests are the largest stores of carbon after oceans and provide habitat for 80 per cent of the world’s terrestrial biodiversity.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;An EU action plan to stop the destruction of these essential forests is long overdue. A group of NGOs have called on the European Commission to produce such a plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/170620%20-%20A%20case%20for%20EU%20action%20in%202017.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;170620 - A case for EU action in 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/170620%20-%20A%20case%20for%20EU%20action%20in%202017.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-20 00:00:00</date><type>Statement</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/palm%20oil%20crossroads%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>The Europe we want: just, sustainable, democratic and inclusive</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/The-Europe-we-want-Just-Sustainable-Democratic-and-Inclusive/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Common appeal to European leaders by European civil society organisations and trade unions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	As we mark the 60th anniversary of the Treaty of Rome, we have a momentous opportunity to take stock of how far Europe has come – and how far we still have to go in order to offer a sustainable and prosperous future to everyone in Europe. It is an opportunity that we call on you, the leaders of Europe, to seize with both hands. We call on you to show leadership, vision and courage to set Europe on the path to a sustainable future which realises the rights of all people and respects planetary boundaries.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EU_hands_b2.png" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EU_hands_b2.png" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/The%20Europe%20We%20Want%20-%20Just,%20Sustainable,%20Democratic%20and%20Inclusive.pdf"&gt;Read the full statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Green 10, ETUC, CONCORD, European Movement International, European Women’s Lobby and European Youth Forum participated in the drafting of this initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/The%20Europe%20We%20Want%20-%20Just,%20Sustainable,%20Democratic%20and%20Inclusive.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-23 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>EUaffairs</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/EU_hands_b2.png</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>WaterPollution</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Investigation: How CAP promotes pollution</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/investigation-CAP-promotes-pollution/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Subsidies from the European Union’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) are supporting some of Europe’s most polluting livestock farms, a Greenpeace investigation has revealed.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over half (51%) of the farms examined in seven EU countries received CAP payments totalling €104 million in the last year reported, despite being the highest emitters of ammonia in their countries. The research compared CAP direct payments and the EU’s registers of pollution from industrial facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ammonia runoff from fertilizers or manure slurry leads to the rapid growth of algae in rivers, lakes and seas, choking plants and animals of oxygen. Ammonia also causes air pollution from fine particulate matter, which impacts human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180424-investigation-how-CAP-promotes-pollution.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180424-investigation-how-CAP-promotes-pollution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180424-investigation-how-CAP-promotes-pollution.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-24 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/chicken%20industrial%20farming.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Out of Balance - industry links in the European Parliament AGRI committee</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/out-of-balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	For 56 years, European farming has been guided by the European Union’s common agricultural policy (CAP) and the subsidies it distributes to European farmers. The CAP currently accounts for almost 40 percent of the EU’s total budget – €59 billion in 2017.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee-infographic.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee-infographic.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the EU carries out a policy review that will affect the CAP over the next seven years, there is concern that the interests of the agriculture industry could be given precedence over public health and the environment, and to the detriment of many European farmers. Greenpeace has investigated the farming links of members of the European Parliament’s agriculture committee (AGRI), which is a key player in the CAP negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research found that a majority of AGRI committee members, 25 out of 46, have strong links to the agriculture sector, and four more MEPs have looser links. This farming expertise is of course important in the reform of the CAP, but it should not eclipse the input of other experts. Agriculture has a significant impact on the environment, public health, climate change, the economy and other sectors, and yet there is a danger that experts in these fields will be prevented from playing a meaningful role in the reform of the CAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-EU-AGRI-committee.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-EU-AGRI-committee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-EU-AGRI-committee.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-24 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/20180524-Out-of-Balance-industry-links-AGRI-committee-infographic.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Investor protection in CETA</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Investor-protection-in-CETA/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Gold standard or missed opportunity?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Back in 2015, the European Parliament (EP) mandated the Commission to ensure a number of reforms in the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA) between the EU and Canada.  Early in 2016, it was announced that a ‘legal review’ of CETA had been completed.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ICS%20CETA%20Report%20COVER.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ICS%20CETA%20Report%20COVER.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only a limited number of the shortcomings identified by the EP were addressed. Consequently, CETA’s new chapter on investment protection is a missed opportunity to create a legal system that addresses these deficiencies, which have long been identified in the ISDS system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/ICS%20CETA%20Report%20WEB.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;ICS CETA Report WEB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/ICS%20CETA%20Report%20WEB.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-10-01 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/ICS%20CETA%20Report%20COVER.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Civil society calls for a new Europe for people and planet</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Civil-society-calls-for-a-new-Europe-for-people-and-planet/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	177 European and national civil society organisations and trade unions signed this common statement, ahead of the EU27 Summit in Bratislava on 16 September 2016.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/JeSuisPlanetEarth.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/JeSuisPlanetEarth.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Too many people across Europe are dissatisfied and disillusioned with the European Union and feel remote from its institutions and policies. But there are groups of committed politicians, trade unions, community groups and non-governmental organisations across Europe who are ready to take action and work for a renewed Europe. Together, we can shape a Europe that is inclusive, open, just, sustainable, and that works for people of all ages, social backgrounds and nations."[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/CSO%20statement%20-%20final%2012092016.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;CSO statement - final 12092016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/CSO%20statement%20-%20final%2012092016.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-12 00:00:00</date><type>Statement</type><tags1>EUaffairs</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/JeSuisPlanetEarth.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGOs call for a Fitness Check of the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP)</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/NGOs-call-for-EU-to-perform-Fitness-Check-of-CAP/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	    
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="float: left; margin: 5px;" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/agriculture%20for%20CAP.jpg" alt="" width="250" height="166"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;107 NGOs are calling on European Commission President Jean-Claude Juncker to initiate an in-depth review of food production and consumption in Europe by conducting a Fitness Check of the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the full letter below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/NGOs%20letter%20-%20CAP%20Fitness%20Check%20_final_version.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;NGOs letter - CAP Fitness Check _final_version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/NGOs%20letter%20-%20CAP%20Fitness%20Check%20_final_version.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-03-23 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/agriculture%20for%20CAP.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>PeoplePower</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Scenario for a Sustainable Europe for its Citizens</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Scenario-Sustainable-Europe-Citizens/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The Future of Europe is in the spotlight.

History-shaping events over the last 12 months, including the UK's vote to leave the EU, constitutional crises in some member states, the emboldening of far-right political parties, the failure to humanely welcome refugees, and failed austerity economics, along with the instability arising from Donald Trump's election in the US, have brought Europe to a crossroads.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/scenario%206%20%20sustainable%20Europe.JPG" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Small/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/scenario%206%20%20sustainable%20Europe.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April 2017 European Commission President Jean-Claude Juncker presented a White Paper on the Future of Europe, including 5 possible scenarios for discussion at European and Member State levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/white_paper_on_the_future_of_europe_en.pdf"&gt;You can read the European Commission's White Paper on the Future of Europe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, &lt;a href="https://www.sdgwatcheurope.org/"&gt;SDGWatch Europe&lt;/a&gt; has faciliated with around 100 civil society organisations the development of an alternative '6th Scenario'. In this '6th Scenario' these organisations present their aims for a sustainable and fair Europe in which care for people and planet are key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They intend to put this '6th Scenario' forward as an alternative and to demand that it be fully considered in national and European discussions on the future of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Sustainable-Europe-for-Citizens-6th-Scenario_20170620.pdf"&gt;Read the civil society 6th Scenario for a Sustainable Europe for its Citizens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/scenario%206%20%20sustainable%20Europe.JPG</value></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/white_paper_on_the_future_of_europe_en.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Sustainable-Europe-for-Citizens-6th-Scenario_20170620.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-08 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>EUaffairs</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/ReSizes/Small/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/scenario%206%20%20sustainable%20Europe.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGO letter to President Juncker urging a ban on neonicotinoid pesticides</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/NGO-letter-Juncker-neonicotinoids/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Over 50 NGOs wrote to European Commission President Jean-Claude Juncker, urging him to ban neonicotinoid pesticides without delay.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Bees and other pollinators remain under threat in Europe. While pesticides are one of multiple factors to blame, the elimination of these chemicals from the environment is a crucial, achievable and effective first step to protect their health and the crucial role they play in our natural ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180316%20Letter%20Juncker%20Ban%20neonicotinoids.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180316 Letter Juncker Ban neonicotinoids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180316%20Letter%20Juncker%20Ban%20neonicotinoids.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-19 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGO statement on deforestation</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/NGO-statement-on-deforestation/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	All eyes on the European Commission, as crucial EU decision on deforestation due “in a matter of weeks”


&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, the European Commission is set to make a momentous decision about the fate of the world’s forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision rests on whether the EU will develop an Action Plan on deforestation and degradation, as envisaged by the Council and Parliament in 2013 in the context of the &lt;a href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32013D1386"&gt;7th EU Environment Action Programme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref1" href="#_ftn1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to act would mean the EU will be unable to deliver on &lt;a href="http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/sustainable-development-goals/"&gt;its international commitments to halt deforestation by 2020&lt;/a&gt;, to protect our climate and biodiversity, and to guarantee that human rights including the rights of indigenous peoples are respected.&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref2" href="#_ftn2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/1.%20Report%20analysis%20of%20impact.pdf"&gt;Research commissioned&lt;/a&gt; by the EC in 2013 was influential in grasping the extent of the EU’s consumption in &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/deforestation.htm"&gt;driving deforestation&lt;/a&gt; in producer countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/ToR%20-%20Feasibility%20Study%20Deforestation%20final_dec15.pdf"&gt;A feasibility study&lt;/a&gt; on policy options to step up EU action against deforestation&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref5" href="#_ftn5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is due to be made public very shortly by the Commission, along with a decision on the next steps. We expect the feasibility study to conclude that meaningful action is feasible and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forestpeoples.org/sites/default/files/documents/deforestation-4.pdf"&gt;Many NGOs&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref6" href="#_ftn6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.euandgvc.nl/documents/publications/2015/december/7/declarations"&gt;EU Member States&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref7" href="#_ftn7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref8" href="#_ftn8"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have asked the Commission for an Action Plan on deforestation and forest degradation. Members of the European Parliament have &lt;a href="http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P8-TA-2017-0098+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN"&gt;made the same plea&lt;/a&gt;, most recently in a Parliament resolution on palm oil and the deforestation of rainforests.&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref9" href="#_ftn9"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2017, &lt;a href="http://www.palmoilandfood.eu/sites/default/files/17.%20Helene%20Perier%20EPOC%20EU%20Work%20on%20deforestation.pdf"&gt;the Commission stated&lt;/a&gt; it was still reflecting on what action to take.&lt;a title="" name="_ftnref10" href="#_ftn10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 10 January 2018, First Vice President of the Commission, Frans Timmermans, and Vice-President Jyrki Katainen, informed NGOs that &lt;em&gt;“the Commission &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;will be making a decision on a possible EU initiative on deforestation in the coming weeks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;”. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vice Presidents further stated that “&lt;em&gt;as part of the implementation of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and of the Paris agreement, addressing the environmental and social challenges of deforestation and forest degradation is more than ever an important matter for the European Union and in particular for the European Commission&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of the EU showing leadership to end deforestation and forest degradation cannot be overstated. According to the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), 8.8 million hectares of natural forest were lost each year between 2010 and 2015, a total area roughly equivalent to Sweden. Forest destruction is a major environmental problem, accelerating biodiversity loss and climate change, and often associated with human rights violations against indigenous peoples and local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the gravity of the situation, NGOs call on the Commission to commit to developing a formal action plan, including legislative measures, as soon as possible within the course of the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe’s environmental legacy and the future of globally significant forests are both at stake.  All eyes on the Commission!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greenpeace European Unit, WWF EU, FERN, Client Earth, Environmental Investigation Agency, Forest Peoples Programme, Conservation International, Global Witness, Wildlife Conservation Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180207-NGO-statement-on-deforestation.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180207-NGO-statement-on-deforestation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/1.%20Report%20analysis%20of%20impact.pdf</value><value>http://ec.europa.eu/environment/forests/pdf/ToR%20-%20Feasibility%20Study%20Deforestation%20final_dec15.pdf</value><value>https://www.forestpeoples.org/sites/default/files/documents/deforestation-4.pdf</value><value>http://www.palmoilandfood.eu/sites/default/files/17.%20Helene%20Perier%20EPOC%20EU%20Work%20on%20deforestation.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180207-NGO-statement-on-deforestation.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-02-07 00:00:00</date><type>Statement</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Unauthorised GMO field trial exposed as EU takes hands-off approach, Greenpeace</title><url>https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Unauthorised-new-GMO-field-trial-exposed-EU-hands-off/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;EU court set to rule on whether new GMOs fall under existing law&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – Media reports in Belgium have exposed an unauthorised field trial of an experimental genetically modified maize in Flanders, preempting a ruling on the classification of a new brand of genetically modified organisms (GMOs) by the European Court of Justice on Wednesday.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Maize%202.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Maize%202.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The reports were published in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.demorgen.be/wetenschap/geheime-proef-met-dna-gehackte-mais-in-vlaanderen-ik-ben-verbaasd-en-teleurgesteld-b4310c58/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;De Morgen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lalibre.be/actu/sciences-sante/un-champ-de-nouveaux-ogm-plante-en-flandre-en-toute-discretion-polemique-en-vue-5b54be2555326925483cda5a"&gt;&lt;span&gt;La Libre&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Authorities in Belgium took a similar approach to the UK, Finland and Sweden in advising that certain plants created with a genetic engineering technique known as CRISPR do not fall under EU GMO law.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Court of Justice will rule whether or not GMOs produced through so-called gene editing techniques, such as CRISPR, are covered by EU GMO law or fall under an exemption reserved for so-called “mutagenesis” techniques (case &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://curia.europa.eu/juris/liste.jsf?language=en&amp;amp;td=ALL&amp;amp;num=C-528/16"&gt;&lt;span&gt;C-528/16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;). [1]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The European Commission has &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/attachments/18._2015.06.15_lettre_autorites_competentes_redacted.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;warned European governments&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; against authorising the deliberate release of such organisms in the absence of a harmonised EU approach, but has so far failed to issue any guidelines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy adviser Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The European Commission must make it clear that countries cannot unilaterally exempt new GMOs from EU rules. By taking a hands-off approach, the Juncker Commission is allowing potential contamination of the environment and the food chain by these experimental GMOs, undermining farmers, retailers and consumers who want to go GMO free. It has effectively raised hopes in the biotech industry that it is possible to circumvent the law.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ensser.org/publications/ngmt-statement/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Scientists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; have warned that CRISPR can, just like conventional genetic engineering, cause unwanted DNA damage with potentially dangerous side effects. A recent article in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.4192"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Nature&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; also argued that gene-editing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“may have pathogenic consequences”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; in humans. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/New-genetic-engineering-techniques/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;NGOs and farmers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; have called for EU GMO law to be applied to all GMOs, new and old, to ensure risk assessment, traceability and labelling of GMO products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br class="kix-line-break"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;During the last few years, several European governments have claimed that GMOs produced through gene editing techniques are not covered by GMO law.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;In November 2015, the Swedish Board of Agriculture &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.upsc.se/documents/Information_on_interpretation_on_CRISPR_Cas9_mutated_plants_Final.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;advised&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that CRISPR-edited plants were not GMOs, as long as any foreign genetic material was bred out. In May 2016, Finnish authorities gave &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/ppl.12661"&gt;&lt;span&gt;similar advice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. This advice ignored the Commission’s June 2015 warning not release new GMOs into the environment, without safeguards reserved for GMOs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/ALL/?uri=CELEX%3A62016CN0528"&gt;&lt;span&gt;October 2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, it became known that the European Court of Justice would rule on the issue in response to a question by the French Conseil d’État. Nevertheless, Belgium and the UK went ahead with their own interpretation of EU GMO law and told researchers of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.demorgen.be/wetenschap/geheime-proef-met-dna-gehackte-mais-in-vlaanderen-ik-ben-verbaasd-en-teleurgesteld-b4310c58/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Flemish Institute for Biotechnology&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/2018/05/22/exclusive-gene-edited-super-crops-grown-uk-first-time/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Rothamsted Research&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that certain GM plants did not fall under EU GMO law, thereby pre-empting the court decision.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; In January 2018, the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=198532&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=req&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=334667"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Advocate-General&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; advised the EU court that mutagenesis exemptions must &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“not involve the use of recombinant nucleic acid molecules”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, or GMOs that are currently regulated under GMO law. The Belgian plants were bred from genetically modified maize and were engineered with the use of recombinant nucleic acid molecules.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;This press release is also available online at &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.eu/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.greenpeace.eu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://corporateeurope.org/sites/default/files/attachments/18._2015.06.15_lettre_autorites_competentes_redacted.pdf</value><value>https://www.upsc.se/documents/Information_on_interpretation_on_CRISPR_Cas9_mutated_plants_Final.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-07-24 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Maize%202.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>New GMOs cannot escape testing and labelling under EU law, EU court rules</title><url>https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/New-GMOs-cannot-escape-testing-labelling-under-EU-law-EU-court-rules/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels – A new brand of genetically modified organisms (GMOs), derived from so-called gene editing techniques, must comply with risk assessment, traceability and labelling requirements under EU GMO law, the European Court of Justice ruled on Wednesday.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;

&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/OGM%20non.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/OGM%20non.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2018-07/cp180111en.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Court&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; said that any organism obtained with new genetic engineering techniques falls within the scope of GMO law. It argued that the risks linked to the use of these techniques are comparable to those associated with conventional genetic engineering.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The ruling confirms warnings by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://ensser.org/publications/ngmt-statement/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;scientists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; who have argued that gene editing can cause unintended DNA damage with unknown consequences. A recent article in&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.4192"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Nature&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; showed that CRISPR/Cas can cause much greater genetic deletions and more complex genomic rearrangements than experts thought.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU food policy director Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; said: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Court makes it crystal clear that plants and animals derived from gene editing are subject to the same safety and labelling requirements as other GM organisms. These requirements exist to prevent harm and inform consumers about the food they eat. Releasing these new GMOs into the environment without proper safety measures is illegal and irresponsible, particularly given that gene editing can lead to unintended side effects. The European Commission and European governments must now ensure that all new GMOs are fully tested and labelled, and that any field trials are brought under GMO rules.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace calls on the European Commission to ensure that the only gene edited plant that is currently grown in North America, a herbicide-tolerant oilseed rape, cannot be imported or grown in the EU unless it complies with EU GMO requirements [1]. The Commission and European governments must also ensure that GMO law is applied to any GM plants currently in the pipeline [2] and to any field trials [3].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Recent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.testbiotech.org/sites/default/files/Background%20Patents%20%26%20Genome%20Editing.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;research&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; shows that DowDupont and Bayer/Monsanto are behind the largest number of international patent applications for gene editing techniques and plants.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; This herbicide-tolerant oilseed rape, developed by US company Cibus is grown in some parts of the US and Canada. It was developed using a gene editing technique called oligonucleotide-directed mutagenesis (ODM). Cibus lobbied&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://corporateeurope.org/food-and-agriculture/2016/02/us-company-railroads-eu-decision-making-new-gm"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;several EU countries&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; to allow field trials outside of GMO regulations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; The plants in the pipeline include a soybean with a changed composition of fatty acids, developed by Calyxt, and a so-called ‘waxy’ maize, with enhanced starch contents, developed by DowDupont. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[3]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; Sweden, Finland, Belgium and the UK had pre-empted the European Court of Justice ruling by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Unauthorised-new-GMO-field-trial-exposed-EU-hands-off/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;greenlighting field trials&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of gene-edited plants outside the scope of EU GMO law. These field trials are now illegal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Franziska Achterberg&lt;/strong&gt; – Greenpeace EU food policy director&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)498 36 24 03, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;franziska.achterberg@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;: +32 (0)2 274 1911, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2018-07/cp180111en.pdf</value><value>https://www.testbiotech.org/sites/default/files/Background%20Patents%20%26%20Genome%20Editing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-07-25 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/OGM%20non.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Ten principles for trade</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Ten-principles-for-trade/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Globalisation affects all of us. The current global trade and investment regime imposes high social and environmental costs on people and planet. In many cases, governments favour trade over social and environmental standards, including regulation designed to promote and protect the public interest.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP044NG_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP044NG_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; We have put together 10 principles of trade and investment because they should work for people and the planet, and not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title="Read the ten principles for trade" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf"&gt;Read the 10 principles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/201705_Greenpeace_10_Principles_for_Trade.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-31 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/GP044NG_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGOs seize Commission against illegal logging of Białowieża forest, Poland   </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Complaint-to-the-European-Commission-concerning-alleged-breach-of-Union-law/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Seven Polish and international NGOs lodged a complaint with the European Commission as Polish minister breaches EU law and approves logging in Białowieża Forest
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Polish%20forest%20april%202016.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Polish%20forest%20april%202016.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Bialowieza National Park in Poland
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NGOs called on the Commission to investigate an illegal plan to log Poland’s Białowieża Forest, a UNESCO heritage forest. The decision by Polish environment minister Jan Szyszko breached Article 6 of the Habitats Directive. This could result in the Polish government being taken to the European Court of Justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Complaint%20to%20European%20Commission%20-Poland%20forest.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Complaint to European Commission -Poland forest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Complaint%20to%20European%20Commission%20-Poland%20forest.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-04-19 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Polish%20forest%20april%202016.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Request for publication of confidential industry studies on glyphosate</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Joint-NGOs-letter-to-Commissioner-Andriukaitis/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Joint NGOs letter to Commissioner Andriukaitis&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	UPDATED 23 June 2016
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Glyphosate%202%20MB.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Glyphosate%202%20MB.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; Here is the &lt;a title="joint NGOs letter sent in April" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Letter%20to%20Commissioner%20Andriukaitis%2020160411.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;joint NGOs letter sent in April&lt;/a&gt;, and here is &lt;a title="Commissioner Andriukaitis' response" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Andriukaitis%20answer%2022%20june%202016.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Commissioner Andriukaitis' response to NGOs dated 22 June.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Letter%20to%20Commissioner%20Andriukaitis%2020160411.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Andriukaitis%20answer%2022%20june%202016.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-04-11 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Glyphosate%202%20MB.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EUaffairs</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>State of the European Union after Brexit: time for a new direction</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/State-of-the-European-Union-after-Brexit-time-for-a-new-direction/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Letter to EU leaders by environmental organisations.

&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;[...] "In the coming days, weeks and months, a debate will take place on the most important question facing the EU: how do we live up to these values and ensure that the policies, structures and institutions that were created to uphold them can do so effectively in the face of fear, alienation and misinformation?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"As ten of the leading environmental networks active at European level, with a collective membership of over 20 million citizens, of whom a significant number live in the UK, we will certainly need to become better in making the case for the values and benefits EU policies have brought for its citizens’ health and wellbeing. This includes cleaner air, water and beaches, thriving wildlife, safer substances and green energy, to name but a few. These benefits should be communicated loud and clear and all the time, not only in the face of an imminent UK departure from the Union." [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To read the full letter click on the link below&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Green10_EU_PostBrexit.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Green10_EU_PostBrexit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Green10_EU_PostBrexit.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-06-27 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Democracy</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace letter to the European Commission on public procurement infringements for the Paks II nuclear project</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/letter-to-European-Commission-public-procurement-Paks-nuclear/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Please click on the link below to read the full letter.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016094%20Letter%20to%20EC%20on%20Paks%20II%20public%20procurement%20infringements.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;2016094 Letter to EC on Paks II public procurement infringements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016094%20Letter%20to%20EC%20on%20Paks%20II%20public%20procurement%20infringements.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-04 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Nuclear</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>ClimateChange</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Leaked TiSA texts reveal threats to climate </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Leaked-TiSA-texts-reveal-threats-to-climate-/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Greenpeace Netherlands publishes analysis of energy chapter during Geneva negotiations &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Amsterdam/Geneva – Greenpeace Netherlands has released unpublished texts from the TiSA (Trade in Services Agreement) negotiations and conducted an in-depth analysis of the energy chapter, which indicates serious threats to international climate policies.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TiSA%20Geneva.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TiSA%20Geneva.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Widely unnoticed by the public, the TiSA trade deal could be finalised by the end of this year. Negotiated in secret, some of the leaked TiSA documents are subject to a five-year ban on publication after signing of the deal.  &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;You can find more information about the leaked documents &lt;a title="here" href="http://www.tisa-leaks.org/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Check out our analysis of the energy annex:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TiSA_report_EN_sept16_09w.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;TiSA_report_EN_sept16_09w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TiSA_report_EN_sept16_09w.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-20 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/TiSA%20Geneva.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>TTIP leaks analysis</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/TTIP-leaks-analysis/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;TTIP leaks analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/TTIP%20leaks%20analysis.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-02 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Joint NGO letter to Commissioner Andriukaitis on bee-harming pesticides</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/letter-Commissioner-Andriukaitis-pesticides/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	In a letter sent today, Greenpeace, Pesticide Action Network Europe and Bee Life asked EU health Commissioner Andriukaitis to end the EU licences for these four pesticides (imidacloprid, clothianidin, fipronil and thiamethoxam) without delay. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Letter%20to%20Andriukaitis_20161205.pdf"&gt;Read the letter to Andriukaitis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Response%20from%20Andriukaitis_20170113.pdf"&gt;Read the response from Andriukaitis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Letter%20to%20Andriukaitis_20161205.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Response%20from%20Andriukaitis_20170113.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-12-05 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>ECHA response heightens rather than alleviates conflict of interest concerns</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/ECHA-response-heightens-concerns/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Chemicals Agency (ECHA) is due to publish a safety assessment of glyphosate, a controversial weedkiller linked to cancer by the WHO. Twenty health and environmental organisations expressed concerns regarding conflicts of interest and transparency at the agency. The executive director's response fails to address these concerns.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/GlyphosateWarning.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/GlyphosateWarning.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This page was updated on 14 March to include a second letter from ECHA to Greenpeace dated 10 March.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to ECHA's own standards, the chairman and two members of the Risk Assessment Committee appear to breach the agency’s own conflict of interest rules. NGOs also criticise ECHA’s practice of basing assessments on unpublished industry studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The executive director of the European Chemicals Agency, Mr. Geert Dancet, responded to our letter, but concerns remain that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ECHA explains how it manages specific conflicts of interest, but fails to address concerns about conflicts of interest that can affect ECHA’s overall work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing experts to move freely between the private sector and public authorities, even if employment periods do not overlap, is the definition of revolving doors. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conflicts of interest related to industry consultancy cannot simply be declared. They must be ruled out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an expert opinion in relation to regulatory processes can be omitted from the declaration of interests, the requirement to disclose such interests may as well be scrapped. These rules only make sense if they are enforced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependence on unpublished scientific evidence provided by industry calls into question the independence of scientific assessments conducted by European agencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee met on 8 March and will meet again on &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/documents/10162/22932537/rac_40_agenda_en.pdf/81de9087-84fd-aca7-9662-bebef1da1d29"&gt;15 March&lt;/a&gt; to discuss the health and environmental impacts caused by the use of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf"&gt;NGO letter to ECHA&lt;/a&gt; (6 March)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B7M6sIHEjPjtbmdod3AxV18xUUU/view"&gt;ECHA's response&lt;/a&gt; (7 March)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170308_response_to_ECHA_about_conflicts_of_interest.pdf"&gt;Letter expressing Greenpeace's heightened concerns&lt;/a&gt; (8 March)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170310%20ECHA%20reply%20to%20Greenpeace%20on%20conflicts%20of%20interest%20glyphosate.pdf"&gt;Second ECHA letter&lt;/a&gt; (10 March)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170308_response_to_ECHA_about_conflicts_of_interest.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170310%20ECHA%20reply%20to%20Greenpeace%20on%20conflicts%20of%20interest%20glyphosate.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-09 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/GlyphosateWarning.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Greenpeace letter to the European Commission on Hungarian nuclear regulator plan </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/letter-to-European-Commission-Hungarian-nuclear-regulator-plan/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Please click on the link below to read the full letter.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016094%20Letter%20to%20EC%20on%20Hungarian%20nuclear%20regulator%20plan.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;2016094 Letter to EC on Hungarian nuclear regulator plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/2016094%20Letter%20to%20EC%20on%20Hungarian%20nuclear%20regulator%20plan.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-11-21 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Nuclear</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Democracy</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open letter to Commission President Juncker on GMOs and democratic principles</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-to-Commission-President-Juncker-on-GMOs-and-democratic-principles/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	National governments did not support the approval of three genetically modified (GM) maize crops for cultivation in Europe for the second time. The European Commission must now take the final decision. However, it is not obliged to approve them.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Six organisations have sent a letter to President Juncker explaining why the Commission has no moral or legal mandate to approve the GM crops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Commission were to authorise these GMOs, it would impose a decision that goes against the majority of EU member states. This would not only run counter to Juncker's efforts to make the EU more democratic; it would effectively demonstrate contempt for democratic principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170410_President_Juncker_GMO_authorisations.pdf"&gt;Read the full letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170410_President_Juncker_GMO_authorisations.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-04-11 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>NGO letter to EU Parliament pesticide committee</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/ngo-letter-pest-committee/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	We, along with 22 other NGOs, wrote to the European Parliament's newly formed pesticide committee (PEST).
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The glyphosate controversy and the eventual decision to re-approve the chemical for another five years has exposed some fundamental failures of the EU’s pesticide approval system. It revealed the staggering influence of chemical companies on EU scientific assessments and a complete disregard for the concerns of independent scientists, the European Parliament and the general public.
&lt;p&gt;The re-approval glyphosate has seriously damaged trust in the EU and its ability to protect Europeans from harm. We hope that the PEST Committee can rebuild this trust by investigating the failures of the EU pesticides regime and by making practicable recommendations for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180411-letter-PEST-committee.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180411-letter-PEST-committee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180411-letter-PEST-committee.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-13 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/GlyphosateToxicWarning.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Stuck in 1957: EU court rejects challenge to state aid for Hinkley nuclear plant</title><url>https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/Stuck-in-1957-EU-court-rejects-challenge-to-state-aid-for-Hinkley-nuclear-plant/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The EU General Court has rejected a challenge by Austria and Luxembourg to a European Commission decision to allow UK state subsidies for the construction and operation of the Hinkley Point C nuclear plant.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Hinkley_GP0STQ3DY_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Hinkley_GP0STQ3DY_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court accepted that the state aid was justified under the Euratom Treaty. Austria and Luxembourg have the right to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU lawyer Andrea Carta&lt;/strong&gt; said: &lt;em&gt;“The court has missed a golden opportunity to acknowledge that nuclear belongs to the past and should not be brought back with taxpayers' money. If the 1957 Euratom Treaty is the legal basis to squander public resources on nuclear plants, then it must be changed to reflect today's reality: renewables are cheaper, safer and can replace nuclear.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling is at odds with EU measures agreed last month to &lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/News/2018/EU-overturns-barriers-to-rooftop-revolution-but-renewable-target-falls-short-of-serious-climate-action/"&gt;encourage citizens&lt;/a&gt; and communities to generate, consume and sell their own renewable power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK government has guaranteed a rate of £92.50 (€104.6) per megawatt hour (MWh) – the so-called ‘strike price’ – for electricity produced at Hinkley Point C. The strike price is over twice as high as current UK wholesale electricity prices. Electricity bill-payers will pay the difference between the wholesale electricity price and the £92.50 "strike price", if the wholesale electricity price falls below the guaranteed strike price. This will &lt;a href="https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201719/cmselect/cmpubacc/393/39306.htm"&gt;cost UK consumers around £30 billion&lt;/a&gt; (€33.9 billion) over the 35-year contract, according to the UK Department for Business, Energy &amp;amp; Industrial Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state aid scheme will benefit NNGB, the company that is building and will operate Hinkley Point C, which is owned by French utility EDF and China General Nuclear Power Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent &lt;a href="https://www.erneuerbareenergien.de/local-added-value-from-a-community-wind-farm/150/437/96249/"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;, cooperative-owned projects bring eight times more revenue into the local economy than a project by a major power company. As well, a &lt;a href="http://www.cedelft.eu/publicatie/the_potential_of_energy_citizens_in_the_european_union/1845"&gt;2016 report by CE Delft&lt;/a&gt; showed that, with the right support, half of all EU citizens could produce their own electricity from renewables by 2050, meeting nearly half of the EU’s electricity demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrea Carta, Lawyer, Greenpeace EU: &lt;/strong&gt;+32 2 2741920, &lt;a href="mailto:andrea.carta@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;andrea.carta@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greenpeace EU press desk:&lt;/strong&gt; +32 2 274 1911, &lt;a href="mailto:pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;pressdesk.eu@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU"&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-07-12 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Nuclear</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2018/Hinkley_GP0STQ3DY_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EUaffairs</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open letter to Juncker and Timmermans requesting active intervention in support of civil society and democracy in Europe</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-to-Juncker-and-Timmermans-requesting-active-intervention-in-support-of-civil-society-and-democracy-in-Europe/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Leading civil society organisations in Europe have written to Commission President Juncker and Vice-President Timmermans to request your active intervention in In view of the situation in Hungary. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/201704_Hungary_demo.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/201704_Hungary_demo.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; The Hungarian government’s recent moves to stigmatise civil society organisations and by the possible forced closure of the Central European University. These developments will have severe negative implications for Hungarian society, social and human rights and the environment. They are unprecedented in the EU and constitute a serious blow to European&lt;br&gt;values, including freedom of academic exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the values of the European Union, the seven organisations urge the Commission to ensure that all Members States defend the role of civil society in promoting open and accountable societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170411_letter%20to%20COM%20on%20situation%20inHungary_FINAL%20with%20logos.pdf"&gt;Read the full letter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170411_letter%20to%20COM%20on%20situation%20inHungary_FINAL%20with%20logos.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-04-11 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Democracy</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/201704_Hungary_demo.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Letter to EU Commissioners on the future of CAP</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2018/letter-commissioners-future-CAP/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Environmental NGOs, farmers, food movements and animal welfare groups wrote to EU Commission First Vice-President Timmermans, and Commissioners Günther Oettinger, Jyrki Katainen, Karmenu Vella and Phil Hogan to voice concerns about the reform of the EU's common agricultural policy. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Vague, contradictory, non-quantifiable and at worst unfounded and outdated EU objectives risk adding a new layer of complexity, market distortions, inefficiency and ineffectiveness to the CAP.&lt;br&gt;Such a state of affairs would not justify such a large proportion of the EU budget being spent&lt;br&gt;on the policy, and risks undermining the legitimacy of EU spending in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180320-ngo_letter_timmermans_cap_objectives.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20180320-ngo_letter_timmermans_cap_objectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2018/20180320-ngo_letter_timmermans_cap_objectives.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-03-20 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Farming</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission fails to regulate new GMOs after intense US lobbying</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Commission-fails-to-regulate-new-GMOs-after-intense-US-lobbying/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Commission has shelved a legal opinion confirming that genetically modified organisms (GMOs) produced through gene-editing and other new techniques fall under EU GMO law, following pressure from the US government. A series of internal Commission documents obtained under freedom of information rules reveal intense lobbying by US representatives for the EU to disregard its GMO rules, which require safety testing and labelling.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GM%20maize%20gloves.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GM%20maize%20gloves.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The documents show that US pressure is focussed on potential barriers to trade from the application of EU GMO law. They suggest that the EU should ignore health and environmental safeguards on GMOs to pave the way for a transatlantic trade agreement. The next round of TTIP negotiations starts on 25 April 2016 in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/20160421%20BR%20US%20lobbying%20on%20new%20GMOs%20FINAL.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20160421 BR US lobbying on new GMOs FINAL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/20160421%20BR%20US%20lobbying%20on%20new%20GMOs%20FINAL.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-04-21 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/GM%20maize%20gloves.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Transparency</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open letter on the independence and transparency of ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-on-the-independence-and-transparency-of-ECHAs-Risk-Assessment-Committee/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	20 health and environmental organisations wrote to the Executive Director of the European Chemicals Agency, Mr. Geert Dancet, to express concerns regarding conflicts of interest and transparency at the agency.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This page was updated on 14 March to include a second letter from ECHA to Greenpeace dated 10 March.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to ECHA's own standards, the chairman and two members of the Risk Assessment Agency appear to breach the agency’s own conflict of interest rules. The organisations also criticise ECHA’s practice of basing assessments on unpublished industry studies. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;ECHA’s Risk Assessment Committee is &lt;a href="https://echa.europa.eu/documents/10162/22932537/rac_40_agenda_en.pdf/81de9087-84fd-aca7-9662-bebef1da1d29"&gt;meeting on 8 and 15&lt;/a&gt; March to discuss the health and environmental impacts caused by the use of glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf"&gt;NGO letter to ECHA&lt;/a&gt; (March 6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B7M6sIHEjPjtbmdod3AxV18xUUU/view"&gt;ECHA's response&lt;/a&gt; (March 7)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170308_response_to_ECHA_about_conflicts_of_interest.pdf"&gt;Letter expressing Greenpeace's heightened concerns&lt;/a&gt; (March 8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170310%20ECHA%20reply%20to%20Greenpeace%20on%20conflicts%20of%20interest%20glyphosate.pdf"&gt;Second ECHA letter&lt;/a&gt; (10 March)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170306_Open_Letter_ECHA_CoI_Concerns.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170308_response_to_ECHA_about_conflicts_of_interest.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170310%20ECHA%20reply%20to%20Greenpeace%20on%20conflicts%20of%20interest%20glyphosate.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-07 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Farming</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Study: dangers of neonicotinoid use in greenhouses</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/study-neonicotinoids-bees-greenhouses/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Will the use of neonicotinoids in greenhouses continue to present a risk for bees and other organisms?
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/bumble%20bee%20on%20flower_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/bumble%20bee%20on%20flower_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;The European Commission has proposed a ban on three neonicotinoids – imidacloprid,&lt;br&gt;clothianidin and thiamethoxam (referred to as neonicotinoids hereafter) – on all crops with the exception of crops grown in permanent greenhouses, “where the crop stays its entire life cycle within the greenhouse and is thus not replanted outside”.
&lt;p&gt;According to the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), the definition of ‘uses in permanent greenhouses’ is as follows: crops/plants grown in a permanent walk-in, static, closed place for crop production with a non-permeable translucent outer shell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EFSA concluded that foliar uses of these three neonicotinoid substances in greenhouses constituted a “low risk to honeybees, bumble bees and solitary bees” for all exposure routes with the exception of exposure of honeybees from residues in surface water which EFSA could not assess, due to a lack of information. EFSA considered that no risk assessment was required for uses as seed treatment and granules in greenhouses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this review is to bring together literature on the uses of neonicotinoids in greenhouses throughout the European Union and assess current knowledge on the potential exposure of bees and other organisms. There is already an existing body of literature that describes the impacts of exposure to neonicotinoids for bees, honeybees and many other organisms. The purpose of this report is to focus specifically on the use of neonicotinoids in greenhouses and is not intended to replicate, or review, literature on specific evidence on impacts of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171211-Neonicotinoids-greenhouses-risk-bees-study.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20171211-Neonicotinoids-greenhouses-risk-bees-study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171211-Neonicotinoids-greenhouses-risk-bees-study.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-12-11 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/bumble%20bee%20on%20flower_Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>New techniques of genetic engineering</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/New-techniques-of-genetic-engineering/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Why EU GMO law must be fully applied to the so-called ‘New Plant Breeding Techniques’&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	The European Commission is considering whether genetically modified organisms (GMOs) that have been produced through a range of new techniques should be excluded from the European Union’s GMO regulations. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Biotechnology companies want to apply these techniques to engineer plants and animals&lt;br&gt;for use in industrial food, biomass and biofuel production. They argue that these new methods to directly modify the genetic make-up of living organisms fall outside the scope of EU GMO regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would mean that there is no risk assessment, labelling and monitoring of GM organisms produced by the new techniques and their derived products. The Commission has announced that it will present a legal analysis on the matter by the end of March 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Joint%20position_New%20techniques%20of%20genetic%20engineering_March%202016-1.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Joint position_New techniques of genetic engineering_March 2016-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/Joint%20position_New%20techniques%20of%20genetic%20engineering_March%202016-1.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-03-16 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>From ISDS to ICS: a leopard can’t change its spots</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/From-ISDS-to-ICS-a-leopard-cant-change-its-spots/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Position paper on the Commission proposal for an investment court system in TTIP&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	This position paper illustrates Greenpeace’s position on the Commission proposal for an Investment Court System (ICS). The Commission presented the proposal at the end of 2015, after its initial approach to Investor-to-State Dispute Settlement (ISDS) mechanisms received vehement criticisms by the public, NGOs, SMEs, media
and political parties in the European Parliament.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="float: left; margin: 5px;" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/leopard_spots.jpg" alt="" width="240" height="160"&gt;The public debate on ISDS and the results of a public consultation on the inclusion of the mechanism in the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP) forced the EU Commission to suspend for two years (from January 2014 to February 2016) the negotiations on the TTIP investment chapter and to rethink its approach to investment protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst containing some improvements, the new proposal substantially fails to address and mitigate our concerns on the detrimental impact of ISDS mechanisms on the protection of public interests, such as health and the environment, and on the fair and non-discriminatory access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/2016_02_11_Greenpeace%20Position%20Paper%20ICS_Final.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Position Paper: From ISDS to ICS: a leopard can’t change its spots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/2016_02_11_Greenpeace%20Position%20Paper%20ICS_Final.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-02-12 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/leopard_spots.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>New techniques of genetic engineering</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/New-genetic-engineering-techniques/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Why EU GMO law must be fully applied to the so-called ‘New Plant Breeding Techniques’&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Biotechnology companies argue that genetically modified organisms (GMOs) that have been produced through a range of new techniques should be excluded from the European Union’s GMO regulations.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;They want to apply these techniques to engineer plants and animals for use in industrial food, biomass and biofuel production. This would mean that there is no risk assessment, labelling and monitoring of GM organisms produced by the new techniques and their derived products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new GMOs present a real risk to the environment and human health. Legal analysis shows that they are covered by EU GMO law. If they were to escape EU regulations, any potential negative effects on food, feed or environmental safety would go unchecked. European consumers, farmers and breeders would have no way to avoid GMOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission and national governments of EU countries should leave no doubt that all products of genetic engineering are subject to EU GMO law which requires rigorous risk assessment, detectability and labelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Joint_position_New_techniques_of_genetic_engineering_Updated_February_2017.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Joint_position_New_techniques_of_genetic_engineering_Updated_February_2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/Joint_position_New_techniques_of_genetic_engineering_Updated_February_2017.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-27 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>GMOs</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>The EU glyphosate timeline</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/The-EU-glyphosate-timeline/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Campaigners and activists met in Brussels and other European cities (Madrid, Rome, Berlin and Paris) today to launch a European Citizens’ Initiative (ECI) to ban glyphosate, reform the EU pesticide approval process, and set mandatory targets to reduce pesticide use in the EU. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The goal is to collect at least one million signatures from Europeans and submit the petition before the Commission’s next move to renew, withdraw or extend the EU licence of glyphosate. To sign the #StopGlyphosate ECI, people can visit &lt;a href="http://www.banglyphosate.eu/"&gt;www.banglyphosate.eu&lt;/a&gt; and follow a simple two-step procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the policy timeline for glyphosate, &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171115_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf"&gt;read the full briefing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20171115_BR_glyphosate_timeline_update.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-02-08 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Pesticides</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>ClimateChange</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Stepping up EU action to protect forests is not optional but the only way forward</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Stepping-up-EU-action-to-protect-forests-is-not-optional-but-the-only-way-forward/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;Greenpeace analysis of the FLEGT evaluation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Illegal logging and related trade remain persistent global problems despite the positive impacts of EU actions undertaken since 2004. A recent independent evaluation assesses the progress of EU action in tackling illegal logging since the launch of the EU action plan on Forest Law Enforcement, Governance and Trade (FLEGT), more than ten years ago. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Oil%20palm%20nursery%20Cameroon.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Oil%20palm%20nursery%20Cameroon.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace welcomes the findings of the evaluators, who urge the EU to continue high level political commitment to FLEGT, to sustain its fight against illegal logging and to undertake more far-reaching actions, in particular to stop deforestation and forest conversion for agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Risso, Greenpeace EU forest policy director&lt;/strong&gt;, said: “&lt;em&gt;Fighting forest crimes &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;requires persistent action, resources and political determination. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Europe must shift gear to end illegal logging and close all entry points for illegal timber to its own internal market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aside from banishing illegal logging, Europe must fulfil its commitment to protect forests and put in place legislation to eliminate deforestation from its supply chains and investments, tackling for instance the massive impact of palm oil and soy production on the world’s forests&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;. There really is no excuse for the continued merciless plundering of forest resources and related dramatic impact on the environment and local communities&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some countries, almost 90 per cent of timber production is estimated to be illegal according to &lt;a href="https://www.chathamhouse.org/sites/files/chathamhouse/field/field_document/20150715IllegalLoggingHoare.pdf"&gt;recent research&lt;/a&gt;. Shiploads of illegal timber routinely reach the international market, and may end up in the hands of European consumers, according to a &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/africa/en/Press-Centre-Hub/Publications/La-Socamba/"&gt;new Greenpeace investigation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, large volumes of agricultural products linked to deforestation are sold on the EU market each day as food, animal feed and cosmetics. Moreover, European banks and financial institutions often finance business operations, like the conversion of forest for palm oil or pulpwood plantations, contributing to forest loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, European leaders committed to halt deforestation and forest degradation by 2020 and to protect and restore forests as a contribution towards limiting global warming to 1.5°Celsius, in the context of the UN sustainable development goals and Paris climate agreement. The EU will only be able to honour these commitments if it secures FLEGT implementation and ensures that the EU’s supply chains and investments are not linked to deforestation and forest degradation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps and FLEGT review take away&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European agriculture ministers are expected to discuss the FLEGT evaluation at the June 2016 agriculture council. The Dutch Council Presidency has already stated that it &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://english.eu2016.nl/documents/publications/2015/12/14/state-of-the-european-union-presidency-edition"&gt;will strive for a more effective, coherent approach that will also strengthen efforts to halt deforestation”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace, together with eight other organisations recently presented its call for action, including recommendations, in a &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/briefingnote_deforestation_designed.pdf"&gt;briefing note&lt;/a&gt;. Many of these are mirrored in the FLEGT evaluation report, which emphasises that the EU must:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensure the effective and uniform enforcement of the EU law banning illegal timber;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;step up international dialogue and diplomacy with other major timber consumer countries, notably China, for them to adopt comparable legislation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;include timber coming from illegal forest conversion within existing FLEGT Voluntary Partnership agreements, and address the issue of conflict timber as this was not adequately dealt with so far;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pursue with more determination the “higher objectives” of sustainable development, notably environmental sustainability, poverty eradication, and human and labour  rights, in the implementation of the FLEGT action plan, including by giving due attention to obligations deriving from international law and agreements;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;combat global deforestation more effectively by taking more far-reaching actions involving all sectors impacting on land use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Greenpeace urges the EU to keep the improvement of forest governance at the forefront of EU action in the coming years. Effective forest governance is essential to ensure the long term sustainability of action to combat illegal logging and deforestation. The EU should urgently address &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;fundamental land-use and governance challenges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;, including corruption, which is preventing progress in FLEGT/VPA action in several partner countries”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;,in line withthe evaluators’ assessment. It should also heed the report’s warning thatsome of the forest governance challenges facing countries affected by illegal logging &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“turn out to be deeply rooted and require sustained action over a long timeframe”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evaluation report replicates a number of generic recommendations, such as simplifying compliance procedures and increasing private sector involvement, which play the tune of the industry, but which risk to undermine the integrity and effectiveness of FLEGT systems, and give corporations undue influence over public policy and issues of forest governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evaluation falls short of adequate recommendations on finance and investment. The report's authors acknowledge that NGO investigations have been the only effective action, other than banks ‘self-regulation’, to address the impact of finance on forests. However, despite noting that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“so far, legally binding constraints on them [banks] have not been included in the EU framework”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;the authors shy away from proposing a concrete regulatory response. Instead, they merely suggest creating a joint platform with actors from private sector and civil society to monitor investments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, legislation to shift investment away from forest damaging activities is urgently needed. Self-regulation and &lt;em&gt;other half-hearted solutions have been ineffective&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacts&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Risso&lt;/strong&gt;, Greenpeace EU forest policy director, &lt;a href="mailto:sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org" target="_blank"&gt;sebastien.risso@greenpeace.org&lt;/a&gt;, T. +32 (0)2 274 19 01. EU transparency register number 9832909575-41.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For breaking news and comment on EU affairs: &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;www.twitter.com/GreenpeaceEU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace is an independent global campaigning organisation that acts to change attitudes and behaviour, to protect and conserve the environment and to promote peace. Greenpeace does not accept donations from governments, the EU, businesses or political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/FLEGT%20report%20analysis%20FINAL%20160527%20-%20GPEU%20site.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;FLEGT report analysis FINAL 160527 - GPEU site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.chathamhouse.org/sites/files/chathamhouse/field/field_document/20150715IllegalLoggingHoare.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/briefingnote_deforestation_designed.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/FLEGT%20report%20analysis%20FINAL%20160527%20-%20GPEU%20site.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-27 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Forests</tags1><categories>NATURE &amp; FOOD</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/Oil%20palm%20nursery%20Cameroon.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Prosumer Rights: Options for an EU legal framework post-2020</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Prosumer-Rights-Options-for-an-EU-legal-framework-post-2020/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Brussels - There are many ways for citizens, small businesses and communities to contribute to the energy transition, actively participating in different aspects of the energy market to become true 'energy citizens'.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Citizens are no longer resigned to the role of passive consumers, but have the potential to be energy producers, or 'prosumers', particularly through self-generation of renewable energy, storage, energy conservation and participation in demand response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this report is to look at different options of EU legal framework for prosumers' rights post-2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/ClientEarth%20Prosumer%20Rights%20-%20options%20for%20a%20legal%20framework%20-%20FINAL%2003062016.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;ClientEarth Prosumer Rights - options for a legal framework - FINAL 03062016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/ClientEarth%20Prosumer%20Rights%20-%20options%20for%20a%20legal%20framework%20-%20FINAL%2003062016.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-05-31 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open letter to Tusk, Juncker and Tajani on EU-China summit</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/Open-letter-presidents-EU-China-summit/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Greenpeace wrote to EU Council president Donald Tusk, European Commission president Jean-Claude Juncker and European Parliament president Antonio Tajani calling on them to use the EU-China summit to lead on action against climate change.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2015/Paris%20COP21.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2015/Paris%20COP21.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The letter urged the three presidents to ensure that the G7 and EU-China summits build on the Paris Agreement to accelerate climate action and pursue a transition to 100 per cent renewable energy, scaling up the global political momentum towards a phase-out of fossil fuels. The letter called on the EU and its partners to publicly oppose all attempts to undermine or call into question the Paris Agreement and instead move the climate agenda forward, with or without the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170426%20letter%20to%20EU%20Presidents%20EU-China%20summit.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20170426 letter to EU Presidents EU-China summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170426%20letter%20to%20EU%20Presidents%20EU-China%20summit.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-05-03 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>ClimateChange</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2015/Paris%20COP21.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Commission risks putting renewable energy transition in the hands of reluctant power companies</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Commission-risks-putting-renewable-energy-transition-in-the-hands-of-reluctant-power-companies/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	On 30 November, the European Commission will release a package of draft legislation to help fulfil EU commitments under the Paris global climate change agreement. Read more here:
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Two of these draft laws – on the development of renewable energy and the redesign of the European electricity market – could in fact endanger the renewable energy transition and constrain the EU’s climate change action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/20161127%20winter%20package%20media%20briefing.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;20161127 winter package media briefing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/20161127%20winter%20package%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-11-28 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>EnergyTransition</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Media briefing: Potential for citizen-produced electricity in the EU</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Media-briefing-Potential-for-citizen-produced-electricity-in-the-EU/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Half of all European Union citizens could be producing their own electricity by 2050, and meeting 45% of the EU’s electricity demand. Our energy market is switching from fossil fuels and nuclear to renewable energy, but it’s also shifting from a centralised market dominated by large utilities to one in which people produce their own energy and help to manage demand.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box middle-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/EU%20breakdown%20of%20energy%20citizens.png" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/EU%20breakdown%20of%20energy%20citizens.png" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without these “energy citizens”, the transition to a 100% renewable energy system won’t be possible. Yet, energy citizens face significant legal obstacles to making their own electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the European Union there are explicit legal restrictions, disproportionate administrative and planning procedures and punitive tariffs that prevent citizens from driving a renewable energy transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the right EU legal framework, energy citizens could flourish and deliver a significant share of Europe’s renewable energy and provide important flexibility to the energy system through demand response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/The-potential-of-energy-citizens-in-the-EU/"&gt;You can read the full report here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full briefing below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;160926 Potential of energy citizens - media briefing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20Potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20-%20media%20briefing.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-26 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Renewables</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2016/EU%20breakdown%20of%20energy%20citizens.png</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Justice</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Open letter to Commissioner Malmstrom on the proposed Multilateral Investment Court</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2017/letter-malmstrom-multilateral-investment-court/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	Open letter to Commissioner Malmstrom, submitted to the public consultation on the proposed Multilateral Investment Court.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame reset-padding"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="hidden"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170315_GP_Open%20letter%20Commissioner%20Malmstrom.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Open letter to Commissioner Malmstrom on Multilateral Investment Court&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2017/20170315_GP_Open%20letter%20Commissioner%20Malmstrom.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-03-15 00:00:00</date><type>Letter</type><tags1>Trade</tags1><categories>DEMOCRACY &amp; EUROPE</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/image/2017/Lady%20justice%20Web_size_with_credit_line.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Renewables</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Report: The potential of energy citizens in the EU</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/The-potential-of-energy-citizens-in-the-EU/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	With an increasing share of renewable energy sources (RES) in the European
Union (EU), the role of energy consumers as active participants in the energy
system is bound to expand, as the developments in an increasing number of
EU Member States demonstrate. A growing number of households, public
organizations and small enterprises are likely to produce energy, supply
demand-side flexibility or store energy in times of oversupply. 
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;So far, however, the extent of this prosumer potential in the EU is unknown. Global and EU-wide decarbonisation scenarios typically model increasing RES capacities, but do not go into the details of how this is achieved, and what role prosumers, also referred to as energy citizens, could play in these developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study therefore aims to create more insight into the potential of energy citizens in the EU: how many energy citizens could there be in 2030 and 2050 throughout the EU and what is their potential contribution to renewable energy production and demand side flexibility?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main result of this project is an Excel workbook that contains the detailed quantitative findings of this study. This report provides the background information to these data, describing the context of the study and the methodology used. The study was commissioned by Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth Europe, European Renewable Energy Federation (EREF) and REScoop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20CE%20Delft%20-%20The%20potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20in%20the%20EU.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;160926 CE Delft - The potential of energy citizens in the EU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/160926%20CE%20Delft%20-%20The%20potential%20of%20energy%20citizens%20in%20the%20EU.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-09-26 00:00:00</date><type>Report</type><tags1>EnergyTransition</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead></lead><title>Hungary: possible state aid to Paks II nuclear plant</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/en/Publications/2016/Paks-nuclear-project-complaint-on-state-aid/</url><text>&lt;h4 class="leader"&gt;
	.
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;Greenpeace's submission on possible state aid to Paks II nuclear power station, February 2016:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/State%20aid%20SA.38454%20(2015C)%20Greenpeace.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;State aid SA.38454 (2015C) Greenpeace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace European Unit</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/eu-unit/Global/eu-unit/reports-briefings/2016/State%20aid%20SA.38454%20(2015C)%20Greenpeace.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2016-02-13 00:00:00</date><type>Briefing</type><tags1>Nuclear</tags1><categories>CLIMATE &amp; ENERGY</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
</items>