<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
<item><date>2009-06-11 00:00:00</date><text>&lt;div class="leader" style="font-weight: bold;margin-bottom: 12px"&gt;
	Greenpeace will soon have a new leader. Kumi Naidoo will take up the role of Executive Director of Greenpeace International in November 2009, when Gerd Leipold steps down after nearly nine years as our activist-in-chief. 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/Global/international/planet-2/image/2009/6/kumi-naidoo.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/ReSizes/Small/Global/international/planet-2/image/2009/6/kumi-naidoo.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Kumi Naidoo
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kumi was part of the successful struggle against apartheid in his native South Africa. He is an activist and a Rhodes Scholar.  For ten years he was the General Secretary of CIVICUS: World Alliance for Citizen Participation. Today he sits on the board of Greenpeace Africa and chairs the Global Campaign for Climate Action (GCCA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was one of the founders of &lt;a href="http://www.whiteband.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Global Call to Action Against Poverty&lt;/a&gt;, which has grown since 2005 into a coalition of anti-poverty campaigners from over 100 countries. They apply public pressure on leaders to fulfil promises on aid, trade, debt, climate change and gender equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kumi brings with him a passion for activism, for non-violence and clear ideas for shaping the future of Greenpeace. His experiences in campaigning, fundraising, advocacy, policy work, networked organisations and leading through change will all be called upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The way Greenpeace works on all levels from confrontation to cooperation with governments and corporations is an inspiration. The mix of pragmatism and passion really gets things done and effects real change in the world. I believe that Greenpeace is one of the most precious assets the global community posses as a critical part in reversing the current fatal trajectory of our planet," says Kumi. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="greyright"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"History teaches us that real change only comes when good men and womenare prepared to put their lives and personal safety on the line toadvance the cause of justice, equity and peace. I believe today thatGreenpeace is the leading organization in embracing that approach."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently Chair of the Global Campaign for Climate Action (GCCA), of which Greenpeace is a member, for the coming months he will focus his attention on generating civil society pressure and cooperation to demand a strong deal at the UN Climate Summit to be held in Copenhagen this December:  one which gets CO2 emissions under control, protects tropical rainforests, and replaces dirty fossil fuel energy with renewables and energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/about/how-is-greenpeace-structured/management/executive-director/"&gt; Gerd Leipold&lt;/a&gt; will remain at the helm until November, and has this to say about the successor he has already worked closely with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Kumi has all of the qualities needed to take Greenpeace forward and lead it in the greatest challenge it and the world has ever faced: climate change."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/about/how-is-greenpeace-structured/governance-structure/"&gt; Greenpeace International&lt;/a&gt; (Stichting Greenpeace Council), is the body that coordinates global Greenpeace policy and strategy, and is based in Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.action-pact.org/"&gt; The best way to welcome Kumi? Take action, of course! Demand world leaders personally attend the Copenhagen summit&lt;/a&gt;, and take personal responsibility for sealing the right deal to save our planet from runaway climate change. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><url>http://p3-raw.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/new-leadership-at-greenpeace-110609/</url><title>New leadership at Greenpeace International</title></item>
<item><date>2009-10-05 00:00:00</date><text>&lt;div class="leader" style="font-weight: bold;margin-bottom: 12px"&gt;
	700 volunteers posed nude in a French vineyard to send a message about climate change. This human art installation in the South of Burgundy was created by artist Spencer Tunick - to warn about the dangers of global warming.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/Global/international/planet-2/image/2009/10/mas-de-700-personas-participar.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/ReSizes/Small/Global/international/planet-2/image/2009/10/mas-de-700-personas-participar.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Naked message: global warming could mean an end to the days of wine... and rosés.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Parental warning: the story below contains nudity)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here's an open letter to world leaders with a naked truth about climate change: their efforts so far have barely made a difference.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Obama, Merkel, Jintao, Lula, Sarkozy, Zapatero, Tusk etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you willhave no doubt witnessed this year - tens of thousands of people are willing togo to some extraordinary lengths for climate action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many are even willing to taketheir clothes off! 700 people havestripped naked in a vineyard to warn the world of the effects climatechange will have on French wine. And a while ago, hundreds of otherswere prepared to &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/naked-glacier-tunick-08182007/"&gt; pose nude on a glacier in Switzerland&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the world, people have made time to march, &lt;a href="http://weblog.greenpeace.org/makingwaves/archives/2009/08/10000_dance_for_a_climate_deal.html"&gt; dance&lt;/a&gt;, create artwork, &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/coal-arctic-svalbard021009/"&gt; chainthemselves overnight to coal installations in Svalbard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="~/link/a2588a5091ff4047b6d4e75fdb5af130.aspx?epslanguage=en-GB"&gt; lock on toequipment in Canada's tar sands&lt;/a&gt;, get arrested for &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/danger-g20-climate230909/"&gt; suspending a messageto the G20 from a bridge in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, spend &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/urgent-action-needed-as-arctic/"&gt; four months at sea awayfrom their families to show again that the Arctic is melting&lt;/a&gt;, document&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QvnqSvvHDGo"&gt; glacial melt at the top of the Himalayas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/countdown-copenhagen-100days280809/"&gt; carved a hundred icestatues in Beijing&lt;/a&gt; to show the threat to Asia's water supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the lengths to which we're all willing to go to call for action on this issue, do you think you could make some time in your busy calendar this December to &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/campaigns/climate-change/take_action/leaders-go-to-copenhagen-climate-summit?0"&gt; show up in Copenhagen&lt;/a&gt;? To date, only Gordon Brown (UK), Donald Tusk (Poland) and Jan Peter Balkenende (the Netherlands) have said they will attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not asking you to take your clothes off in Copenhagen - but &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/campaigns/climate-change/take_action/leaders-go-to-copenhagen-climate-summit?0"&gt; we do expect you to be there - to sign a fair, ambitious and binding deal to save the future of our planet&lt;/a&gt;. A half-decent climate treaty simply wont do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenpeace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- START DYNAMIC CONTENT --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;embed type="application/x-shockwave-flash" id="ss189" width="430" height="400" bgcolor="#ffffff" align="middle" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" quality="high" flashvars="xmlfile=http://www.greenpeace.org/xml/international/photosvideos/slideshows/700-strip-naked-for-climate-me&amp;amp;captionTextSize=10" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/resources/gcms/slideshow/ss189.swf"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;!-- END DYNAMIC CONTENT --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; &lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><url>http://p3-raw.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/strip-naked-4climate051009/</url><title>700 strip naked for climate message</title></item>
<item><date>2003-05-23 00:00:00</date><text>&lt;div class="leader" style="font-weight: bold;margin-bottom: 12px"&gt;
	A container ship currently heading from southern India to the US represents a small victory in the fight against corporate crime across the globe. The ship is carrying 320 tonnes of toxic mercury contaminated waste which comes from a closed plant owned by the Indian subsidiary of consumer products giant Unilever.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/Global/international/planet-2/image/2005/12/unilever-agrees-to-clean-up-it.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/ReSizes/Small/Global/international/planet-2/image/2005/12/unilever-agrees-to-clean-up-it.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            Unilever agrees to clean up its toxic mercury mess in south India.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Unilever mercury thermometer production plant was set up in TamilNadu, India in 1983 after being shipped wholesale from it previous location in New York State in the US. It is a classic tactic of the chemical industry to ship plants that are too dirty or inefficient for the US or Europe to areas such as India and extend their life where environmental and safety standards are lower. Hence the industry can continue to make profits from pollution for many more years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="heading5"&gt;Moving the problem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plant at Kodaikanal imported mercury from the US and re-exported the thermometers back to the US. Mercury is a potent toxin affecting the nervous system of people and animals and a highly dangerous pollutant. Lax safety standards at the plant left workers with mercury poisoning and large amounts of mercury contaminated waste were dumped in the surrounding areas in complete disregard for the local communities by the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local environmental groups and Greenpeace first exposed the mercury dumping scandal in May 2001. Subsequent protests by locals forced the closure of the plant but the contaminated waste was left littering the site and surrounding area. Investigations by the pollution control authorities revealed the pollution to be far worse than the company had admitted with soil contamination 600-800 the legal levels and approximately 17 times more mercury was unaccounted for than the company estimates. The authorities ordered the company to clean up the site and safely treat the waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ananthapadmanabhan, one of our campaigners in India, is studying the clean up: "We will be keeping a close watch on all future remedial actions by the company. Several thousand tonnes of toxic wastes and contaminated soil are still to be properly identified and contained. Now that the clean up has begun in earnest, compensation and health care for affected ex-workers should be immediately brought on to the agenda."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span class="heading5"&gt;A step in the right direction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The waste will be treated at a special plant in the US. The start of the clean up is a big victory for campaigners in India where other polluted hotspots cause by irresponsible companies, like Bhopal, abound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><url>http://p3-raw.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/bon-voyage-mercury-waste/</url><title>Bon Voyage</title></item>
<item><date>2007-12-10 00:00:00</date><text>&lt;div class="leader" style="font-weight: bold;margin-bottom: 12px"&gt;
	Out of 11,000 submissions in our competition to name the humpback whales we were tracking on their migration to the Southern Ocean, we narrowed it down to the final 30. Over 150,000 people then voted for their favourite name. 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mister Splashy Pants is the winner by a nautical mile!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Humpback whales, Southern Ocean." src="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/Global/international/planet-2/image/2005/11/humpback-whales-southern-ocea.jpg" alt="Humpback whales, Southern Ocean." width="600" height="395"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like the world couldn't get enough of Mister Splashy Pants with many websites encouraging their readers to vote for 'Splashy'. And as we all know, once the wonderful world of the internet got hold of Mister Splashy Pants, it was all over bar the final splash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mister Splashy Pants got a huge 119,367 votes (over 78 percent of the vote) with his nearest rival being Humphrey at 4,329 (less than 3 percent). The rest of the top ten were Aiko, Libertad, Mira, Kaimana, Aurora, Shanti, Amal and Manami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many websites also took credit for the rise and rise of the Splashy-Panted One. Some websites encouraged their readers to cheat and vote more than once, while others like &lt;a href="http://treehugger.com/"&gt;Treehugger&lt;/a&gt; seemed to imply that Mister Splashy Pants wasn't a proper name for a whale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're sure Treehugger didn't mean it that way but it resulted in a final wave of votes from their readers that took Splashy to an unreachable position at the top of the pod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To everyone who voted for Mister Splashy Pants, now that you've named him, it's time to save him - he might have a great name but he and his friends are still in danger. The only way to be 100 percent sure that 'Splashy' doesn't get harpooned is to stop killing all whales in the Southern Ocean Whale Sanctuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the people who voted for a name other than Mister Splashy Pants, take heart. The scientists involved in the &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/campaigns/oceans/fit-for-the-future/whaling/great-whale-trail/"&gt; Great Whale Trail&lt;/a&gt; tagged 20 humpback whales in the South Pacific. The top 7 names will be used to name whales with a further 5 whales being named by our Whale Defenders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And last but not least, a big thanks to YOU, the people who made the name-a-whale competition so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><url>http://p3-raw.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/splashy-101207/</url><title>Mister Splashy Pants the whale - you named him, now save him</title></item>
<item><date>2008-05-27 00:00:00</date><text>&lt;div class="leader" style="font-weight: bold;margin-bottom: 12px"&gt;
	We chased it for 5 days, but as dawn broke over the Pacific this morning we finally confronted the biggest tuna fishing vessel in the world. The Spanish-owned and flagged tuna purse seiner "Albatun Tres" is known as a 'super, super seiner' and can net 3,000 tonnes of tuna in a single fishing trip. This is almost double the entire annual catch of some Pacific island countries.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="events-box small-box left"&gt;
    &lt;div class="frame"&gt;
        &lt;a class="open-img EnlargeImage" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/Global/international/planet-2/image/2008/5/the-most-devastatingly-efficie.jpg" title=""&gt;
            &lt;img id="ctl00_cphContentArea_Property3_ctl00_ctl02_Image1" class="Thumbnail" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/ReSizes/Small/Global/international/planet-2/image/2008/5/the-most-devastatingly-efficie.jpg" alt="" style="border-width:0px;"&gt;
            
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="events-content no-title"&gt;
        &lt;span class="date"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            The most devastatingly efficient tuna fishing vessel in the world.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We caught this monstrous tuna catcher deploying its net close to the Phoenix Islands of Kiribati and witnessed many tonnes of tuna being taken out of the Pacific. We laid a 25-metre floating banner reading "No Fish, No Future"' across the inside of the net as it was being hauled in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first found the Albatun Tres on May 22nd and tracked her across more than 1,000 nautical miles. Her crew must have noticed us when we came within visual range as they immediately steamed away at high speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We managed to catch up with them when they stopped to fish, and as they pulled in their catch we showed up in inflatable boats, a jet ski and helicopter in order to expose their plunderous activities to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BA7enHKa5As?rel=0" width="600"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purse seine vessels surround schools of fish with curtain-like nets to catch tuna. A rope along the bottom of the net is pulled like a drawstring and the whole catch is hauled onboard. These vessels have increased their efficiency enormously in the last decade through a variety of technological innovations. While targeting skipjack tuna, these vessels also catch juvenile bigeye and yellowfin tuna, as we witnessed this morning. This bycatch is seriously threatening the already vulnerable stocks of bigeye and yellowfin tuna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foreign fishing nations including those of the European Union (EU) are fishing unsustainably where Pacific island countries depend on tuna for income and food. The Albatun Tres arrived in the Pacific from the Indian Ocean earlier this year. It is owned by the Spanish tuna company Albacora, which is part of OPAGAC, a powerful association of Spanish tuna boat owners, processors and traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No more fish at home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Western and Central Pacific tuna fishery, the world's biggest, has been subjected to intense fishing by fleets from Asia and the United States since the 1960s. With declining tuna stocks in the Atlantic and Indian Ocean, the European Union has gained access to this Pacific fishing ground as a reciprocal benefit for giving aid to Pacific countries. With their own waters fished out, the EU and other foreign fishing fleets including Japan, Korea, Taiwan and the US, are literally sailing across the world to take vital fish and income from people whose lives depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe align="middle" frameborder="0" height="430" scrolling="no" src="http://www.flickr.com/slideShow/index.gne?user_id=16093524@N00&amp;amp;set_id=72157605296853768" width="430"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The super seiners of OPAGAC have a questionable history in the region and some of the vessels which they currently represent were pirate fishing in the area last year. Just when the Pacific fishing fleets need to be reduced we have found evidence to show that OPAGAC is trying to expand their fishing capacity here. This group of companies has no shame and targets the poorest and most vulnerable countries in order to gain access to Pacific waters. Greenpeace is urging Pacific island countries to cease any future dealings with OPAGAC. Vessels of this size need to be taken off the water and scrapped immediately in order to address the overcapacity of the world's tuna fleets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ship Esperanza has been in the region for the last eight weeks highlighting the overfishing of tuna. During this time we have taken action against fishing fleets from Taiwan, Korea, the US, the Philippines and now Spain.  At the same time, our ship Arctic Sunrise has been taking action against overfishing of tuna &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/campaigns/oceans/marine-reserves/the-mediterranean/"&gt; in the Mediterranean&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Take action&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/marine-reserves-now"&gt;Dead oceans? Dead planet. Help us preserve one of the planet's life support systems by setting aside 40 percent of the world's oceans as marine reserves. Our seas need time to recover.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Donate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/donate"&gt;Help keep our ships at sea and our activists in action. We don't accept money from governments or corporations, but rely on millions of people all over the world like you to keep us going.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><url>http://p3-raw.greenpeace.org/international/en/news/features/albatuna-tres-062708/</url><title>World's largest tuna destroyer - caught!</title></item>
</items>