<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<items>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	May 15, 2018 (MONTREAL) - At a press conference this morning, various Quebec personalities, including Normand Baillargeon, Emmanuel Bilodeau, Dominic Champagne, Véronique Côté, Yann Perreault and Éric Pineault, stood alongside representative of the Treaty Alliance Against Tar Sands Expansion and Mohawk Council of Kanesatake Grand Chief Serge 'Otsi’ Simon as well as a coalition of unions and environmental, social and citizen groups to unveil a declaration in opposition to Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline.
</lead><title>PRESS RELEASE: 120 personalities and organizations in Quebec call for an emergency mobilization against the expansion of the Kinder Morgan pipeline   </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2018/PRESS-RELEASE-120-personalities-and-organizations-in-Quebec-call-for-an-emergency-mobilization-against-the-expansion-of-the-Kinder-Morgan-pipeline---/</url><text>&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	May 15, 2018 (MONTREAL) - At a press conference this morning, various Quebec personalities, including Normand Baillargeon, Emmanuel Bilodeau, Dominic Champagne, Véronique Côté, Yann Perreault and Éric Pineault, stood alongside representative of the Treaty Alliance Against Tar Sands Expansion and Mohawk Council of Kanesatake Grand Chief Serge 'Otsi’ Simon as well as a coalition of unions and environmental, social and citizen groups to unveil a declaration in opposition to Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p style="text-align: left;" align="center"&gt;The declaration, entitled “All together against Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline and for a just transition”, has been signed by 120 personalities and organizations in solidarity with the First Nations and communities who oppose the Kinder Morgan project along with the government of British Columbia. The signatories of the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdYQdHozNhZhlU6R1fMez1GcIfqIP1r9bu2PxzBGw27QNZngg/viewform"&gt;declaration&lt;/a&gt; also called for an &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1704127356346194/?notif_t=events_add_page_cohost&amp;amp;notif_id=1526387526812587"&gt;emergency mobilization&lt;/a&gt; on May 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; at 1:30 PM at the Place des Festivals in Montreal in order to demand that Justin Trudeau reject the Kinder Morgan project, refuse to finance it and respect the right of First Nations and of British Columbia to reject this dangerous project. Organizations can continue to sign on to the declaration until May 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;The declaration recalls that "&lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;a signatory of the Paris Agreement, Canada must engage quickly in a just and profound transition that will significantly reduce our dependence on oil, our greenhouse gas emissions (GHG), and will create a greener economy complete with greener jobs. This transition requires resources, planning and leadership that must come from all levels of government.&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/campaigns/Energy/tarsands/Kinder-Morgan-pipeline/"&gt;Trans Mountain Expansion&lt;/a&gt; Kinder Morgan tar sands pipeline project is more at risk than ever with the company halting certain work on the project in April. The opposition by First Nations and the general public, numerous legal battles, the economic precariousness of the project, and the legitimate actions taken by the government of British Columbia to protect the environment have together created too much &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/kinder-morgan-untenable-pipeline-1.4625667"&gt;uncertainty&lt;/a&gt; for the company. It therefore set a deadline of May 31&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, by which time the situation needs to be resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;As for Prime Minister Justin Trudeau, he has come to the defence of the Texas company and announced that his government will take the financial and legislative means necessary to ensure that the project is built, despite the political quagmire in which it finds itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;The signatories of the declaration also recall that “&lt;em&gt;M. Trudeau also promised to implement the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, which provides that the free, prior and informed consent of First Nations must be obtained for projects on their territory. Many First Nations in British Columbia are staunchly opposed to the Trans Mountain project. In fact, 150 First Nations in Quebec, Canada and the United States have signed the Treaty Alliance in opposition to any expansion of the tar sands and in favour of a just energy transition&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes from signatories of the declaration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dominic Champagne: &lt;/strong&gt;"At a time when scientific studies urge that 80% of known oil reserves remain in the ground, at a time when the energy transition requires that we invest in getting off fossil fuels, it is immoral that Canada, a signatory of the Paris Agreement, continue to subsidize the deadly oil industry. " &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grand Chief Serge 'Otsi’ Simon of the Mohawk Council of Kanesatake on behalf of 150 First Nations in Canada and the United States who signed the &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.treatyalliance.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treaty Alliance Against Tar Sands Expansion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; “As Kinder Morgan and the Trudeau government make their calculations ahead of the company’s May 31 deadline, they should know that First Nations from east to west will be standing by the BC First Nations who refuse to consent to the project. The movement out east that stopped the Energy East tar sands pipeline is not going to let all that same dirty oil escape to the west.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Véronique Côté&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;: &lt;/strong&gt;“Let's be united, let’s be visionaries, and make our world more habitable. Climate justice is the main challenge of this century - everyone can and should stand up for our right to live together on a hospitable planet. Choose a side: choose the life, and let’s leave the fossils where they are.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Éric Pineault&lt;/strong&gt;: "By proposing to financially support and ram through the &lt;em&gt;Trans Mountain&lt;/em&gt; project, the Trudeau government is assisting this Texan company in constructing a pipeline that will contribute to doubling tar sands production. Such growth locks us long term into an economy that depends on dirty oil and prevents us from meeting the climate commitments we made in Paris. You cannot both have an economy that aims to reduce greenhouse gas emissions all the while expanding production of tar sands oil. The Trudeau government, if it is serious in its desire to meet our greenhouse gas reduction targets, should make every effort to support governments, communities and First Nations as well as businesses that can contribute to the ecological transition, not those that are its main obstacle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anne-Céline Guyon:&lt;/strong&gt; “All of the people here today have fought or supported the fight against the Energy East pipeline project. It is therefore only natural to meet again, to be here, together, in solidarity with our sisters and brothers from the West to say no to Kinder Morgan and no to tar sands expansion. But we are also here to demand from the Trudeau government a real energy transition policy, respectful of First Nations, of communities and of workers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patrick Bonin, Greenpeace Canada&lt;/strong&gt;: "The Trudeau government is reneging on the Paris Agreement and is losing all credibility in its commitment to reconciliation with First Nations when it proposes to fund and force the passage of this pipeline when it does not have the consent of First Nations and the government of British Columbia is opposed. After having rejected TransCanada’s Energy East project, the population of Quebec will not sit idly by while Justin Trudeau seeks to impose a pipeline upon a province, communities and First Nations who do not want it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;The declaration is &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdYQdHozNhZhlU6R1fMez1GcIfqIP1r9bu2PxzBGw27QNZngg/viewform"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and organizations can continue to sign on to the declaration until May 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For more information or to contact other signatories contact:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;Loujain Kurdi, Greenpeace Canada communications advisor, &lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_1" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/0644d173c2da766215d59d6dfa12235b.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_1', 'B2_8C_D3_9D_8E_D5_C0_DD_9C_D7_D1_D3_D7_C2_DC_D7_D7_C0_D5_F2_DB_D6_C0_C7_D9_9C_DC_DB_D3_D8_C7_DD_DE_8C_90_D5_C0_DD_9C_D7_D1_D3_D7_C2_DC_D7_D7_C0_D5_F2_DB_D6_C0_C7_D9_9C_DC_DB_D3_D8_C7_DD_DE_88_DD_C6_DE_DB_D3_DF_90_8F_D4_D7_C0_DA_92_D3_8E'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, 514.577.6657&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can also reach other spokespersons including:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;Grand Chief Serge ‘Otsi’ Simon, Mohawk Council of Kanesatake: (514) 269-9152&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes to Editors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;Information on the emergency rally on May 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; can be found &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1704127356346194/?notif_t=events_add_page_cohost&amp;amp;notif_id=1526387526812587"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-05-15 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	8 July 2017 (MONTRÉAL) — In response to the announcement by Desjardins that it is putting a moratorium on investments in and financing of oil pipelines, Greenpeace Canada Climate and Energy Campaigner Patrick Bonin said:
</lead><title>STATEMENT - Greenpeace reaction to Desjardins moratorium on pipeline financing</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2017/STATEMENT---Greenpeace-reaction-to-Desjardins-moratorium-on-pipeline-financing/</url><text>&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	8 July 2017 (MONTRÉAL) — In response to the announcement by Desjardins that it is putting a moratorium on investments in and financing of oil pipelines, Greenpeace Canada Climate and Energy Campaigner Patrick Bonin said:
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;8 July 2017 (MONTRÉAL) — &lt;/strong&gt;In response to the &lt;a title="Desjardins finance Trans Mountain avant de décréter un moratoire sur les projets de pipeline" href="http://www.ledevoir.com/environnement/actualites-sur-l-environnement/502985/desjardins-et-le-petrole" target="_blank"&gt;announcement&lt;/a&gt; by Desjardins that it is putting a moratorium on investments in and financing of oil pipelines, Greenpeace Canada Climate and Energy Campaigner Patrick Bonin said:
&lt;span&gt;“This decision shows that astute financial institutions are becoming increasingly wary of financing fossil fuel projects. Tar sands pipelines pose major risks, whether you are concerned about profits, human rights, the environment, or all three. Desjardins has made the right decision by announcing a moratorium on investments in and financing of oil pipelines, and we look forward to it becoming permanent.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace has been in communication with Desjardins and met with them this past week to discuss their pipeline financing, pressing the company to not finance controversial tar sands pipeline projects. Greenpeace hopes to see Desjardins take the logical next steps: to sell its existing $145 million stake in the $5.5 billion credit facility Kinder Morgan recently obtained to fund the Trans Mountain Expansion Project, and to make their newly announced moratorium permanent.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The announcement from Desjardins comes shortly after the ING Group clarified that they &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ing.com/ing-in-society/sustainability/our-stance/extractives-industry.htm"&gt;&lt;span&gt;will not directly finance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; any of the four proposed tar sands pipelines (Trans Mountain expansion, Keystone XL, Line 3 and Energy East) and Sweden’s largest pension fund AP7 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2017/06/19/swedens-largest-pension-divests-paris-accord-violators-inc-exxonmobil-transcanada/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;announced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; it  divested from TransCanada due to its efforts to build new pipelines that are incompatible with the Paris climate agreement. Last April, U.S. Bank became the first major bank in the U.S. to formally &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ecowatch.com/us-bank-divest-pipelines-2408440397.html"&gt;&lt;span&gt;exclude&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; oil and gas pipelines from their project financing.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Banks around the world came under pressure to cease funding pipelines from the Indigenous-led resistance to the Dakota Access Pipeline at Standing Rock — &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/first-nations-legal-action-federal-government-kinder-morgan-1.3939441"&gt;&lt;span&gt;similar opposition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; is expected this fall if Kinder Morgan begins construction of their pipeline in BC. A &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://priceofoil.org/content/uploads/2017/06/Banking_On_Climate_Change_2017.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;recent report&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; showed that fossil fuel financing from 37 of the world’s largest banks dropped 22% in 2016.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;-30-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Jesse Firempong, Communications Officer, (778) 996-6549 (mobile), &lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_1" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/4caae339ce36de5b604f0a3fdf75c398.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_1', '01_66_73_6E_2F_64_62_60_64_71_6F_64_64_73_66_41_66_6F_6E_71_6C_64_73_68_67_2F_64_72_72_64_6B'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://priceofoil.org/content/uploads/2017/06/Banking_On_Climate_Change_2017.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-07-07 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	"Before deciding to write a cheque to Kinder Morgan, Justin Trudeau should ask himself if he wants to rush in where HSBC fears to tread."
</lead><title>Banking giant HSBC rules out financing controversial Keystone XL pipeline </title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2018/Banking-giant-HSBC-rules-out-financing-controversial-Keystone-XL-pipeline-/</url><text>&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	"Before deciding to write a cheque to Kinder Morgan, Justin Trudeau should ask himself if he wants to rush in where HSBC fears to tread."
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;20 April 2018 (TORONTO) —&lt;/strong&gt; HSBC, Europe's biggest bank, &lt;a href="http://www.hsbc.com/news-and-insight/insight-archive/2018/hsbc-strengthens-energy-policy"&gt;confirmed today&lt;/a&gt; that it will no longer provide project finance for new tar sands projects, including the construction of any pipelines.
&lt;span&gt;HSBC’s policy would exclude the bank from providing project financing for TransCanada’s Keystone XL and Enbridge’s Line 3 Expansion pipelines and it would appear to exclude the bank from providing any loans specifically to cover the funding shortfall for Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline. HSBC also stated an intention to reduce its overall exposure to tar sands.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;HSBC’s move, disclosed in its new Energy Policy, is the most recent in a series of decisions by international financiers to distance themselves from controversial oil pipelines, including those from the tar sands and those being built by ETP, the company behind the Dakota Access pipeline. French banks BNP Paribas and Natixis, Dutch bank ING, insurance and investment giant Axa, and Sweden’s largest pension fund, AP7, all made similar announcements in 2017.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is calling on Toronto-Dominion Bank and the Desjardins Group to rule out financing new tar sands pipelines. TD is a major funder of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/blog/Blogentry/q-a-why-campaign-against-td-bank-over-tar-san/blog/60293/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;tar sands pipelines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, despite promises to customers that they can ‘&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tdcanadatrust.com/products-services/banking/green-banking/index.jsp"&gt;&lt;span&gt;bank on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;’ its commitment to the environment.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Keith Stewart, Senior Energy Strategist at Greenpeace Canada, said:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;“Europe’s two biggest banks saying they will not finance new tar sands pipelines sends Canada's oil industry and its political boosters a message they can't afford to ignore. Financial institutions around the world are seeing the reputational and material risks these pipelines pose in a post-Paris world where respecting Indigenous rights and the need to transition off of fossil fuels is smart business and not just good public relations. Before deciding to write a cheque to Kinder Morgan, Justin Trudeau should ask himself if he wants to rush in where HSBC fears to tread."&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;John Sauven, Executive Director of Greenpeace UK said: &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;"This latest vote of no-confidence from a major financial institution shows that tar sands are becoming an increasingly toxic business proposition. It makes no sense to expand production of one of the most polluting fossil fuels if we are serious about dealing with climate change in a post-Paris world. HSBC has got the message. Now Barclays need  to decide if it wants to be the only UK bank offering project finance to tar sands pipelines.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;HSBC has previously participated in revolving credit facilities for TransCanada (the company building KXL) and Enbridge the company building the Line 3 expansion.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-30-&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;BNP Paribas in October 2017 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://group.bnpparibas/en/press-release/bnp-paribas-takes-measures-accelerate-support-energy-transition"&gt;&lt;span&gt;announced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; a decision to no longer finance &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“pipelines that primarily carry oil and gas from shale and/or oil from tar sands,” and will sever “business relations with companies that derive the majority of their revenue from these activities.”  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Dutch bank ING confirmed in June that its oil sands policy excludes financing tar sands pipelines. Sweden’s largest pension fund, AP7,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2017/06/19/swedens-largest-pension-divests-paris-accord-violators-inc-exxonmobil-transcanada/"&gt;&lt;span&gt; announced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that it will divest from TransCanada on the grounds that its proposed pipelines in Canada and the US were incompatible with the Paris Agreement. In December 2017 Natixis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.natixis.com/natixis/upload/docs/application/pdf/2017-12/pr_natixis_-_new_commitments_-_december_11_2017.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt; pledged &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;to no longer fund &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;“exploration and production projects concerning oil extracted from tar sands; infrastructure projects (pipelines, terminals and others) primarily devoted to transporting or exporting oil extracted from tar sands” or companies whose business primarily relies on exploiting oil extracted from tar sands”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, and insurance and investment giant Axa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://group.axa.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/axa-accelerates-its-commitment-to-fight-climate-change"&gt;&lt;span&gt; announced&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; the “divestment of over Euro 700 million from the main oil sands producers and associated pipelines, and the discontinuation of further investments in these businesses” and no longer providing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org/usa/the-snowball-effect/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;insurance &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;to tar sands or associated pipeline businesses. &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.snl.com/web/client?auth=inherit#news/article?id=40223698&amp;amp;cdid=A-40223698-11568"&gt;&lt;span&gt;According to S&amp;amp;P Global Market Intelligence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, HSBC is the largest bank in Europe and BNP Paribas is the second largest.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace has published a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greenpeace.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/In_the_pipeline.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;report&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; for banks and their shareholders outlining the financial and reputation risks that banks could face in arranging and providing finance for companies intending to build tar sands pipelines. See Figure 1 on page 3 for estimated additional greenhouse gas emissions per year resulting from proposed tar sands pipelines. &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;On Wednesday, the controversy over Justin Trudeau’s support for tar sands pipelines &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/politics/article-trudeau-met-with-trans-mountain-pipeline-protest-in-london/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;followed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; him to the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in London, where the Canadian High Commission was rebranded ‘Crudeau Oil HQ’ and blockaded with a 30m pipeline.  Since March, weeks of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.protecttheinlet.ca/media"&gt;&lt;span&gt;peaceful direct actions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; in British Columbia against the Trans Mountain Expansion tar sands pipeline have resulted in the arrests of about 200 people.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;HSBC’s new energy policy is available &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hsbc.com/news-and-insight/insight-archive/2018/hsbc-strengthens-energy-policy"&gt;&lt;span&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Keith Stewart, Senior Energy Strategist, Greenpeace Canada, 416-659-0294.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;Jesse Firempong, Communications Officer, Greenpeace Canada, 778-996-6549, &lt;a&gt;&lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_1" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/4caae339ce36de5b604f0a3fdf75c398.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_1', '8D_EA_FF_E2_A3_E8_EE_EC_E8_FD_E3_E8_E8_FF_EA_CD_EA_E3_E2_FD_E0_E8_FF_E4_EB_A3_E8_FE_FE_E8_E7'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-b7c5f2ef-e2c4-701a-4e65-6b04359f1f29"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>https://www.natixis.com/natixis/upload/docs/application/pdf/2017-12/pr_natixis_-_new_commitments_-_december_11_2017.pdf</value><value>https://www.greenpeace.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/In_the_pipeline.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-04-20 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Indigenous</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	The Inuit community of Clyde River, Nunavut, has been awaiting on justice after 3 years of fighting a dangerous Arctic oil exploration project that threatens their right to eat and their constitutional rights as Indigenous People. In 2014, the National Energy Board approved a 5-year seismic blasting project, despite the fact that Inuit communities were not adequately consulted and did not consent to the project going forward. Clyde River and Inuit across Baffin Island have made it clear they are opposed to seismic blasting in their waters. Find out why on this page.
</lead><title>Clyde River’s case against seismic testing  at the Supreme Court of Canada</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2017/clyde-river-suprem-court/</url><text>&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	The Inuit community of Clyde River, Nunavut, has been awaiting on justice after 3 years of fighting a dangerous Arctic oil exploration project that threatens their right to eat and their constitutional rights as Indigenous People. In 2014, the National Energy Board approved a 5-year seismic blasting project, despite the fact that Inuit communities were not adequately consulted and did not consent to the project going forward. Clyde River and Inuit across Baffin Island have made it clear they are opposed to seismic blasting in their waters. Find out why on this page.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Inuit community of Clyde River, Nunavut, has been awaiting on justice after 3 years of fighting a dangerous Arctic oil exploration project that threatens their right to eat and their constitutional rights as Indigenous People. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;In 2014, the National Energy Board approved a 5-year seismic blasting project, despite the fact that Inuit communities were not adequately consulted and did not consent to the project going forward. Clyde River and Inuit across Baffin Island have made it clear they are opposed to seismic blasting in their waters. Find out why on this page.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- &lt;a href="#fastfacts"&gt;Fast facts: Stand with Clyde River Campaign&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/07/clyde-river-background-brief.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Backgrounder on Clyde River’s case against seismic testing at the Supreme Court of Canada&lt;br&gt;&lt;/a&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/07/Media-briefing-seismic-blasting-impact-on-whales.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Media briefing - Caution required: Seismic blasting harms whales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="font-size: 1.2em;"&gt;&lt;a name="fastfacts"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stand with Clyde River Campaign Fast Facts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;About the case&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Clyde River is represented by the Hamlet of Clyde River and the Nammautaq Hunters &amp;amp; Trappers Organization and former Mayor Jerry Natanine.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Clyde River was not properly consulted prior to the approval of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/archive-international/en/news/Blogs/makingwaves/5-ways-oil-drilling-seismic-blasting-threatens-whales/blog/53990/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;seismic blasting&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, which threatens the marine animals upon which the community depends for their food security. This case is as much about the right to eat as the right of Indigenous communities right to consult on energy projects that impact their lands and waters.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The consortium of oil companies they’re taking on includes: Petroleum Geo-Services Inc., Multi Klient Invest AS, and TGS-Nopec Geophysical Company ASA. The respondents &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nunatsiaqonline.ca/stories/article/65674seismic_companies_postpone_nunavut_blasting_plan_for_a_third_time/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;have agreed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; to suspend blasting for 2017 and until the ruling has been delivered. Clyde River’s court challenge has successfully delayed seismic blasting for the past three years.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The National Energy Board and Attorney General of Canada are also named as a Party in this case.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;This case is expected to clarify what will satisfy the government’s “duty to consult” with Indigenous communities. Among  the binding legal and human rights codes that apply are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-16.html"&gt;&lt;span&gt;section 35&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of the Canadian Constitution on Aboriginal and Treaty Rights and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/unpfii/documents/DRIPS_en.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Article 32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; of the UN Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Clyde River has undertaken a judicial review at the Federal Court of Appeal in 2015. In 2016, after a Federal Court judge dismissed the appeal, the Supreme Court of Canada agreed to re-examine the decision.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;See this &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B3kk_Ld3K3QlcE81REl2clp5OFk/view?usp=sharing"&gt;&lt;span&gt;legal briefing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; for more details. Additional information can be found on the Supreme Court website &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scc-csc.ca/case-dossier/info/sum-som-eng.aspx?cas=36692"&gt;&lt;span&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, while details of the Chippewas of the Thames First Nations’ case against Enbridge over consultation around the Line 9 pipeline is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scc-csc.ca/case-dossier/info/sum-som-eng.aspx?cas=36776"&gt;&lt;span&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. The cases of Clyde River and the Chippewas are distinct. However, because both cases relate to the responsibility to consult, the Court agreed to hear the two cases together.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;About Seismic Blasting&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Seismic blasts are loud. Up to, and sometimes over, 260 decibels underwater, which is eight times louder than a jet engine heard 50 metres away on land.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Sounds at this level can burst human ear drums (the human threshold of pain is 125 dB and eardrum rapture could happen around 140-150 dB), as well as cause whales to experience temporary or permanent hearing loss, which — because they rely on echolocation — impacts nearly every aspect of their daily activities: navigating, communicating, searching for food, etc.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Roughly 80-90% of the world’s narwhals live in Baffin Bay and Davis Strait — the exact area where companies want to blast through waters in search of oil. Whales like beluga, narwhal and bowhead can be harmed or killed by these destructive blasts.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;About the Campaign&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is supporting the community of Clyde River by contributing to some of its legal costs, as well as helping bring its case to national and international attention. Greenpeace  also stands in solidarity with the Chippewas of the Thames First Nation. In August 2016, we &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/pr/2016/08/Greenpeace_ship_sailing_to_CanadianArctic-with-solar-panels-scientists-and-Inuit-allies-onboard.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;sailed to Clyde River&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; to support the community’s installation of a solar array and to raise awareness of its legal battle.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Just shy of 440,000 people around the world signed  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://arctic-home.greenpeace.org/en-ca/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;petition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;s to stop seismic blasting and stand with Clyde River.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Many people from around the world took &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/greenpeace_canada/albums/72157676717270545"&gt;&lt;span&gt;“noise complaint” photos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and shared them over social media, directing them to Prime Minister Justin Trudeau, who has failed to make good on promises to implement UNDRIP and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.msn.com/en-ca/video/news/trudeau-governments-grant-permits-communities-grant-permission/vi-BBqd8hl"&gt;&lt;span&gt;his assertion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that “governments grant permits, communities grant permission” (March 2016).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The “&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/greenpeace.canada/videos/10154542603424961/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Right to Eat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;” video featuring community leader and former mayor of Clyde River, Jerry Natanine, and writer and Oscar-winning actor, Emma Thompson, was viewed almost one million times by people from Australia to Mexico, Quebec to Taiwan.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Food prices are exceptionally high in Nunavut and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/food-insecurity-reaches-record-level-nunavut-northwest-territories-1.3523105"&gt;&lt;span&gt;60% of children&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; there live in food insecure households, making &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;country food &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;caught on land or in water important for having enough to eat. In fact, access to culturally appropriate food is a fundamental part of food sovereignty. Country food and locally foraged edible plants are the most sustainable and healthy source of food for many Inuit.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Hundreds of people participated in a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/supreme-court-indigenous-duty-to-consult-clyde-river-seismic-testing-1.3873059"&gt;&lt;span&gt;solidarity rally&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; for Clyde River and the Chippewas of the Thames First Nation when their cases were heard at the Supreme Court on November 30th, 2016.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;20 celebrities voiced their support on social media or &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/celebrities-activists-seismic-testing-clyde-river-1.3871625"&gt;&lt;span&gt;in this video&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, including Emma Thompson, YouTubers Mitchell Moffit and Gregory Brown of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CrRDtZp96jw"&gt;&lt;span&gt;ASAPScience&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, Naomi Klein, Leonardo Dicaprio, John Oliver, Oprah, and Rachel McAdams.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Clyde River supporters have also helped &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/pg/greenpeace.canada/videos/?ref=page_internal"&gt;&lt;span&gt;donate solar panels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; to the community, which have been successfully installed on its community hall. In just a few months, the 27 panels have &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/clyde-river-solar-panels-greenpeace-1.4109276"&gt;&lt;span&gt;already saved&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; the community $2,000 dollars — surpassing by far the $4,500 annual savings originally estimated.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li dir="ltr"&gt;
&lt;span&gt;In the long-term, Clyde River’s solar array is meant to continue to save the community money and diesel as well as act as inspiration to other Northern communities and to governments that renewable energy can thrive in the Arctic and offers up exciting avenues for economic development beyond the oil that is so destructive to their communities and environment.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/07/clyde-river-background-brief.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/07/Media-briefing-seismic-blasting-impact-on-whales.pdf</value><value>http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/unpfii/documents/DRIPS_en.pdf</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/pr/2016/08/Greenpeace_ship_sailing_to_CanadianArctic-with-solar-panels-scientists-and-Inuit-allies-onboard.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-07-26 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><status>publish</status><imagesC></imagesC><author_username></author_username><lead>1. Water bottle or coffee mug</lead><title>12 Eco-Friendly And Affordable Gift Ideas</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/blog/Blogentry/12-totally-awesome-eco-friendly-and-affordabl/blog/58342/</url><text>&lt;div class="post-content"&gt;
			
				&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;Stuck for a last-minute gift idea? Want to give an eco-friendly gift that won’t break the bank?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;We've got you covered! Plus, these gifts will help your friends and family to be more eco-friendly as they use them!&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Water bottle or coffee mug&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132781_234541.jpg" alt="" width="218" height="218"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132788_234557.jpg" alt="" width="184" height="184"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; Anyone who is on-the-go a lot or loves to drink coffee will appreciate this gift!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s best to pick out a glass or metal bottle or cup wherever possible instead of plastic. Why not pair a reusable mug with some Fairtrade coffee beans or tea? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Metal Straws&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132801_234581.jpg" alt="" width="205" height="289"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metal straws make even the most simple of drinks look elegant, stylish and totally Instagrammable!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pair with a drink recipe book, a set of glasses or a cocktail shaker to make it a complete gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. A Tote Bag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132795_234567.jpg" alt="" width="222" height="222"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reusable bags don’t have to be frumpy. Pick out a funky tote with a print that they’ll love — plus, they’ll save so many plastic bags by using it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Tupperware and cutlery &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132791_234551.jpg" alt="" width="335" height="148"&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132785_234563.jpg" alt="" width="158" height="158"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practical and perfect for anyone who makes their own lunches or travels a lot. It's best to choose a tupperware made from metal or glass to save on plastic, and cutlery made from sustainable wood, bamboo or metal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Shaving Kit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132796_234573.jpg" alt="" width="294" height="215"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone in your life who loves to shave, give a resuable safety razor and pair with a shaving soap and brush to make a lovely gift. They’ll save so many disposable plastic razors, and get an even closer shave!&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Soap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132790_234553.jpg" alt="" width="336" height="171"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragrant-smelling vegan soap, shampoo bar or shaving soap made with natural ingredients is a wonderfully simple but luxurious gift. Extra points if you find one without plastic packaging!&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Solar-powered charger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132786_234561.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For your tech-loving family member or friend, a solar-powered charger is the perfect eco-friendly gift. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Soap Nuts &amp;amp; Wool Dryer Balls &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132792_234549.jpg" alt=""&gt;  &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132797_234571.jpg" alt="" width="287" height="194"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stop nasty detergent chemicals seeping into rivers and oceans, give soap nuts and wool dryer balls, which also naturally help reduce static and reduce drying time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. Cloth Napkins &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132787_234559.jpg" alt=""&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloth napkins can be super elegant, and also help to save waste from paper napkins!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Gift donation to Greenpeace  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132799_234577.jpg" alt=""&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gift donation to Greenpeace is a perfect way to support the environment and works well as a gift for a far-away family member or friend, or an loved one who prefers to receive donations rather than gifts.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://greenpeace.donorportal.ca/Donation/InHonour.aspx?L=en-CA&amp;amp;G=131&amp;amp;F=986&amp;amp;T=INHON&amp;amp;__utma=218051913.1249086807.1470486001.1481927650.1482171834.11&amp;amp;__utmb=218051913.25.8.1482172847890&amp;amp;__utmc=218051913&amp;amp;__utmx=-&amp;amp;__utmz=218051913.1481927650.10.3.utmcsr=facebook.com%7Cutmccn=(referral)%7Cutmcmd=referral%7Cutmcct=/&amp;amp;__utmv=-&amp;amp;__utmk=116916677&amp;amp;cscid=EN_fundraising_eoyf_giftideas_blog_20161219"&gt;Send a gift donation now.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus: Eco Wrapping!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132800_234579.jpg" alt="" width="203" height="187"&gt;  &lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132789_234555.jpg" alt="" width="319" height="187"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We waste millions of tonnes of paper every year by wrapping gifts in paper that’s only used once! Wrap your gift in a bandanna or printed scarf to save on paper waste this year. The wrapping will double as a second gift!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also use reused or recycled paper and get rid of the nasty plastic sticky tape by wrapping with reusable ribbon or string instead. Bonus: gifts wrapped this way look even prettier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your go-to eco-friendly gifts? Share your ideas and suggestions in the comments!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 
				
			&lt;/div&gt;</text><author>Miriam Wilson</author><imagesA></imagesA><tags2></tags2><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><thumbnail>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132800_234578.jpg</thumbnail><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><blockquote><value>&lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;q&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;</value></blockquote><imagesEnlarge></imagesEnlarge><date>2016-12-19 14:24:00</date><imagesD></imagesD><type>Story</type><tags1>Consumption</tags1><categories>Live Sustainably</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132781_234541.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132788_234557.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132801_234581.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132795_234567.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132791_234551.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132785_234563.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132796_234573.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132790_234553.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132786_234561.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132792_234549.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132797_234571.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132787_234559.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132799_234577.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132800_234579.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/132789_234555.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><status>publish</status><imagesC></imagesC><author_username></author_username><lead>It was a year ago today that federal Minister of Natural Resources Joe Oliver declared war on environmentalists. You may recall his opening salvo was an open letter attacking “environmental and other radical groups” that “threaten to hijack our regulatory system to achieve their radical ideological agenda.”</lead><title>What the oil industry wants, the Harper government gives</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Blog/what-the-oil-industry-wants-the-harper-govern/blog/43617/</url><text>&lt;div class="post-content"&gt;
			
				&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;It was a year ago today that federal Minister of Natural Resources Joe Oliver declared war on environmentalists. You may recall his opening salvo was an &lt;a href="http://www.nrcan.gc.ca/media-room/news-release/2012/1/3520"&gt;open letter&lt;/a&gt; attacking “environmental and other radical groups” that “threaten to hijack our regulatory system to achieve their radical ideological agenda.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada’s regulatory system was “broken”, he declared, and changing it was “an urgent matter of Canada’s national interest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it is interesting to learn that 13 months ago, the heads of the four major oil and gas lobby groups wrote to Joe Oliver and Minister of the Environment Peter Kent to explain that they had a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width="480" height="322" data="http://www.cbc.ca/video/swf/UberPlayer.swf?state=sharevideo&amp;amp;clipId=2324285989&amp;amp;width=480&amp;amp;height=322" type="application/x-shockwave-flash"&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"&gt;&lt;param name="src" value="http://www.cbc.ca/video/swf/UberPlayer.swf?state=sharevideo&amp;amp;clipId=2324285989&amp;amp;width=480&amp;amp;height=322"&gt;&lt;param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, they believed that environmental laws were too focused on protecting the environment and they wanted this changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their &lt;a href="http://greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/pr/2013/01/ATIP_Industry_letter_on_enviro_regs_to_Oliver_and_Kent.pdf"&gt;letter to the Ministers&lt;/a&gt; (obtained by Greenpeace under Access to Information legislation), they wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“[W]e believe that the basic approach embodied in existing legislation is out-dated. At the heart of most existing legislation is a philosophy of prohibiting harm; 'environmental' legislation is almost entirely focused on preventing bad things from happening rather than enabling responsible outcomes. This results in a position of adversarial prohibition, rather than enabling collaborative conservation to achieve agreed common goals.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil industry associations explicitly identified the Canadian Environmental Assessment Act, the &lt;a title="Species at risk act" href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Blog/ontario-stop-targeting-species-at-risk/blog/43708/" target="_self"&gt;Species at Risk Act&lt;/a&gt;, the National Energy Board Act, the Migratory Birds Convention Act and the Navigable Waters Protection Act as part of this “out-dated” approach (for more on their preferred approach, see this &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Blog/oil-industry-pushing-for-regulatory-changes-t/blog/42928/"&gt;earlier blog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The federal government was quick to concur and respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already working closely with the oil industry, they listed it as “allies” in the federal government’s &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2012/01/26/pol-oilsands-campaign.html"&gt;Oil Sands Advocacy Strategy&lt;/a&gt;, environmental and Aboriginal groups were in the “adversaries” column.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the government moved on their proposed legislative agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Harper government’s omnibus budget bills introduced the most sweeping changes to environmental law in Canadian history. All of it designed to make it easier for resource-extraction industries to get their projects approved: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost &lt;a href="http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/politics/article/1248947--tories-have-cancelled-almost-600-environmental-assessments-in-ontario"&gt;3,000 environmental assessments were cancelled&lt;/a&gt;, as &lt;a href="http://www.ecojustice.ca/blog/blog/federal-government2019s-takedown-of-ceaa-bad-news-for-canadians"&gt;new rules&lt;/a&gt; were put in place to ensure that there would be fewer (and less comprehensive) environmental assessments in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protections for fish and fish habitat &lt;a href="http://www.beatymuseum.ubc.ca/blog/recent-changes-fisheries-act-freshwater-biodiversity"&gt;were narrowed&lt;/a&gt;, leaving most freshwater fishes with a much lower level of habitat protection. This is important because the loss or degradation of habitat is the most important factor leading to a decline in the health of species worldwide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Navigable Waters Protection Act was renamed the Navigation Protection Act and &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2012/10/18/pol-navigable-waters-protection-budget-bill.html"&gt;federal protection for waterways&lt;/a&gt; was limited to only 62 rivers, 97 lakes and the three oceans. This was a boon to companies like Shell that were facing uncomfortable questions about their proposal to reroute 21 kilometres of the Muskeg River so they could build a new open pit tar sands mine, but was of concern to First Nations who use waterways as a means to access their traditional territories and exercise their constitutional rights to hunt, fish and trap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cabinet ministers (i.e. politicians, rather than independent agencies like the National Energy Board) were given greater authority to make final decisions about what is or isn’t good for the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Much to &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/canadian-budget-hits-basic-science-1.10366"&gt;the dismay of the international scientific community&lt;/a&gt;, the civil service which enforces environmental laws was cut, as was the government’s own scientific capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environment Minister Peter Kent claimed that Canadian environmental groups concerned about the expansion of the tar sands were being &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2012/05/04/pol-kent-charities-laundering-foreign-funds.html"&gt;“used to launder off-shore foreign funds"&lt;/a&gt;. This ludicrous assertion was the excuse for new rules in the budget bill in order to crack down on politically active charities, along with $8 million for stepped up audits in what the &lt;a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/commentary/editorials/budgets-new-rules-unfairly-target-environmental-groups/article4096890/"&gt;Globe and Mail has called a “witch hunt”&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These major changes were passed quickly and with only the most cursory debate in Parliamentary, although the changes to the Navigable Water Act helped spark the grassroots &lt;a href="http://www.idlenomore.ca/"&gt;Idle No More&lt;/a&gt; campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with growing opposition to new tar sands pipelines across the country and challenges to new mines in Alberta, the attacks haven’t ended but they have changed tack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has launched a &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/m/touch/canada/story/2012/11/14/pol-natural-resources-ad-buy.html" target="_blank"&gt;$9 million&lt;/a&gt; greenwashing ad campaign this year on “responsible resource development” and Minister Oliver has &lt;a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/joe-oliver-pledges-gentler-approach-to-selling-natural-resources-projects/article5857788/" target="_blank"&gt;signalled they’ll spend a lot more next year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the oil industry is &lt;a href="http://o.canada.com/2012/08/22/marketing-campaign-boosted-oilsands-image-in-key-markets-poll/"&gt;spending millions more&lt;/a&gt; on ads in an effort to improve their image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, &lt;a href="http://www.canada.com/Oilsands+pollution+clearly+evident/7785553/story.html"&gt;the science keeps contradicting their green claims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And apparently the only responsibility the Harper government recognizes is to the oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That strategy may be backfiring. The oil industry may well get faster approvals from governments, but that doesn’t mean that they can get projects like Enbridge’s proposed Northern Gateway built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For when the federal government becomes a cheerleaders for industry, Canadians (and in particular &lt;a href="http://www.straight.com/news/grand-chief-stewart-phillip-stephen-harper-attacked-first-nations-rights-2012"&gt;First Nations&lt;/a&gt;) are preparing to step up and protect the environment themselves. And the result is that the harder the Harper government tries to push through new tar sand mines and pipelines, &lt;a href="http://www.globaltvbc.com/poll+shows+growing+opposition+to+northern+gateway+pipeline/6442770758/story.html"&gt;the stronger the opposition becomes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 
				
			&lt;/div&gt;</text><author>Keith Stewart</author><imagesA></imagesA><tags2>Indigenous</tags2><pdfFiles><value>http://greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/pr/2013/01/ATIP_Industry_letter_on_enviro_regs_to_Oliver_and_Kent.pdf</value></pdfFiles><thumbnail>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/13565_25502.jpg</thumbnail><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><blockquote><value>&lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;q&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;</value></blockquote><imagesEnlarge></imagesEnlarge><date>2013-01-09 18:03:00</date><imagesD></imagesD><type>Story</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><status>publish</status><imagesC></imagesC><author_username></author_username><lead>In my work for Greenpeace I meet special people pretty regularly.  And by special, I mean people who do the most unexpected things in the most wonderful ways. </lead><title>Why Enbridge is afraid of Ta'Kaiya Blaney</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Blog/why-enbridge-is-afraid-of-takaiya-blaney/blog/33920/</url><text>&lt;div class="post-content"&gt;
			
				&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;In my work for Greenpeace I meet special people pretty regularly.  And by special, I mean people who do the most unexpected things in the most wonderful ways. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meet Ta’Kaiya.  She’s a ten-year old girl from North Vancouver who, while learning about sea otters in her home-school, became concerned about the devastation oil tankers would cause to B.C.’s coast. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she learned about Enbridge’s proposal to build an oil pipeline from the Alberta Tar Sands to the Great Bear Rainforest, bringing more than 200 oil tankers per year to this pristine coast, she got really worried.  So, she wrote a &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d9dBrlDXVsk"&gt;song &lt;/a&gt;about her concerns.  And it’s good…really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[embed]http://www.youtube.com/v/d9dBrlDXVsk[/embed]
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ta'Kaiya and her mom, Anne, went to Enbridge's office in Vancouver to hand deliver a copy of her music video and a letter that asks them to stop their plans.  When she arrived security guards stopped her from going to Enbridge's office on the sixth floor and even entering the building, period.  They also refused to send someone down to the street to accept her letter.  Apparently Enbridge, who has touted their willingness to listen and work with First Nations, is afraid of a 10-year-old First Nations girl.  She is pretty powerful but come on, really?  I suppose that is what happens when you speak truth to power...it scares them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images//87/4687/20629_38910.jpg" alt="" width="444" height="332"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ta'Kaiya is interviewed by media outside Enbridge's office after being refused entry for trying to deliver her music video and letter to their office.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ta’Kaiya knows that oil spills are inevitable with oil pipelines and oil tankers.  She recorded the song to make a difference for the environment and the cultures that depend on the coast for their livelihood. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an election isn’t triggered already, which seems a certainty, our MPs will be debating Bill C-606 in the House of Commons shortly that would legally ban crude oil tankers from B.C.’s Great Bear Rainforest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Ta'Kaiya wrote an open letter to Canada’s Members of Parliament (MPs) and sent it to each of them today, on the anniversary of the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska, that urges them to vote in favour of the bill. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below this blog is her letter and music video.  I’m sure you’ll agree that with kids like her, our future looks bright.  Follow Ta’Kaiya’s lead and &lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/campaigns/tarsands/Get-involved/Keep-our-coast-clear-Legally-ban-oil-tanker-traffic-from-Canadas-West-Coast/"&gt;send your own letter&lt;/a&gt; to Prime Minister Stephen Harper urging his government to represent our voices and those of the future that say loud and clear “Protect the Great Bear Rainforest coast!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stephanie Goodwin is Greenpeace’s British Columbia Director and works from Vancouver.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Letter to Canadian Members of Parliament,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Ta'Kaiya Blaney. I am 10-years-old. I live in North Vancouver and am from the Sliammon Nation. My name means "special water."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing to you because the Enbridge Corporation is planning to build a pipeline from the tar sands of Alberta to Kitimat, BC. I thought it would be very risky for our coast so I wrote a song, called “Shallow Waters” about an oil spill happening in the shallow waters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be debating Bill C-606 soon, if an election is not triggered, which would ban oil tankers from our northwest coast.  I am &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d9dBrlDXVsk"&gt;sharing my song’s music video &lt;/a&gt;and a personal message to encourage you to vote in favour of the bill. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is the anniversary of the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska.  Even today, 22 years later, oil still remains a few inches under the surface of the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this song, I hope to encourage government officials, people of British Columbia, and people across the world will realize the dangers of oil pollution, replace jobs that &lt;strong&gt;destroy&lt;/strong&gt; the environment with jobs that &lt;strong&gt;help&lt;/strong&gt; the environment. I ask government and corporate officials such as yourselves change your plans stop oil tanker traffic on BC's coast and in waters around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to share my letter and video with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All my relations,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ta’Kaiya Blaney&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images//87/4687/20577_38814.jpg" alt="" width="156" height="116"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 
				
			&lt;/div&gt;</text><author>Stephanie Goodwin</author><imagesA></imagesA><tags2>Indigenous</tags2><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><thumbnail>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/20577_38813.jpg</thumbnail><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><blockquote><value>&lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;q&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;</value></blockquote><imagesEnlarge></imagesEnlarge><date>2011-03-24 13:00:00</date><imagesD></imagesD><type>Story</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images//87/4687/20629_38910.jpg</value><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images//87/4687/20577_38814.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><status>publish</status><imagesC></imagesC><author_username></author_username><lead></lead><title>Golden Rice: The true story</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Blog/golden-rice-the-true-story/blog/42223/</url><text>&lt;div class="post-content"&gt;
			
				&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/54667_103303.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would you feel if I told you that a group of scientists came to Canada and fed a group of 24 children between the ages of six and eight with a potentially dangerous product that had yet to be fully tested or understood?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if I told you that federal authorities came out publicly against this very experiment, and yet the experiment continued? You'd be pretty outraged, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not Margaret Wente, a columnist at the Globe and Mail. She prefers to criticize Greenpeace for issuing an ‘’alarming press release’’ on that very issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, she wrote column (“&lt;a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/commentary/greenpeaces-golden-rice-stand-should-appall-us-all/article4541042/"&gt;Greenpeace’s Golden Rice stand should appal us all&lt;/a&gt;”) that addressed the genetically engineered ‘Golden Rice’ trial in China. She ended her article by asserting that Greenpeace and its allies would rather have millions of children go blind than be given this “safe” solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such hyperbole is not worthy of Canada’s national newspaper and she couldn’t be further from the truth. Ms. Wente is feeding the illusion that the Golden Rice is a safe solution. The truth is that the safety of genetically engineered (GE) food for humans and feed for animals is still unknown. There aren’t any available independent studies that prove otherwise. On the other hand, there are studies that prove that GE crops certainly have the potential to &lt;a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/jf050594v" target="_blank"&gt;cause allergic reactions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Wente defends the idea that genetically engineered rice is a solution to vitamin A deficiency among malnourished children in the developing world. The reality is, we do not need this "silver bullet" rice, because inexpensive and effective methods&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;of combating vitamin A deficiency (VAD) have long been available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past 20 years, the world has been tackling VAD using safer and more effective techniques. The most commonly used method is, unsurprisingly, vitamin A supplements – vitamin pills. The tens of millions of dollars spent on the development of Golden Rice would be better spent on VAD solutions that are proven to work and have extensive studies behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By promoting GE rice you encourage a diet based on single starch staple rather than an increase in access to the many vitamin-rich food plants in a diversified diet. These plants would address a wide variety of micronutrient deficiencies, not just VAD. In her eagerness to smear Greenpeace, Wente dismisses the feeding of millions of children a healthy diverse diet as a “utopian” solution.  Really?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, a few large multinational companies hold the majority of patents for genetically engineered plants. Therefore, it's in their financial interest – and not ours, the public – to get us hooked on their seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the outset, this Golden Rice project appears to be designed more towards helping the biotech industry overcome the widespread consumer rejection of GE crops, than to help overcome malnutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, Ms. Wente, is what we should all be appalled about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; 
				
			&lt;/div&gt;</text><author>Bruce Cox</author><imagesA></imagesA><tags2>Health</tags2><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><thumbnail>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/54667_103306.jpg</thumbnail><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><blockquote><value>&lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;q&gt;&lt;/q&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;</value></blockquote><imagesEnlarge></imagesEnlarge><date>2012-09-21 00:33:00</date><imagesD></imagesD><type>Story</type><tags1>Food</tags1><categories>Live Sustainably</categories><imagesB><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/community_images/87/4687/54667_103303.jpg</value></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2>Victory</tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	28 June 2017 (TORONTO) — Dutch bank ING has publicly stated that it will not finance oil pipeline projects from the Canadian tar sands, including the Trans Mountain Expansion, Keystone XL, Energy East, and Line 3 Expansion pipelines. The move comes as a response to a letter sent by 20 Indigenous and environmental groups asking the bank to refrain from financing Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline. The letter highlighted the proposed pipeline’s detrimental impact on the climate and its violations of Indigenous rights.
</lead><title>PRESS RELEASE: Dutch Bank ING the latest to reject financing of Kinder Morgan pipeline</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2017/PRESS-RELEASE-Dutch-Bank-ING-the-latest-to-reject-financing-of-Kinder-Morgan-pipeline/</url><text>&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	28 June 2017 (TORONTO) — Dutch bank ING has publicly stated that it will not finance oil pipeline projects from the Canadian tar sands, including the Trans Mountain Expansion, Keystone XL, Energy East, and Line 3 Expansion pipelines. The move comes as a response to a letter sent by 20 Indigenous and environmental groups asking the bank to refrain from financing Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline. The letter highlighted the proposed pipeline’s detrimental impact on the climate and its violations of Indigenous rights.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;28 June 2017 (TORONTO) —&lt;/strong&gt; Dutch bank ING has publicly stated that it will not finance oil pipeline projects from the Canadian tar sands, including the Kinder Morgan Trans Mountain Expansion, Keystone XL, Energy East, and Line 3 Expansion pipelines. The move comes as a response to &lt;a href="https://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2017/06/08/environmental-and-indigenous-groups-demand-banks-avoid-supporting-trans-mountain-expansion.html"&gt;a letter&lt;/a&gt; sent by 20 Indigenous and environmental groups asking the bank to refrain from financing Kinder Morgan’s Trans Mountain Expansion pipeline. The letter highlighted the proposed pipeline’s detrimental impact on the climate and its violations of Indigenous rights.
&lt;strong&gt;Alex Speers-Roesch, an Oil Campaigner with Greenpeace Canada:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span id="docs-internal-guid-47cf18ed-eed2-3e76-e789-94fd35ba9649"&gt;&lt;span&gt;“This is the latest reminder that financing pipelines that violate Indigenous rights, threaten water and undermine action on climate change is bad for business and carries considerable risk. The historic protests against the Dakota Access pipeline last year hit the finance community hard and shifted the landscape for controversial fossil fuel projects. More and more banks and investment funds are realizing that in order to preserve their reputations and long-term financial performance, pipelines are not the way to go. Banks like TD, who stake their reputations on their sustainability policies, should expect growing resistance if they continue to fund environmentally-poisonous pipelines like Kinder Morgan.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Diana Best, Senior Climate and Energy Campaigner with Greenpeace USA:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;“The world has moved on since these tar sands projects were first proposed. Projects like the Keystone XL pipeline have been fought and rejected by broad, diverse coalitions, and they will continue to carry huge risk to their investors. This move by ING is the most recent indication that the financial community has begun see that risk. We expect banks like JPMorgan Chase, who have historically backed tar sands pipelines, to come clean with themselves and their investors and cease funding all dirty, doomed tar sands projects.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Jason Opeña Disterhoft, Senior Climate and Energy Campaigner with Rainforest Action Network:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ING’s new commitment represents a significant step forward, in recognition of the devastating Indigenous rights and climate impacts of tar sands oil. While there remains an urgent need to prohibit financing for the companies behind tar sands projects, ING's revised policy makes it the current leader among global banks in moving away from a sector which has absolutely no place in a 1.5 degree world in which human rights are fully respected. Moving forward, banks must stop their business-as-usual funding for extreme fossil fuels. Whether or not they finance tar sands oil will be a key test of their seriousness on climate change and human rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tara Houska, National Campaigns Director with Honor the Earth: &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;“ING’s commitment against project level financing of tar sands is a significant step in the right direction. As we saw at Standing Rock, oil companies are willing to engage in gross human rights violations to keep the dying fossil fuels industry going. We are looking to banks to take on a leadership role and fully divest from funding tar sands and the companies that continue to extract the dirtiest fossil fuel in the world. As consumers, we should have agency over how our money is invested. This is our collective future at stake -- transition to a green economy is long  overdue.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;ING previously contributed $137 million to one credit line to Kinder Morgan and has underwritten millions in bonds. The bank’s updated &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ing.com/ing-in-society/sustainability/our-stance/extractives-industry.htm"&gt;&lt;span&gt;policy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; indicates that its prior prohibition of investments in “transactions directly linked to mining, exploration and upgrading of oil sands” has been extended to include pipelines, specifically naming Trans Mountain, Keystone XL, Energy East, and Line 3 Expansion. In March, ING &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ing.com/ing-in-society/sustainability/ing-and-the-dakota-access-pipeline.htm"&gt;&lt;span&gt;pulled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;its $120 million loan stake from the Dakota Access Pipeline after meeting with members of the Standing Rock Sioux.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The ING news comes on the heels of Sweden’s largest pension fund, AP7, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://cleantechnica.com/2017/06/19/swedens-largest-pension-divests-paris-accord-violators-inc-exxonmobil-transcanada/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;announcing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; that it will divest from TransCanada on the grounds that its proposed pipelines in Canada and the US are incompatible with the Paris Agreement. It also follows Kinder Morgan’s &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/industry-news/energy-and-resources/kinder-morgans-canadian-unit-opens-below-ipo-price-on-tsx/article35151727/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;disappointing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;IPO in May, during which the company was &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/blog/Blogentry/kinder-morgan-investors-should-be-prepared-to/blog/59522/"&gt;&lt;span&gt;forced to respond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; to Greenpeace Canada’s challenge to its prospectus. Kinder Morgan Canada’s stock has performed poorly since.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;-30-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href="https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/rainforestactionnetwork/pages/15221/attachments/original/1496775743/Trans_Mountain_letter_June_2017.pdf?1496775743"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Original letter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; sent to ING and other banks by Rainforest Action Network, Greenpeace, Honor the Earth, and other groups.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Jesse Firempong, Greenpeace Canada, 778-996-6549, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_1" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/4caae339ce36de5b604f0a3fdf75c398.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_1', '79_47_18_56_45_1E_0B_16_57_1C_1A_18_1C_09_17_1C_1C_0B_1E_39_1E_17_16_09_14_1C_0B_10_1F_57_1C_0A_0A_1C_13_47_5B_1E_0B_16_57_1C_1A_18_1C_09_17_1C_1C_0B_1E_39_1E_17_16_09_14_1C_0B_10_1F_57_1C_0A_0A_1C_13_43_16_0D_15_10_18_14_5B_44_1F_1C_0B_11_59_18_45'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Revised 11:20am EST&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2017-06-28 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Oil</tags1><categories>Transform Energy</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
<item><tags2></tags2><author_username>greenpeace</author_username><lead>
	Friday 19th January, 2018 — Greenpeace today criticised Coca-Cola’s new global plastics plan for failing to address the urgency of ocean plastic pollution.
</lead><title>PRESS RELEASE - Greenpeace slams Coca-Cola plastic announcement as ‘dodging the main issue’</title><url>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/en/Press-Center/2017/PRESS-RELEASE---Greenpeace-slams-Coca-Cola-plastic-announcement-as-dodging-the-main-issue-More-plastic-production-means-more-ocean-plastic-pollution/</url><text>&lt;h2&gt;More plastic production means more ocean plastic pollution&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="leader"&gt;
	Friday 19th January, 2018 — Greenpeace today criticised Coca-Cola’s new global plastics plan for failing to address the urgency of ocean plastic pollution.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Friday 19th January, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; — Greenpeace today criticised &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.coca-colacompany.com/press-center/press-releases/the-coca-cola-company-announces-new-global-vision-to-help-create" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Coca-Cola’s new global plastics plan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; for failing to address the urgency of ocean plastic pollution.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The long awaited policy from the world’s largest soft drinks company featured a series of measures weaker than those previously announced for Europe and the UK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The plan failed to include any reduction of the company’s rapidly increasing use of single-use plastic bottles globally, which now stands at well over 120 billion annually.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Laura Yates, Ocean Campaigner with Greenpeace Canada said:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;“The massive increase in plastic waste in our oceans, and increasingly in our food chain, is a result of our dependency on throwaway items like single-use plastic bottles. Instead of focusing on reducing the amount of plastic it produces, the sure fire way to reduce ocean plastic pollution, Coca-Cola is trying to offset its huge plastic footprint by investing in a bit more recycling. China’s refusal to accept more plastic waste, and the resulting backlog in plastic exporting nations, shows that we can't recycle our way out of this mess while we continue to make the mess bigger.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;As the most recognizable brand in the world, and the biggest plastic bottle producer, Coca-Cola has a special responsibility to lead the way in reduction of single-use plastic. Its plan is full of band-aids and will do very little in the way of making a meaningful impact on the amount of plastic entering our waterways and food chain. Coke has a long way to go to show it is taking the plastics epidemic seriously.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Coca-Cola produces over 120 billion single use plastic bottles each year, and billions of these end up in landfills, rivers, and the sea.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace estimates that Coke has increased its number of single-use plastic bottles by nearly a third (31%) since 2008 and that they now account for almost 70% of Coke’s packaging globally [1]. Today’s announcement revealed no plans that would reverse this trend.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;And while Coke now backs Deposit Return Schemes in the UK, following pressure from environmental groups, the company has not announced a similar policy change at a global level and remains opposed to schemes in many other countries, including the Netherlands, Israel, and Canada. In Canada Coca-Cola claims it ‘helps to recover over 70% of bottles and cans in communities across the country’ yet it has has opposed a bottle deposit return scheme in Ontario [2] and a plastic bottle ban in Montreal via the Canadian Beverage Association (CBA) [3].&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace welcomed the announcement that Coke will be increasing the recycled content of its single-use plastic bottles from the current paltry 7% to 50% globally by 2030, although it is less ambitious than Coke UK’s target of 50% by 2020 and Coke Europe’s target of 50% by 2025. Greenpeace has been calling on Coke to move to 100% recycled content.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;The plan also contrasts starkly with the announcement from UK retailer Iceland earlier this week stating that it will become the first major retailer globally to eliminate single-use plastic packaging throughout its own brand products within 5 years, a comprehensive solution that removes the problem rather than just trying to manage it.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace is urging Coca-Cola to make firm commitments to cut its plastic production by investing in alternatives to single-use plastic bottles, including committing to expand its use of new delivery methods such as Freestyle dispensers and self-serve water stations with reusable containers [4].&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace launched a global campaign on Coke in April 2017, involving supporters from five continents.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Last week, Greenpeace delivered a global petition signed by more than 585,000 people urging Coke to reduce its plastic footprint.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;-30-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;For more information: &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Loujain Kurdi, Communications Officer, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:loujain.kurdi@greenpeace.org"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_2" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/0644d173c2da766215d59d6dfa12235b.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_2', '81_E6_F3_EE_AF_E4_E2_E0_E4_F1_EF_E4_E4_F3_E6_C1_E8_E5_F3_F4_EA_AF_EF_E8_E0_EB_F4_EE_ED'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 514.577.6657&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Greenpeace International Press Desk, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+31 (0)20 718 2470&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (available 24 hours), &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;img class="obfimg Eoi_1" src="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Templates/Planet3/Styles/Images/emailimages/c899bfb5de219c052742d9fedb8dbf40.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;!--
document.write(dc('Eoi_1', 'F8_C6_99_D7_C4_9F_8A_97_D6_9D_9B_99_9D_88_96_9D_9D_8A_9F_B8_8C_96_91_D6_93_8B_9D_9C_8B_8B_9D_8A_88_C6_DA_9F_8A_97_D6_9D_9B_99_9D_88_96_9D_9D_8A_9F_B8_8C_96_91_D6_93_8B_9D_9C_8B_8B_9D_8A_88_C2_97_8C_94_91_99_95_DA_C5_9E_9D_8A_90_D8_99_C4'));//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media images of Coke plastic bottles can be found here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJXPFVO4" target="_blank"&gt;http://media.greenpeace.org/collection/27MZIFJXPFVO4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span&gt;1) &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/05/Bottling-It_FINAL.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/05/Bottling-It_FINAL.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
2) &lt;a href="https://environmentaldefence.ca/2017/10/26/big-bottlers-wont-deal-with-plastic-waste/" target="_blank"&gt;https://environmentaldefence.ca/2017/10/26/big-bottlers-wont-deal-with-plastic-waste/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span&gt; 3) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.canadianbeverage.ca/news-media/press-releases/canadian-beverage-association-statement-regarding-bottled-water/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;span&gt;http://www.canadianbeverage.ca/news-media/press-releases/canadian-beverage-association-statement-regarding-bottled-water/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span&gt;4) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.packaging-gateway.com/comment/coca-colas-refillable-trial-finally-signal-end-plastic-bottles/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;span&gt;http://www.packaging-gateway.com/comment/coca-colas-refillable-trial-finally-signal-end-plastic-bottles/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.coca-colacompany.com/stories/coke-testing-self-serve-water-station-with-flavors-and-bubbles" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.coca-colacompany.com/stories/coke-testing-self-serve-water-station-with-flavors-and-bubbles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span&gt;According to research by the Guardian newspaper approximately one million plastic bottles are bought around the world every minute - and almost half of them are thrown away after a single use, ending up in landfill, in incinerators, and in the oceans.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jun/28/a-million-a-minute-worlds-plastic-bottle-binge-as-dangerous-as-climate-change" target="_blank"&gt; https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jun/28/a-million-a-minute-worlds-plastic-bottle-binge-as-dangerous-as-climate-change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</text><author>Greenpeace Canada</author><imagesA></imagesA><p3_image_gallery>false</p3_image_gallery><pdfFiles><value>http://www.greenpeace.org/canada/Global/canada/report/2017/05/Bottling-It_FINAL.pdf</value></pdfFiles><imagesC></imagesC><date>2018-01-19 00:00:00</date><type>Press Release</type><tags1>Consumption</tags1><categories>Live Sustainably</categories><imagesB></imagesB></item>
</items>